<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[The SuperSonic (Tennis) Fox]]></title>
  <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-14T08:51:28-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://supersonicfox.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mark Fussell]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[One grip to rule them all]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/one-grip-to-rule/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-14T20:40:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/one-grip-to-rule</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I hear a lot of &lsquo;chatter&rsquo; about grips when on the court.  People switching between a and b, c and d, forehand and
 backhand.  Never for any particularly logical reason, but just switching all the same.</p>

<p>I play with a classic (1980s) set of grips: Eastern forehand, Eastern backhand, Continental volley, Less-than-Eastern-Backhand
Forehand slice / serve, and finally Eastern-Forehand backhand slice.  Of these, only the last would be a little
unusual / extreme.  I started with a Continental, but my 4500 RPM backhand is partially possible because I am a bit
more extreme than a Continental.  All of these I may slightly tweak to suit my strokes or the specifics of a particular shot.
But they are clearly my core.  I can also do both right and left-handed two-handed backhands, but that is a different story.</p>

<p>A couple days ago I was working on an aggressive topspin lob on my one-handed backhand.  This is among the hardest strokes
 in the game to me.  I can &lsquo;bullet&rsquo; my backhand trivially.  And can topspin the bullet quite easily too.  But getting a
 ball high up in the air with a lot of spin&hellip; that was not happening for me.</p>

<p>At first I cheated and switched to a two-handed backhand.  Actually, ultimately, this cheat may simply be my solution,
but after cheating a bit, I wanted to figure out what was failing with my one handed backhand.</p>

<h2>Forehand topspin</h2>

<p>My forehand was fine, so I switched back to it and thought about what I was doing.  To control any shot, you must be able
to apply full power and go <em>short</em> and <em>long</em>.  Then all you do is dial in the middle.  On my forehand, I couldn&rsquo;t go
really short, but I could lob and hit the service line, which is about as short as you ever want to go with a real shot.
And I could lob into the other court, which is normally a bit longer than you ever want to go.</p>

<p>OK, so this was better than my backhand.  But wasn&rsquo;t as controlled as I wanted.  Why couldn&rsquo;t I go shorter?  Say lob
and have it land <em>on</em> the net.  I pondered and decided it must be the grip.  So I shifted to a western-ish grip.  And
hit some balls.  Really short.  Like straight at my service line.</p>

<p>I pondered Rafa who has the most extreme topspin I am aware of, and I tried to &ldquo;channel him&rdquo; along with &ldquo;his grip&rdquo;.
Now I had something.  Lots of spin.  Not much power, but definitely a lot of spin.</p>

<p>So what was the advantage compared to the backhand?  The grip?  Actually, no.  The eastern backhand is <em>as extreme</em>
as the western forehand for generating topspin.  I will get to that in a moment.</p>

<p>Basically the advantage came down to the <em>stance</em> and <em>ball contact</em> point.  For my normal, driven, forehand, I hit the ball
and my racket goes forward and up, eventually with my thumb passing over my left ear.  For my &lsquo;Rafa&rsquo; forehand, I hit
the ball and my racket goes almost straight up, with my thumb never even passing my <em>right</em> ear.  For both of these, I
use an open stance.  The first doesn&rsquo;t require it, but the second totally does (or so I believe).</p>

<p>My flaw with my backhand is I was trying to do an upward drive with a closed stance.  And basically up isn&rsquo;t really possible
because your should is already in front based on the stance vs. on the side.</p>

<p>So my ultimate fix to my backhand lob was to open my stance.  Or to two-hand it.  The later still is better to date.</p>

<h2>One grip, Two grip</h2>

<p>A tennis racket grip is an octagon (usually), so grips are primarily based on hand anatomy compared to that octagon.
But one grip is easy to describe in more normal vernacular: the continental.  The continental is also called the &lsquo;shake hand&rsquo;, or
&lsquo;hatchet&rsquo; grip.  If you place your tennis racket on a table so it is &lsquo;slicing&rsquo; the table, the continental is simply shaking
hands with the grip.  Your &lsquo;v&rsquo; will be on top, your fore-finger hand-joint will be to the side, and your thumb and finger tips
will touch-ish on the other side.</p>

<p>If you had to pick <em>one grip</em> to use throughout an entire game, this seems like the obvious one to choose.  Everything
is symmetric, so both forehand and backhand can be hit.  Flat is easy.  Slice is easy.  Topspin is a little hard, but
is possible.</p>

<p>One grip&hellip; to rule them all.</p>

<p>Except it isn&rsquo;t the <em>right grip</em> to rule anyone nowadays.  Probably wasn&rsquo;t even right back in the sixties.  But lets not
dwell.</p>

<h3>The true one grip</h3>

<p>I mentioned my grips above, but swapping in Rafa for some of mine, we get:</p>

<ul>
<li> Western-ish forehand, topspin</li>
<li> Eastern backhand, topspin</li>
<li> Eastern-ish backhand, forehand slice</li>
<li> Western-ish backhand, backhand slice</li>
<li> Eastern-ish backhand, serve</li>
</ul>


<p>Isn&rsquo;t the symmetry above a little suspicious?  Now consider that a Western Forehand and an Eastern Backhand <em>are identical</em> grips (just flipped in motion direction)
and we now have:</p>

<ul>
<li> EB-ish forehand, topspin</li>
<li> EB backhand, topspin</li>
<li> EB-ish forehand, slice</li>
<li> EB-ish backhand, slice</li>
<li> EB-ish backhand, serve</li>
</ul>


<p>So the true one grip is the EB/WF grip.  It is the most extreme spin grip.  It is just kind of hard to &lsquo;wield&rsquo; so people
tend to approach it vs. use it.</p>

<p>And why it is both aweful and awesome is simple to see when you describe how to grip it in normal vernacular.</p>

<p>Put your racket <em>flat</em> on a table.  Now shake hands with it.  Now you have a flyswatter vs. a hatchet.  Awesome!</p>

<p>This hold makes it so your default capability with any ball coming toward you (or simply dropped in the air) is to <em>slice it</em>.
On either side of your body (forehand, backhand).  In either direction (forward, backward).  And even on either side of the racket (bottom strings, top strings).</p>

<p>Slice it eight ways baby :&ndash;)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Time dilation]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/time-dilation/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-11T20:40:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/time-dilation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I stand near the service line (halfway) when I return serve.  People find this unimaginable, even inconceivable.
The ball is coming at 120 MPH and you are standing there?!?!</p>

<p>The answer to how I can stand there has two parts, but the first is basically &lsquo;Time Dilation&rsquo;.  Just like computers
do a lot of things in a short amount of time, you too can do a lot of things in a short amount of time.  You just don&rsquo;t
realize it.  You are operating on &lsquo;slow&rsquo;.</p>

<p>The difference between &lsquo;slow&rsquo; and &lsquo;fast&rsquo; is not the effort, energy, or
speed aspects of what a person does.  It is changing the <em>unit of time</em> at which the person does exactly the same
things you are doing on &lsquo;slow&rsquo;.  So the simplest way to think about this is to adjust time to be in equivalent &lsquo;slow&rsquo; units
vs. thinking the person is doing more in a unit of time.  This is exactly how 120 FPS becomes 30 FPS.</p>

<p>For most people, thinking in &lsquo;tens&rsquo; is the easiest.  So imagine I (or maybe Roger) is operating at 10x the speed of you
on the tennis court.  Where <em>one second</em> passes for you, <em>ten seconds</em> passed for Roger.  Where three tenths of a second
passed for you, three seconds passed for Roger.  You can get a lot done in three seconds!  And have a sip of coffee to
boot.</p>

<p>If you want to see the time dilation in action, just slow down the video of Roger to going at 1/10th its normal speed.
I believe you will see <em>continuous motion</em> at that speed.  Or something really close to it.  Now do the same of some
video of your club matches.  And everyone will look &lsquo;frozen&rsquo;.  That is time dilation.  Mages are in continuous motion at
about 10x the speed of muggles.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[In the rain]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/in-the-rain/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-30T20:40:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/in-the-rain</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It is raining in California.  This is a good thing, because we need a lot of water and we don&rsquo;t have it.  The rain causes my internet to go out (another story),
which is actually enjoyable because the internet is a dangerous drug.  Cold turkey the drug!</p>

<p>It doesn&rsquo;t rain very much in California any more: climate change has caused our weather to be &lsquo;nicer and nicer&rsquo;.  Tennis is played outside, so
tennis benefits from this niceness.  It is hard to not be able to play tennis in California (or at least the Bay Area).</p>

<p>You can certainly play tennis in the rain.  Don&rsquo;t play if you start sliding around, but other than that, there is absolutely nothing preventing playing in the rain. Yes,
the balls will get wet and be no longer Wimbledon quality.  Yes, the racket will get wet and you may have to replace the grip or even the strings.  So what?</p>

<p>Well, for most people, even a drizzle makes them go somewhere else.
On my courts, when I manage to get two-three hours in a day (in the rain or between spells), almost no one else shows up at all.</p>

<h2>Better courts after a rain</h2>

<p>If it has recently rained but is no longer raining, you can get your courts (hard courts) in better shape by leveraging the power of the sun.  The sun is <em>really good</em>
at drying things, but it needs &lsquo;to see&rsquo; the water.  Puddles are not good (can see the top but not below), so you should squeegee puddles and spread them around.  You
can also blow things around with an electric blower, mop with a blanket, push with a broom, etc.</p>

<p>If you get the water spread out, it takes about 15-30 minutes for a wet court to be quite playable.  So you can choose your ball-wetness to wait time.</p>

<p>I rarely wait for much of anything nowadays :&ndash;)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Being a Mage]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/being-a-mage/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-24T20:40:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/being-a-mage</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday I documented what an objective camera showed: I have crazy, top-40 professional, levels of spin and speed in my game.  I might be able to make it all the way to the US Open in New York.
I am 48.  I have only played for eighteen months since taking a thirty year hiatus.  I have a full-ish time job doing something quite sedentary (read software).  This is all quite bizarre.</p>

<p>Well, it is different from &lsquo;normal&rsquo;.  I am a tennis mage.  I learned from John, who is also a tennis mage.  John started at 14 when he earned a racket.  Then he VHS taped all the
great tennis that was out there (McEnroe, Borg, Lendl, Everett, Navratalova, etc.), he went to the court and tried it out, and year-after-year he self-taught himself the actual
magic that is required to do crazy things to a fuzzy yellow ball.  He is a self-taught mage.</p>

<p>Eighteen months ago I decided to start playing tennis with my daughter.  For about nine months, I did something similar to John but only watched one pro: Federer.  I would watch
slow-motion captures of his strokes and read/listen-to analysis of what he did so well.  At the end of nine months, I was not a mage but maybe a 4.x player.</p>

<p>But then I met John, and his wisdom combined with my effort and focus enabled me to become a mage too.  Yesterday I both measured my magic and revealed who I was.  And I did it in my &lsquo;Fox&rsquo; shirt :&ndash;)</p>

<p>Yesterday was a ton of fun, but today I was on the court yet again for about two hours starting at 5:30AM.  Why?  Because I love the magic, and need to practice it
and look for new spells everyday.  Today I worked on &lsquo;checked&rsquo; backhands and forehands.  The &lsquo;checked&rsquo; backhand is critical to returning serves targeting your left leg.
John showed me it the other day, and yesterday a 110 MPH serve targeted my left leg and I hit it.  The leg that is&hellip; so I would like to not do that again.  The &lsquo;checked&rsquo;
forehand is just because it is symmetric.  John didn&rsquo;t mention it, but it is natural.  So are &lsquo;checked&rsquo; slices.  The trajectory of the ball comes off the racket differently,
and that may have been helpful against this crazy kid who had wicked topspin.</p>

<p>So being a mage is not an award&hellip; an honor&hellip; it is a state along a journey.  I know magic and I want to know more.  When there is no more, I may be a bit more bored with tennis.  But maybe not :&ndash;)</p>

<p>Being a mage also tends to make you want to pass it on, so I taught a tiny two year old girl &lsquo;La Ti Da&rsquo; to help her catch a tossed tennis ball :&ndash;)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Wilson Spin Clinic]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/wilson-spin-clinic/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-23T20:40:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/wilson-spin-clinic</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I had an awesome time with adults and kids at a &lsquo;spin clinic&rsquo; hosted by Wilson.  Basically they want to show how swapping in one of their newer rackets makes your shots better.
It was interesting to see other people do it (I was helping retrieve balls, so was effectively &lsquo;receiving&rsquo; and watching pretty closely).  The right way to do this is you hit
your kind of normal 70% game speed balls, swap in a new racket, and compare.  I am not normal, but I did try the &lsquo;normal way&rsquo; and swapped in a wilson racket for my best
HeadMP+Strings+57.  Unfortunately for Wilson, their racket was not better.</p>

<p>But again, I was invited to this by Timi and was there to <em>have fun</em> and <em>be helpful</em>.  For the <em>helpful</em>, I provided  music, fresh orange juice, champagne, and a good ball retriever.
For the <em>fun</em>, I did what any mage would do with a machine like that watching them.  I hit my <em>wickedest</em> shots possible off every ball that was hit my way :&ndash;)  And then
wanted to see my stats.</p>

<p>The numbers:</p>

<ul>
<li> Forehand-Topspin: 2500 RPM</li>
<li> Forehand-Slice:  4500 RPM ! :&ndash;)</li>
<li> Backhand-Topspin: 1500 RPM</li>
<li> Backhand-Slice: 3000 RPM</li>
</ul>


<p>And my favorite number:</p>

<ul>
<li> Furthest travel: 140 feet :&ndash;))</li>
</ul>


<p>I also served, but they were packing up and I didn&rsquo;t really get any numbers for it (too many kinds of serves and only five serves as my quota).</p>

<p>Great day.  And I am headed to Carmel for the Prequalifier for the New Haven Qualifier for the New York Open.  :&ndash;)</p>

<p>Thanks to John for the game and to Steve for keeping my shoulder on.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[El Camino Del Diablo (5)]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/el-camino-del-diablo-5/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-22T20:40:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/el-camino-del-diablo-5</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Continuing the road to the devil&hellip;</p>

<h2>Serve &lsquo;H&rsquo;</h2>

<p>Serve &lsquo;H&rsquo; is the serve this series is actually named after.  It is the &lsquo;Hell&rsquo; serve.  It is my first &ldquo;this is only a jump serve&rdquo;,
but to understand that you need to watch &lsquo;Roger Rabbit&rsquo;.  So go watch that&hellip; I will wait&hellip;</p>

<h3>Flow</h3>

<p>The key to all tennis and martial arts motions is &lsquo;flow&rsquo;.  You flow your body through the motions that you want your body
to do.  But it isn&rsquo;t just any-old-flow.  It is a &ldquo;get real fast&rdquo; and &ldquo;woah horses&rdquo; pair.  It turns out that the &ldquo;woah horses&rdquo;
part is the harder part.  Because you don&rsquo;t really want to halt your horses, you want them to just relax.  To slow down on their
own.  Stop being &lsquo;fast&rsquo; and somehow you will get back to some reasonable velocity.  And by horses&hellip; I really mean &lsquo;Joints and Muscles&rsquo;
because I am pretty sure you don&rsquo;t have horses inside your body.  Even if you are a Unicorn yourself.</p>

<p>I can&rsquo;t teach you here how to become slow.  And slow down.  Please seek John and Steve and my other mages if you want to learn that.
But be aware that slowing down is critical to the road.  If you can slow down, basically without brakes, then you are ready to speed up.
Don&rsquo;t continue until then.</p>

<h3>Coil, Spring</h3>

<p>All real tennis serves are jump serves.  You might not see it visibly, but a jump serve is simply a &ldquo;Coil, Spring&rdquo; serve, which
is the ultimate version of &ldquo;flow&rdquo; ignoring the slow down part I addressed above.</p>

<p>To serve a real serve, you toss the ball, and then <em>immediately</em> go get it.  Coil, Toss, Spring.  I tend to say the &ldquo;Coil&rdquo; to myself in a nice low voice.
Not sure what actor I am channeling for the Coil.  But for the &lsquo;Spring&rsquo; I channel Roger Rabbit (you did see the movie right?  If not, please go back to paragraph-1).</p>

<p>So &ldquo;Cooooiiiiilllll&rdquo; , &ldquo;SPRING!&rdquo;.  &ldquo;Cooooiiiillll&rdquo;, &ldquo;SPRING!&rdquo;.</p>

<p>I actually hit some spectacularly bad serves when I start off, because I am not really ready to &ldquo;SPRING!&rdquo;.  But <em>all</em> my serves have this rhythm.  I jump-serve <em>all</em>
my serves.  The only thing that varies is where the ball is.</p>

<h2>Serve &lsquo;A&rsquo; prime</h2>

<p>The value of Serve &lsquo;A&rsquo; (my flat butterfly serve) is that it is simple.  It has a nice continuous flow, so slowing down is not a problem.  That makes it great
for testing new things out.  A-prime is a test of &ldquo;Toss that ball somewhere crazy&rdquo; and &ldquo;Go get it&rdquo;.</p>

<p>If you have a jump serve, the coil puts your body into a jump-capable position.  So, if you toss the ball somewhere &lsquo;stupid&rsquo; you should be able to jump after
it.  And get to it.  If you can get all this timing right.</p>

<p>Again, I can&rsquo;t help you with all the timing, physical fitness, etc.  Blogs and books aren&rsquo;t a good medium, and I haven&rsquo;t taken
enough time to process all my videos.</p>

<p>But the basic concept is: &ldquo;Toss the ball <em>forward</em> about one foot, and then do &lsquo;Serve A&rsquo; given the ball is there&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Doing this with your &lsquo;A&rsquo; serve likely produces a little more speed on the ball and reduces the amount of time people
have to react to the ball.  You are closer to them.  You hit it faster.  Very obnoxious.</p>

<p>But this is basically the <em>same serve</em> as an &lsquo;A&rsquo;, so I don&rsquo;t label it differently.  It is just a more serious &lsquo;A&rsquo;</p>

<h2>Serve &lsquo;H&rsquo;</h2>

<p>The Hell serve is a different serve from all that preceeded it.  It is actually a jumped &lsquo;C&rsquo; (topspin) serve, but unlike a jumped &lsquo;A&rsquo;
this produces something radically different.  Because you tossed the ball so &lsquo;wrong&rsquo; for a &lsquo;C&rsquo;, when you actually hit the ball,
it similarly comes out &lsquo;wrong&rsquo; and is ridiculously flat.  A proper &lsquo;C&rsquo; is a nice loopy serve.  A proper &lsquo;H&rsquo; is flat.</p>

<p>Until it hits the ground.  When all hell breaks loose.  A proper &lsquo;H&rsquo; has all the top-spin of a &lsquo;C&rsquo; but that is concealed in an &lsquo;A&rsquo; like
trajectory.  When an &lsquo;H&rsquo; hits ground, it transforms into a &lsquo;C&rsquo; and worse, and that ball kicks all over the place.</p>

<p>When I learned &lsquo;H&rsquo; I thought I had been given a gift of the nastiest serve on the planet.</p>

<p>But the letters continue&hellip;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Being Competent]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/being-competent/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-21T20:40:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/being-competent</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Continuing my &lsquo;insanity&rsquo; subtopic, or slightly related to it, I am now going to properly define &lsquo;competent&rsquo;, and explain
how you become competent at something, and how long this takes.  The answer may surprise you because it makes complete
sense, but is not how people normal commonly (incorrectly) define the term.</p>

<p>An important realization is that &lsquo;Competent&rsquo; is <em>completely orthogonal to</em> (independent of, think North-South vs. East-West) &lsquo;Skill&rsquo;.  I am a skilled and competent
tennis player.  I may be a 5.5.  Not totally sure.  Will figure that out at the next tournament.  With competitive sports
it is very hard to become <em>incompetent</em>  If you beat Roger, you are #1.  If you lose to him, you probably are not.  If you
can&rsquo;t even <em>see</em> his serve, you are likely a lot less skilled than Roger.  Almost all sports have this wonderful characteristic:
on game day every one is competent&hellip; or simply in denial.  No incompetency at all.</p>

<p>I am also a highly unskilled and competent brain surgeon.  I will not operate on your brain.  Period.  Just not going to happen.
If we are trapped in the woods and I have to chop off you leg to get you out of a bear trap&hellip; I will first warn you that
I am similarly unskilled as a leg-chopper-offer.  I am competent at it, but you are likely to die if you ask me to do it.</p>

<p>With the second example, you can see that being competent takes <em>absolutely no time</em>!  At all.  None.  Phew!  Thought it
was hard.</p>

<p>Ah&hellip;. but it can be hard.  It gets hard to become competent when you are trapped in being incompetent.  To be incompetent probably takes some amount of time&hellip;
you invested a year or two in improving your tennis game&hellip; and during that time you thought your were getting better and better&hellip; you were sure it was the
case.  An hour here and there&hellip; adds up to 100 hours&hellip; over five years, maybe 500 hours&hellip; You put in all time, so you must be &lsquo;Good&rsquo;.</p>

<p>But that is delusional.  You aren&rsquo;t good because your put in time.  One becomes good by progressing through failure.  Over&hellip; and over&hellip; and over&hellip;
Playing 500 hours of club tennis makes you as skilled in tennis as&hellip; have no idea.  But <em>you can</em> figure it out.  Find a 4.0 and play them.
Oh&hellip; they might be incompetent too and are really a 3.0?  Yes.  That is the said part.  If you get enough incompetent people together,
you have no clue.</p>

<p>That is why I am going to a spin-clinic tomorrow, why I have nine go-pros, and why I am going to a true &ldquo;Kill each other&rdquo; kind of Open in the spring.
Because I know I am not incompetent&hellip; but I have no idea what my skill level <em>really is</em>.  I don&rsquo;t care very much, but I am curious.</p>

<p>Never going to be even a moderately skilled brain surgeon.  Never is enough for that one.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[El Camino Del Diablo (4)]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/el-camino-del-diablo-4/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-19T20:40:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/el-camino-del-diablo-4</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Continuing the road to the devil&hellip;</p>

<h2>Serve &lsquo;F&rsquo;</h2>

<p>Serve &lsquo;E&rsquo; does not make a lot of sense as an actual serve, but it is highly useful in a game.  If you hit a ball
to me at about should height, you will get a snap serve back.  Basically serve &lsquo;E&rsquo; but with a snap (to be explained later).
Actually, at this point, if you hit a ball to me above my waist-line you may get a snap serve back.  You probably will
not like that&hellip; but I digress.</p>

<p>Serve &lsquo;F&rsquo; is a pure slice.  Again, you must leverage the fact that you are a box and make sure the ball is in the <em>back</em>
of the box and generally a bit higher than your head.  Then you slice it just like you did with &lsquo;E&rsquo;.  Very nice slice.
You must put everything you can into slicing that ball to really see how wonderful a serve this is.  And after you
have done all of that, I will show you more.</p>

<h2>Serve &lsquo;G&rsquo;</h2>

<p>Serve &lsquo;G&rsquo; is among the most fun serves to do as well as the most useless in an actual game.  To do a &lsquo;G&rsquo; serve, your
racket is parallel to the ground.  Yes, facing down.  If you get better it is facing down and <em>backward</em>.</p>

<p>The goal of the &lsquo;G&rsquo; serve is to produce <em>maximum spin</em> with <em>minimal ball travel</em>.  A perfect &lsquo;G&rsquo; does not travel forward
at all.  The ball simply rises up in the air, hits the ground, and goes backward from where you are standing.  You are
slicing the air with your racket, and the ball just happens to be there to feel the slice.  If another person was there&hellip;
well&hellip; they wouldn&rsquo;t be very happy.</p>

<p>As with all serves, you should be able to put everything you have into this serve.  Yesterday I was measured to produce about 800 watts per arm,
and I put 800 watts into Serve &lsquo;G&rsquo;.  &lsquo;G&rsquo; is awesome.  And useless.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[MRP]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/MRP/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-17T20:40:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/MRP</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Continuing my &lsquo;insanity&rsquo; subtopic, this one is about how the world really works.  Again, assuming you are not going
to actually physically threaten me, there is a simply progression to how you can gain power over me.  You need:</p>

<ul>
<li> Money</li>
<li> Relationship</li>
</ul>


<p>to get to the first level that I will call &lsquo;Influence&rsquo;.  Yes, Money could be something other than actual money, but that would
require you to know I like (for example) mangoes, gnocchi, and aquatic plants.  So to keep things simple, assume it is money.
How much money?  <em>A lot</em> of money.  Like tens of thousands of dollars.  With that you have my attention.  Others might
be a bit less&hellip; and others might be even more.  Money alone won&rsquo;t work on me though, you have to have some kind of
relationship with me.  I have to know you and what your goals in general are.  The stronger the relationship, the
smaller the money might have to be.  Or leveraging the relationship you might realize aquatic plants are very valuable to me.</p>

<p>OK, so you now have &lsquo;Influence&rsquo;&hellip; how do you get &lsquo;Power&rsquo; over me?  That part is simple too.  You need to have a Purpose.
For you.  For me.  For the Money.  For the Relationship.</p>

<p>So in total you need:</p>

<ul>
<li> Money</li>
<li> Relationship</li>
<li> Purpose</li>
</ul>


<p>and if those are compelling to me, you have a lot of power over me.  I will do a lot of things for you.</p>

<h2>Politics and Lemmings</h2>

<p>Venturing even further off from tennis.  I live in a country that is basically insane.  People go vote every couple
years where voting <em>in no way</em> involves any of the above.  Voting is &ldquo;cute&rdquo; but to actually impact things, you need</p>

<ul>
<li> Money</li>
<li> Relationship</li>
<li> Purpose</li>
</ul>


<p>and I am pretty sure no voting booth on the planet ever provided any of the above to any politician or political seat.
And then to make things worse, these insane American voters then go onto Facebook and banter with all <em>their friends</em>
about how bad things are.  But again, none of that is doing MRP with the people that could actually change anything.</p>

<p>But they keep doing it year after year&hellip; election after election&hellip; instead of simply doing MRP.  Sigh.  Lemmings.  Insane lemmings.  Except they are the norm.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ROIC]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/ROIC/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-16T20:40:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/ROIC</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Continuing my &lsquo;insanity&rsquo; subtopic, and venturing even further from Tennis, I am going to help you optimize you life even more.
Insanely great people interact with each other in only four ways:</p>

<ul>
<li> Requests</li>
<li> Offers</li>
<li> Information</li>
<li> Commitments</li>
</ul>


<p>These aren&rsquo;t the only ways people can interact with each other (we are amazingly good at coercing and killing each other),
but if two mages or power players interact with each other, these are the only tools they need as long as life and limb
is not on the line.  These don&rsquo;t just make you a better person (say morally), they make you an incredibly optimized person that is
much more productive because fewer things are &ldquo;in the air&rdquo; in your life.</p>

<h2>Requests</h2>

<p>Requests are simply what they sound like.  I would like a drive to the airport.  I would like you to buy a five million dollar house.
Amazingly, I have made both those requests in my life (the latter more recent&hellip; I can generally get to the airport on my own).
You might think asking someone to put $5MM into a house is a pretty bizarre and misguided thing&hellip; but it was simply a
request.  The person (&ldquo;S&rdquo;) didn&rsquo;t have to do it if he didn&rsquo;t want to, and I gave &ldquo;S&rdquo; enough information to understand
why I made the request even though that is totally optional.  As long as &lsquo;no&rsquo; is fine, it is simply a request.  &ldquo;S&rdquo; ultimately
did not buy the five million dollar house because it did not match his goals at the time.</p>

<h2>Offers</h2>

<p>Offers are again simply what they sound like.  I offer bread to people pretty much every week (the bread is from Manressa, so it
is not ordinary bread).  I have offered my house to people.  Offered my car to a nephew.  Offered to hook people up to this likes of George Lucas.
Offered to sell people my tennis racquets.  Offered to loan people my ball machine.</p>

<p>Strangely offers are commonly not taken.  I can&rsquo;t really explain that.</p>

<h2>Information</h2>

<p>Again, information is just information.  Things I think, experienced, believe, or maybe even &lsquo;know&rsquo; that you might be interested in.
Information can support the two above or it can be just for the fun of exchanging information.</p>

<h2>Commitments</h2>

<p>Offers are inherently commitments.  They can have a time limit (I will sell you my racquet, but it expires on Friday when I have to
pay for it myself), but barring that, commitments must be fulfilled or this system does not work.  Living up to your commitments
may seem onerous, but as soon as your commit to committing, it is actually a relief.  You <em>must</em> do it.  People can&rsquo;t
dissuade you.  You can&rsquo;t dissuade yourself.  Just do it.  Except if it involves the taking of lives&hellip;. unless you are
really up to that level :&ndash;/</p>

<h2>Example</h2>

<p>I recently offered two tables to a robotics tournament.  I forget if I got an acceptance of the offer, but I brought the two tables
and put them into the building for people to use.  I set up one of the tables myself, and left the other for other uses.
At the end of the day, I retrieved the one I set up, but could not find the other one after many minutes of looking for it.</p>

<p>Instead of being annoyed, I simply did the ROIC part again.  I explained the table situation.  Requested that if they find my marked
table when tearing down the event, that they put it outside the building.  And committed to picking it up later that evening.</p>

<p>I returned at about 8PM, scrounged around, but no table.  So I am down a table and need to buy a new one if I still need two.</p>

<p>Yes, I could email people about the missing table&hellip; but I don&rsquo;t care to waste my time on that.  Yes, I could be annoyed about
losing something of value&hellip; but again I don&rsquo;t care to waste my time on that.  Finally&hellip; Yes, I could have emailed someone <em>before</em>
trying to pick up the table&hellip; but that would cause a stall in the system (my system) and I did not want to waste time/energy on that.</p>

<p>I made Offers, Requests, Commitments, and provided Information.  And as of this blog posting&hellip; I am completely done with the event.</p>

<p>But maybe someone will return my table later in my life.  And then I will thank them.  So it is really ROICT.</p>

<p>&mdash;Mark</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pong-Ping]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/pong-ping/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-14T20:40:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/pong-ping</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This site is meant to be primarily about Tennis, and more accidentally about other things.
But today I had a conversation that is more about other things and only somewhat about tennis,
so I guess this post stretches the boundary of this blog a bit.</p>

<h2>Insanity</h2>

<p>Insanity is doing things that you have enough evidence to know <em>will not work</em> but yet you still do them.
That should be the only good definition of the word: you try something, it fails, you try again, it fails, yet
you keep doing exactly the same thing expecting it to succeed.  That is a useful word
and would be helpful to most of the planet if they learned it.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, most people prefer a different definition of insanity, which is basically equivalent to &ldquo;Not like &lsquo;normal&rsquo; people&rdquo;.
This is not a very useful concept because it is pejorative.  &ldquo;Awesome!&rdquo; good word.  &ldquo;Amazing!&rdquo; good word.  &ldquo;Insane!&rdquo; meaning not normal&hellip; useless negative word.
Unless you consider it to be a humbler version of the two definitions preceding it.</p>

<p>So now that I have explained my understanding of the word &ldquo;insane&rdquo;, I will actually accept my last definition and say simply &ldquo;I am insane&rdquo;.
I do things <em>very differently</em> from &lsquo;normal&rsquo; people.  My insanity makes my incredibly productive.  Beyond most
people&rsquo;s conception of &lsquo;productive&rsquo;.</p>

<p>You may or may not want to follow my lead, but I have now committed to explaining it.</p>

<h2>Pong-Ping</h2>

<p>If you have read my book <a href="http://SlumsOfPaloAlto.com/">http://SlumsOfPaloAlto.com/</a>, you know a bit about the sequences of startups I have participated in.  The first four were relatively
soft participations in the management, the fifth was my own (lost a lot of money), and the sixth through tenth were me trying
to focus on executing what I was clearly good at while learning a bit more about the other aspects of the company.</p>

<p>For the first of these five, I joined Jerry Kaplan (<a href="http://www.google.com/?gws_rd=ssl#q=jerry+kaplan">http://www.google.com/?gws_rd=ssl#q=jerry+kaplan</a>) at his startup <a href="http://winster.com">http://winster.com</a>.
There are different kinds of Entrepreneurs, and Jerry would commonly be called an &lsquo;Optimizer&rsquo;.  This is a very useful skill
when things are running very smoothly, so a lot of Jerry&rsquo;s skills would help you have a more optimized life.</p>

<p>One of the critical things Entrepreneurs have to do is <em>raise money</em>.  Potentially lots of money ideally from people you barely know,
so these people need to investigate you quite a bit before deciding to give you money.  And these people are commonly very busy.
Some could take months to get back to you (even when you are Jerry), so you have to be patient.  Also these people do not like
to be &lsquo;pestered&rsquo;, so you don&rsquo;t have to poke them many times.  Poke once and then wait.  Poke many different people to hopefully get
a positive response from someone.</p>

<p>You might consider this to be &lsquo;Ping&rsquo; them and they &lsquo;Pong&rsquo; you back.  So it is a game of Ping-Pong.</p>

<p>But that is not optimal <em>if</em> there are many interactions with these people.  Or it makes the rhythm misleading for the truly optimal
interaction.  Any time you get a &lsquo;Pong&rsquo; you should ASAP &lsquo;Ping&rsquo;.  &lsquo;Pong&rsquo;&ndash;&lsquo;Ping&rsquo;&hellip; pong-ping&hellip;.. pong-ping&hellip;. pong-ping&hellip;</p>

<p>If you rush as soon as you get a Pong, the other person has the ball again and it is up to them to Pong you again.  There is
now <em>nothing</em> you can do&hellip; which is incredibly relieving.</p>

<h2>Pong-Ping <em>everything</em></h2>

<p>I gave the VC cycle as an example, but this actually works for <em>absolutely</em> everything that needs to get done.  Consider
any request from someone this way and you can get it out of your hair (or brain) almost instantly.  I was recently contacted
by McDonalds and responded within five minutes.  It was a completely composed response, which would have been hard for me
to do that quickly a couple decades ago, but the core process was identical:</p>

<ul>
<li> Receive Pong</li>
<li> Read Pong</li>
<li> Decide whether to kill the Pong (trash it)</li>
<li> If going to Ping, do it immediately.  Might take a day or two.  Or you might have to break it into smaller tasks and do one then <em>pong yourself</em></li>
</ul>


<p>And you are done.  It really works for pretty much everything and means you have nothing looming over you undone.  Everything is done, pinged, and you are free to
get new Pongs.  Even from yourself :&ndash;)</p>

<p>The site <a href="http://FixYourMom.com">http://FixYourMom.com</a> went from idea conceived at the lunch table to live in less than four hours based on Pong-Ping!  And during that time I was mostly doing other things!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Unboxed Boxes]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/unboxed-boxes/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-25T20:40:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/unboxed-boxes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I do not want you to be &lsquo;Boxed&rsquo;, to be constrained by artificial constraints or limitations you believe exist but
have never verified or actively chosen.  I hate that kind of boxing and a huge part of SOPA <a href="http://SlumsOfPaloAlto.com/">http://SlumsOfPaloAlto.com/</a>
is getting people to recognize the boxing that occurs and get rid of it in themselves and others.</p>

<p>On the other hand, you must recognize that you are a box&hellip; at least pretty close to a box&hellip; physically.</p>

<h2>Quadrants around Boxes</h2>

<p>Previously I described the quadrants around your body, but in that I treated you as if you were a <em>point</em> in
space.  But looking down at you, your left and right shoulders are clearly visible as different things.  Assuming
you swing your arms vertically in a circle around your shoulders, you form a box: your right swinging arm on the right of you,
and your left swinging on the left of you.</p>

<p>To get to your ultimate game, you have to let the ball (or position yourself to enable the ball to) get to racket-side
of this box.</p>

<h3>Volleys</h3>

<p>For example, a backhand volley is innately <em>easier</em> than a forehand volley because you have both: &ldquo;Get to the ball soon&rdquo;
combined with &ldquo;Hit it on the racket-side of the box&rdquo;.  You rotate your body for a backhand and your racket is automatically
close to the net.  Actually pretty much everything is <em>easier</em> for your backhand, because of this &lsquo;box&rsquo; rotation.  The
only thing that is harder are the strokes that rely on lots of rotation, because you inherently don&rsquo;t need to, so don&rsquo;t
practice, rotational backhands.</p>

<p>People actually comment on my backhand more than almost anything else about my game.  I do like my one-handed-bullet-and-pretty-much-whatever-I-want
backhand, but it isn&rsquo;t my best shot.  It just isn&rsquo;t &ldquo;weak&rdquo;: I hit it as well as a backhand can be hit.  But most people
fear their backhands and so they avoid and don&rsquo;t practice it.  My model is simply &ldquo;Hit my weakest shot&rdquo; and over time
that rotates around and all my shots are &ldquo;my weakest shot&rdquo;&hellip; that makes you <em>very dangerous</em> when your weakest shot
is the shot that everyone complements you on.</p>

<h3>Forehand Slice</h3>

<p>The box is the most frustrating when dealing with forehand slices, including forehand volleys.  You want to hit the ball&hellip; soon&hellip; right now!&hellip;
but no&hellip; you must wait for it to enter your box and almost <em>leave it</em> out the right/rear side of the box.  Slices hit
late can actually be fine with the right grip, but power slices hit early in the box just fly off the court :&ndash;(  Very frustrating
and likely to make you want to hit <em>even earlier</em> which is exactly the wrong reaction.  Be patient!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[El Camino Del Diablo (3)]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/el-camino-del-diablo-3/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-24T20:40:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/el-camino-del-diablo-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Continuing the road to the devil&hellip;</p>

<h2>Serve &rsquo;D&#8217;</h2>

<p>I have no second serves&hellip;. except for one.  It isn&rsquo;t always a second serve, but it&rsquo;s purpose is to relieve me.  Relief
is very useful when you are stressed.  And although I am a pretty laid-back tennis player outwardly, I can get very
annoyed at myself and my inadequacies.</p>

<p>How inadequate?  Well for many <em>months</em> I couldn&rsquo;t manage to toss the ball properly.  Toss&hellip;. toss&hellip; toss&hellip; In club
tennis you can pretty much just keep tossing because people don&rsquo;t play with a time limit.  But eventually I would
just get annoyed and not want to stop play.  So I would hit the one serve I practiced more than any other until
about month-nine.  A drop forehand.  Simply hit.</p>

<h3>A Forehand?</h3>

<p>Yes, a drop forehand is perfectly legal.  It is also very relieving because it is something so practiced that you
just &ldquo;do it&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Actually now I can do some pretty powerful &rsquo;D&#8217; serves, but the goal isn&rsquo;t to win, it is just to get the ball in play.
It does that very nicely.</p>

<p>And some of my partners have even been aced by it!</p>

<h2>Serve &lsquo;E&rsquo;</h2>

<p>Serve &lsquo;E&rsquo; had the most strange development of all my serves, and ultimately it developed all the way to
obsolescence.  I do not use it at all any more&hellip; I don&rsquo;t even practice it any more&hellip; but my <em>entire</em>
touch game is based on understanding this &ldquo;serve&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Serve &lsquo;E&rsquo; is a slice done shoulder-height.  You toss the ball out into quadrant I at approximately 45-degrees and you
slice it.  And by slice, I mean every essence of your mind is thinking and <em>most</em> of your body
is doing &lsquo;slice&rsquo;, &lsquo;perpendicular&rsquo;, &lsquo;rotations&rsquo;, &lsquo;insane&rsquo;, etc.</p>

<h3>Step-1</h3>

<p>Step-1 is just getting the idea that the ball is out in quadrant-1 and you are slicing it.  If you
instinctively get really good at Step-1, the ball barely moves forward.  Ultimately I think I did things
in slightly the wrong order and serve &lsquo;G&rsquo; would have been better to focus on first, but this is a minor
nuance because both serves are really about understanding &lsquo;Step-2&rsquo; so you can go back to &lsquo;Step-1&rsquo; and
get it right.</p>

<h3>Step-2</h3>

<p>The problem with Step-1 is you don&rsquo;t have faith.  If every part of your body is dedicated to slicing, the
ball does not go forward&hellip; at all.  It just spins in place.</p>

<p>So we need the ball to go forward but your arm isn&rsquo;t going to be helping.  But above I didn&rsquo;t say <em>all</em>, I said <em>most</em>.
The part of your body that will make the go forward is the one part that can&rsquo;t help with slice.  Your legs and hips.
These we need to rotate.  Rotate forcefully enough to propel a ball forward over the net.</p>

<p>That isn&rsquo;t actually that hard: attach a racket to your hips and you can serious hit a ball.  But you need to seriously
rotate.</p>

<p>In my case John first made me toss a ball a bit too far away and rotate with my right leg stretched out&hellip; spinning
like a top around the left foot.  This may have helped me start thinking right, but it lasted only a week.  The
next week I was to keep my right foot in and think more like &lsquo;Flying Superman&rsquo; with my bodies and limbs (except the
left leg keeping me in the air)&hellip; but the rotation was still there.</p>

<p>The reasons for the spin are (a) to get contact with the ball that will propel it forward, (b) to make insane slice
easier (effectively the ball is moving toward you by you spinning and that is easier to slice than not-moving), and
&copy; to get your body out of the way of the insane power slicing racket.</p>

<h3>Step-3</h3>

<p>Now combine Step-2 back with Step-1 and make sure to still do Step-2 to get your lower body helping out,
but focus on Step-1 and <em>slice</em> the ball where that is all your slice is about&hellip; slice.  rotations&hellip;
insane rotations&hellip;</p>

<p>The toss is still about 45 degrees into Quadrant-I, but it will be pretty close to your body&hellip;
about a forearms length out.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Quadrants]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/quadrants/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-22T20:40:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/quadrants</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Quadrants</h2>

<p>Serving can be simplified into &lsquo;toss ball&rsquo;, &lsquo;hit ball&rsquo;.  You can have one serve or a dozen, but all of them have this
core rhythm.  If you do have a dozen serves, they do not &ldquo;all work&rdquo; with every kind of toss.  I have an underhand slice
serve that starts with me dropping the ball right in front of me&hellip; very hard to hit top-spin on that one.  I would even
say &lsquo;Inconceivable&rsquo;.</p>

<p>To understand the toss, it can be helpful to think of yourself in the middle of the universe.  Where is your body?
And relative to that body, where is that ball?</p>

<p>Assuming you have only overhead serves, then the ball better be &lsquo;up&rsquo;.  But &ldquo;up where?&rdquo;.</p>

<h3>Four Quadrants</h3>

<p>In plane geometry there are four quadrants going from I (1) to IV (4):
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quadrant_(plane_geometry)">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quadrant_(plane_geometry)</a>.  If you consider your body as the center of the universe,
and you are right-handed, your relative quadrants match the geometry ones exactly.  If you are left-handed, please
flip the even/odd ones.</p>

<p>So there are four quadrants around your body, and the ball is always in one of them (or on a line, but let&rsquo;s not be
picky about that).  So where is it?  And where should it be?  The obvious answer is &ldquo;It depends&rdquo;.</p>

<h3>Different serves, different quadrants</h3>

<p>For my butterfly, flat, &lsquo;A&rsquo; serve, I contact in &lsquo;I&rsquo;.  My body rotates so my right shoulder is forward (parallel to the baseline plus or minus)
before contact, which basically guarantees I have to hit in &lsquo;I&rsquo;.  The ballistic serve &lsquo;B&rsquo; is behind me, so in either &lsquo;IV&rsquo; or maybe
&lsquo;III&rsquo;.  And &lsquo;C&rsquo; is a top-spin serve, so you want to be mostly going &lsquo;up&rsquo; and that means the ball is in &lsquo;III&rsquo;.</p>

<p>Note that the quadrants exist <em>all the time</em> and if your body is moving, the quadrants are changing because of your
movement.  Later I will explain my &lsquo;hell&rsquo; serve, which is basically a serve that you toss deep into &lsquo;I&rsquo; and then get your
body in the right spot to hit top spin on it: i.e. &lsquo;III&rsquo;.</p>

<h3>Proper ball position</h3>

<p>The quadrants are a great way to start being aware of &lsquo;proper ball position&rsquo;.  There are others too, but
lets stop with this for the moment.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[El Camino Del Diablo (2)]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/el-camino-del-diablo-2/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-11T20:40:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/el-camino-del-diablo-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Continuing the road to the devil&hellip;</p>

<h2>Serve &lsquo;C&rsquo;</h2>

<p>Again, the serves are alphabetical on the time that John or I came up with them.  After understanding the ballistic serve &lsquo;B&rsquo;,
we returned to a more normal top-spin serve &lsquo;C&rsquo;.  This turns out to be both one of the most useful serves if you want to &lsquo;win&rsquo;
or just &lsquo;have fun&rsquo; (without blowing people&rsquo;s minds like &lsquo;B&rsquo; does).</p>

<p>Serve &lsquo;C&rsquo; is also amongst the most complex of the serves until we get into the hell range.</p>

<p>To serve an &lsquo;A&rsquo;, your racket comes
up from behind, hits the ball in front of you (quadrant &lsquo;I&rsquo; if you look down on your body <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quadrant_(plane_geometry)">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quadrant_(plane_geometry)</a>)
and then finishes into quadrant &lsquo;III&rsquo;.  So for a right-handed person the racket ends to the left of your left leg.  At
least to me, this all seems very natural and I can do a butterfly movement all day long where the racket starts in &lsquo;I&rsquo;,
goes down and back into &lsquo;IV&rsquo;, then goes up and back into &lsquo;III&rsquo;, over the top
to hit the ball in &lsquo;I&rsquo;, and then back down briefly through &lsquo;II&rsquo; into &lsquo;III&rsquo;
and then comes back up to the start in &lsquo;I&rsquo; to do it all again.  Part of my warm-up is swinging those butterflies.</p>

<p>If you move the ball more to the left and on top of you, and swing an &lsquo;A&rsquo; you might think you get a &lsquo;C&rsquo;, but that is not a &lsquo;C&rsquo;,
it is just a kind of weird &lsquo;A&rsquo;.  &lsquo;C&rsquo; is really about understanding your rotator cuff <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rotator_cuff">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rotator_cuff</a>, which is an impressive and potentially fragile
set of muscles that connect your arm to your body.  If you google &lsquo;rotator cuff&rsquo;, the first entries are about injuries!  So
please talk with a coach before <em>trying</em> anything I am describing.  I am not a doctor!  Don&rsquo;t <em>trust me with your body</em></p>

<p>So how is &lsquo;C&rsquo; related to the rotator cuff?  I will show you!</p>

<p>With a racket in hand, stick whichever arm you serve with straight out from your body.  Like the lower arms of this: <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leonardo_da_Vinci#mediaviewer/File:Da_Vinci_Vitruve_Luc_Viatour.jpg">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leonardo_da_Vinci#mediaviewer/File:Da_Vinci_Vitruve_Luc_Viatour.jpg</a>.
Now have the racket face upward (your palm forward depending on grip).  The face of the racket should be forward, toward the net.
Now rotate just your shoulder so the racket is downward and the face of the racket is now to facing the fence.  About 180 degrees of rotation.
Do that a few times to get the feel of it.  You can enlarge it a bit to get more than 180 degrees too, but that core 180 degrees
is the core of how &lsquo;C&rsquo; is very different from &lsquo;A&rsquo;.</p>

<p>After practicing sideways, practice the same move with your arm vertical.  The racket starts facing the net over your head, and ends facing the fence and away
from your body.  John calls this a &lsquo;helicopter&rsquo;.  Some other people call it &lsquo;whipping a wet diaper&rsquo;.  This helicopter move
imparts a lot of racket velocity: I can actually serve quite nicely using it alone (back to being &lsquo;to the side&rsquo;).  And
that extra velocity is very effective for producing spin.  Eventually tennis becomes all-about-the-spin: velocities are
so high that <em>going faster</em> will simply <em>go outer</em>.  But <em>spinning faster</em> will stay in and drive people crazy.</p>

<h3>Wrong-side</h3>

<p>OK, so you take an &lsquo;A&rsquo;, add the helicopter, and toss the ball slightly more left and on top of you, and you get a &lsquo;C&rsquo;.  That is
most of the basics of a &lsquo;C&rsquo; except for one major issue&hellip; where does the racket <em>go</em> after you hit that ball?  With an &lsquo;A&rsquo; the racket
went forward and veering to the &lsquo;III&rsquo; quadrant (left of left-leg for a right hander) is natural.  With a &lsquo;C&rsquo; you just flipped
your racket way to the right and quadrant &lsquo;III&rsquo; is no where close.</p>

<p>Well, if &lsquo;III&rsquo; is gone, the only thing left is &lsquo;IV&rsquo;, so that is where you have to finish.  Except &lsquo;IV&rsquo; is where your other leg is!
Don&rsquo;t wack it!  It isn&rsquo;t pleasant!</p>

<p>You need to get that leg out of the way to do a real &lsquo;C&rsquo;, and because of rotational aspects and other dynamics, the best place to put
it is further away (up) in &lsquo;IV&rsquo;.  So the racket goes below your outstretched leg, which gives it enough time to slow down.</p>

<h3>What?</h3>

<p>So &lsquo;C&rsquo; is really quite complex and I probably can&rsquo;t explain it well without photos (maybe later), but I wanted to get
something down on paper to start with.  If you practice the helicopter to your side and above, you will begin to
understand the &lsquo;C&rsquo;.  That is a good start.  Just keep your shoulder attached while you do it :&ndash;)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[El Camino Del Diablo]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/el-camino-del-diablo/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-19T20:40:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/el-camino-del-diablo</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As I have mentioned before, I <em>do not</em> have a second serve.  For nine or more months I worked on a single
serve that was meant to be as close as possible to Federer&rsquo;s flat-ish serve.  That was my model.  I served
it twice.  No second serve, just a first serve served twice.  I failed a lot.  And over time I became pretty
insanely great with that model.  At least insanely great for a 50-year old geezer :&ndash;)</p>

<p>After I managed to have a reasonable serve, which I simply named &lsquo;A&rsquo;, I was willing to consider other serves.
To really get a strong beach-hold on &lsquo;A&rsquo; I ultimately needed a coach (John) and John was very generous with
offering me &ldquo;Other Serves&rdquo;.  Again, none of these are a second serve, they are just &ldquo;different serves&rdquo;.  John
is very scientific and intelligent and pretty much insanely great at teaching people about tennis.  If they
want to listen.  To his insanity.  Which it isn&rsquo;t.</p>

<h2>Serve &lsquo;A&rsquo;</h2>

<p>So as of about March, 2014, I had one serve:</p>

<ul>
<li> A: Full Power Serve.  Hit relatively flatly, arm finishes to my left, and I am right handed.</li>
</ul>


<p>Serve &lsquo;A&rsquo; seems straightforward, and it is.  But serving is anything but straightforward.  Learning to springboard, learning
to handle any kind of toss, and even learning to toss a fuzzy yellow ball&hellip; all of these things seem simple but they aren&rsquo;t.
So &lsquo;A&rsquo; lets you worry about things other than &ldquo;How do I hit thee?  Let me count the ways!&rdquo;.</p>

<p>For quite a while, I refused to learn a different serve because I didn&rsquo;t really get &lsquo;A&rsquo;, so didn&rsquo;t want to be distracted by
something different.</p>

<p>But one fine Friday, I said the fateful words, &ldquo;John, I am ready to learn another serve&rdquo;.  That was the birth of &lsquo;B&rsquo;&hellip;</p>

<h2>Serve &lsquo;B&rsquo;</h2>

<p>My serves are simply &lsquo;in-order&rsquo; alphabetically, but sometimes coincidences occur.  Serve &lsquo;B&rsquo; is also my &lsquo;Ballistic&rsquo; serve.
It is an insane serve from John, and witnessed by me when I said &ldquo;I am ready&rdquo;.  To serve &lsquo;B&rsquo; you have to let the fuzzy
yellow ball fall <em>behind</em> you.  And by behind you, I mean <em>way behind you</em>.  You are still headed forward but that ball is going
backward.</p>

<p>And you are patient right?  You must be patient!  For eventually that ball will be behind you enough to hit &lsquo;B&rsquo;.  &lsquo;B&rsquo; is hit up
into the air and it lands in the service box (if you are so lucky) and bounces&hellip;. and is never to be seen again.  At its best
&lsquo;B&rsquo; leaves the court after that bounce.  One bounce&hellip; one kill.</p>

<p>The crazy thing about great shots is they commonly don&rsquo;t work how you think they do.  To hit a &lsquo;B&rsquo; you don&rsquo;t hit &ldquo;up&rdquo; at all.  &lsquo;B&rsquo;
is among the crazy slice family.  You put incredibly amount of spin on a ball, and because of its position, that spin does
incredibly things to a ball.  As I mentioned, <em>you</em> are going forward.  Ignoring the movement of your racket, as long
as you are going forward, you will impart forward kinetic energy to the ball.  Effectively <em>your body language</em> hit the
ball into the service box.  Now your racket is free!</p>

<p>A freed racket is a marvelous thing, and &lsquo;B&rsquo; takes that freedom to solely produce &lsquo;kick&rsquo;.  The ball lands&hellip; it &lsquo;kicks&rsquo;&hellip;
it is gone!</p>

<p>Returning a &lsquo;B&rsquo; is a different topic, but understanding a &lsquo;B&rsquo; is a gateway to understanding the insanity of &lsquo;slice&rsquo;.  Which
is incredibly awesome!!!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[La Ti Da!]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/la-ti-da/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-12T20:40:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/la-ti-da</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A simple organization around doing any physical activity is:</p>

<ul>
<li>Form: The maneuvers of your body, muscles, joints, etc. that you use to cary out the activity</li>
<li>Fitness: How strong and fit you are at doing the above form</li>
<li>Timing: How you do things at the right time to be successful (or better) at the activity</li>
<li>Mentality: What you think when doing the activity (beyond Form and Timing)</li>
</ul>


<p>This post is specifically on the third of the above: &lsquo;Timing&rsquo;.  How do you get the right timing for the various
strokes and activities you have in tennis?</p>

<p>In music, being aware of timing is basically innate to both you and the activity.
You can use a metronome to produce a consistent &lsquo;beat&rsquo;, and you can easily
hear the different speeds.  Percussion instruments (which include the Piano), are
the most obvious of all the musical instruments.  And this obviousness almost
certainly makes timing easier (on the one hand) and more awesome (consider a drumline or a great pianist)
on the other hand.  Tennis players do not have the awesome timing of a great drummer.
Or do they?  And if they do, how did they get it?</p>

<h2>Grunt! or Ha!</h2>

<p>The answer to awesome depends on what you think of service returns and rapid volleying.  I will
tend to stay with service returns as I consider them to be the most visibly awesome aspect in
tennis, and I believe I can produce visuals to help describe &lsquo;what is going on&rsquo;.</p>

<p>To start at the beginning, I will start with the simplest of timing.  When do you hit the ball?  How do you know?
There are two good answers:</p>

<ul>
<li> I know because I just saw me hit the ball I was watching it</li>
<li> I know because I heard the ball hit the racket  I was listening to it</li>
</ul>


<p>Of these, the first is a little more reliable: light travels faster, and background noise does not impede it.  Strangely though,
the route to great timing is more likely based on the latter: our brains are very sound-timing oriented compared to
our vision.  If sound entered your ear/s only 30 times per second, you would be <em>very disturbed</em>.
Your brain doesn&rsquo;t like that.  Your brain works with sound <em>much faster</em> than 30 times per second, and it is
very good at telling the distance between those sounds (that distance-between-sound is basically the definition of &lsquo;pitch&rsquo;).</p>

<p>So although it is import to watch the ball, and your brain does work with the information, ideally you would always
have both &lsquo;I can see it&rsquo; and &lsquo;I can hear it&rsquo;.  If the ball made no sound when it hits your racket, simply make the
 sound for it.  In my case I &lsquo;grunt&rsquo; when I hit a ball at my fullest.  But when I am playing softer, I say/think something
 like &lsquo;Ha!&rsquo;.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t actually think &lsquo;Ha!&rsquo; because I have a different word, but John recommends &lsquo;Ha!&rsquo; and so I do too.  John is a better
coach than me :&ndash;)</p>

<h2>A! Ah!</h2>

<p>OK, so you watch the ball as you hit it with your racket, and you made a &lsquo;Ha!&rsquo; at the moment of contact.  That is kind of the
start to awesome timing, but not really.  There is no &lsquo;time&rsquo; involved, just a moment-in-time.  We need &lsquo;time&rsquo; to get &lsquo;timing&rsquo;.</p>

<p>To get the most basic form of time, you need two moments.  The &lsquo;Ha!&rsquo; is the second moment: you hit the ball.  Not much more to do than
that on that current ball (although maybe&hellip;)  So you need the first moment&hellip; the &lsquo;A&rsquo; moment. But let us call it the &lsquo;Ah!&rsquo; moment.</p>

<p>So now we have a nice timing pair:</p>

<ul>
<li> Ah!   ?</li>
<li> Hah!  Contact</li>
</ul>


<p>If the Hah! is Contact, what should the Ah! be? Turns out there are lots of choices&hellip;</p>

<h3>Ah! the bounce</h3>

<p>You can &lsquo;Ah! the bounce&rsquo; before contact.  This is among the most basic (and also the most powerful) &ldquo;Ah! Hah!&rdquo; pairs.
The bounce is basically the last easily determined moment in time before contact.  By getting the feel of the following variations,
you open yourself up to both some interestingly powerful shots (e.g. on the rise off the bounce) and also start
yourself down the path of insane reaction times where the &lsquo;dot&rsquo;s below are ticks at 30 ticks per second or even 120 ticks per second!</p>

<ul>
<li> &ldquo;Ah! &hellip;&hellip;&hellip;&hellip;. Hah!&rdquo;</li>
<li> &ldquo;Ah! &hellip;&hellip; Hah!&rdquo;</li>
<li> &ldquo;Ah! &hellip; Hah!&rdquo;</li>
<li> &ldquo;Ah! . Hah!&rdquo;</li>
</ul>


<p>If you can get your brain and body to do these variations with a dot representing 1/120th of a second, you can likely return
any professional&rsquo;s serve.</p>

<h3>Ah! the hit</h3>

<p>You can also choose to &ldquo;Ah!&rdquo; the contact (the &lsquo;hit&rsquo;) of the &ldquo;opponent&rdquo;.  This is way earlier than the bounce, but the big
advantage is that you are now <em>clearly tracking that ball</em>.  You have made sure your brain and eyes are paying attention
and can start moving your body where it needs to move (both feet and hands).</p>

<p>Now let&rsquo;s take this up a level!</p>

<h2>La Ti Da!</h2>

<p>Simply combine the two above with a simple rename</p>

<ul>
<li> La  The Hit</li>
<li> Ti  The Bounce</li>
<li> Da  Contact</li>
</ul>


<p>If you have seen me return serve at my best a few months ago (April 2014), that is what I was doing.  And I could <em>totally crush</em>
many serves that seemed to others to be almost un-returnable.  But bit by bit my &lsquo;ticks&rsquo; became faster and faster and by &lsquo;Ti&rsquo;
I was in position and the &lsquo;Da&rsquo; was sending a decent serve back at the net man (or the space in the center) at a nice 100+ MPH
pace.</p>

<p>Get your &ldquo;Ah! Hah!&#8221;s and your &#8220;La Ti Da!&#8221;s into your head and your game&hellip; and you will become much better very quickly.</p>

<h2>Don&rsquo;t take my word on it.</h2>

<p>Some captures from high-speed video to show the idea.</p>

<h3>Ah! Bounce, Hah! Contact</h3>

<h4>Ah! Bounce</h4>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/LaTiDa_20140912a_f3_w779.png"/></p>

<h4>Hah! Contact</h4>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/LaTiDa_20140912a_f4_w779.png"/></p>

<h3>Ah! Hit, Hah! Contact</h3>

<h4>Ah! Hit</h4>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/LaTiDa_20140912a_f2_w779.png"/></p>

<h4>Hah! Contact</h4>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/LaTiDa_20140912a_f4_w779.png"/></p>

<h3>La! Hit, Ti! Bounce, Da! Contact</h3>

<p>Switching to &ldquo;La Ti Da!&rdquo;</p>

<h4>La! Hit</h4>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/LaTiDa_20140912a_f2_w779.png"/></p>

<h4>Ti! Bounce</h4>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/LaTiDa_20140912a_f3_w779.png"/></p>

<h4>Da! Contact</h4>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/LaTiDa_20140912a_f4_w779.png"/></p>

<h3>Fa! Toss, La! Hit, Ti! Bounce, Da! Contact</h3>

<p>And to help you beat me <em>now</em>, I use something closer to this as my model.</p>

<h4>Fa! Toss</h4>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/LaTiDa_20140912a_f1_w779.png"/></p>

<h4>La! Hit</h4>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/LaTiDa_20140912a_f2_w779.png"/></p>

<h4>Ti! Bounce</h4>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/LaTiDa_20140912a_f3_w779.png"/></p>

<h4>Da! Contact</h4>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/LaTiDa_20140912a_f4_w779.png"/></p>

<h4>And the result :&ndash;)</h4>

<p>By the &lsquo;ticks&rsquo; (30 feet in about &frac14;th of a second), this ball is traveling at about 80 MPH to the net,
so above 90 MPH off the racket against a relatively slow serve.  To confirm the fraction of the second,
if you look at the &ldquo;net man&rdquo; (his name is Tuan&hellip; he is <em>very</em> fast), he has barely moved by the time the ball passes the net.
The server has not moved at all between the two frames.</p>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/LaTiDa_20140912a_f5_w779.png"/></p>

<h2>Summary</h2>

<p>The core of the idea is &ldquo;Ah! Hah!&rdquo;.  This enables you to leverage your natural auditory and mental timing capabilities to get
your physical timing right.  Right can be &ldquo;warmed up&rdquo;, &ldquo;match ready&rdquo;, or &ldquo;on a new level&rdquo;.  Try it.  It&rsquo;s insanely great :&ndash;)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What does the fox wear?]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/what-does-the-fox-wear/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-04T20:40:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/what-does-the-fox-wear</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As part of doing <a href="http://insanelyGreatTennis.com/">Insanely Great Tennis</a> for the local pros of Palo Alto,
I came up with the idea of pitching a franchise to <a href="http://google.com/search?q=SharkTank">Shark Tank</a>.  To
pitch a television show, you need a picture of yourself.  I had my standard Linked-In profile, but that isn&rsquo;t really
very compelling.  So I augmented my pitch with my tennis outfits, so it is a good time to blog about them :&ndash;)</p>

<p>My outfits came out of two issues:</p>

<ul>
<li> I frequently played tennis after biking (I biked with my kids to school, and then biked some more after).</li>
<li> To play tennis, you need <a href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/lots-of-fuzzy-balls">Lots of fuzzy balls</a></li>
</ul>


<p>Through daily dealing with these two issues came my <em>amazing epiphany</em>: you should play tennis in biking shirts!  And by <em>you</em>, I really mean
<em>you</em>&hellip; as in everyone&hellip;. if you are reading this&hellip; go change your shirt&hellip; and go play some tennis :&ndash;)</p>

<p>Another constraint on my tennis outfits and clothing in general is that I do not want to think about clothing very much.  So
I have suits.  My primary suits involve a red shirt and black pants.  Sometimes I swap in a black shirt.  That is it.
Two choices.  Mostly affected by the contents of the hamper.</p>

<p>Below you will see four outfits, which were initially just one, but broadened somewhat when the second and especially the
third came along.</p>

<h2>The Red Fox</h2>

<p>This is the original.  Worn with either a red (&ldquo;Fear the Tree&rdquo;) or black cap.</p>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/IGT_Foxes3_mlf1a2_w720_redFox.png"/></p>

<h2>The Frisco Fox</h2>

<p>This is a fun augmentation to the Red Fox.  There is a picture of the Golden Gate bridge on the shirt, and it promotes
a good local bike shop.  No one (sane) in or near San Francisco actually calls the city Frisco, but my slightly insane
daughter likes to call it that, so this outfit&rsquo;s name is for her.  The hat is an alien-hat which seems to match the
charm of the city too!</p>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/IGT_Foxes3_mlf1a2_w720_friscoFox.png"/></p>

<h2>The Zebra Fox</h2>

<p>The above shirts were the top of the heap until this one came along.  Having a shirt named after you is too awesome to
not wear it.  I need to get this in red though.</p>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/IGT_Foxes3_mlf1a2_w720_zebraFox.png"/></p>

<h2>The Yoga Fox</h2>

<p>This is a fun shirt, but  has just one large pocket in the back, so isn&rsquo;t as good as the ones above for tennis (or for biking either).
This was actually the original &ldquo;biking/tennis shirt&rdquo;, but it has only one rear pocket, so I now
store it as a dry spare in my bag.  For this outfit, I reveal my (lack of) hair.</p>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/IGT_Foxes3_mlf1a2_w720_yogaFox.png"/></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lots of fuzzy balls!]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/lots-of-fuzzy-balls/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-28T20:40:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/lots-of-fuzzy-balls</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I am going to reveal my most incredibly genius complete transformation of the planes of reality&hellip; just for
you!</p>

<p>First some context.  In tennis, you need to hit fuzzy tennis balls.  Sometimes you hit the ball where you want it to go,
and the other person hits it back to you.  That is called a rally.  If all you ever do in your tennis life is &lsquo;rally&rsquo;,
my incredible genius is not meant for you.</p>

<p>But in certain circumstances in tennis, you either (a) don&rsquo;t hit the ball where your partner is, or (b) you or your
partner don&rsquo;t really hit the ball well at all.  So if either of these happen to you, you need to either go chasing after
that wayward ball, or have a brother/sister-ball easily available.</p>

<p>I value my and your time very highly, so I don&rsquo;t like chasing wayward fuzzy balls.  Instead I carry sibling balls with
me to stand in their elders&#8217; place: primus, secondus, &hellip; septimus, and onward.  Wait did I just say &lsquo;septimus&rsquo;?  That is
seven right?  Nobody carries seven balls!  Well, except me.  And as of today, I will teach you to as well.</p>

<p>The tennis industry is a bit backward.  Men are allowed to maybe carry four balls, plus one in their hand if they have a
single handed backhand (Hah!).  Women are apparently still meant to torture themselves with various bizarre &ldquo;stashes&rdquo; or
equipment just to carry one ball out-of-hand.  The tennis fashion industry is clearly seriously demented.</p>

<p>So look elsewhere for salvation.  Where?  Biking!  Yoga!  Walking!  All these other industries can make tennis more fun and
functional for you.</p>

<p>If you are a &lsquo;guy&rsquo; (or &lsquo;dude&rsquo; or &lsquo;mensch&rsquo; or an awesome woman who is also flexible with her clothing), you can actually acquire
some Fila or similar
tennis pants.  Later I will let you know what should be under those pants (and no, it isn&rsquo;t &lsquo;underwear&rsquo;&hellip; and no, it isn&rsquo;t
&lsquo;commando&rsquo; either&hellip; but that is a different topic for a differnt day).  OK, so you have pants that can now carry four balls.
Huzzah!</p>

<p>Now for the seven.  Well, actually, the dozen!  Instead of buying a silly tennis shirt, go buy a 3-pocket biking shirt.
These shirts are both totally suitable for tennis, and by having <em>three</em> pockets, they can carry <em>six</em> balls.  Four in the
pants, six in the shirt, and two in your left hand.  With one in play, you have a baker&rsquo;s dozen.
Burdened with a two-handed backhand?  Terrible penalty!  You are down to <em>ten</em> balls plus
the one in play.  A &ldquo;two-handed dozen&rdquo;?</p>

<p>Playing with ten to a baker&rsquo;s dozen balls is a very different experience.  Much more time hitting with your partners.
Much more productive and less chase-y.  And totally
suitable for <em>serving</em> without having the overhead of a ball-hopper.</p>

<p>You are the ball hopper!</p>

<h3>Women</h3>

<p>If you are a woman and don&rsquo;t want to buy men&rsquo;s clothes to get pockets (Tennis industry dementia), apparently LuluLemon and likely
similar clothing lines are happy to provide 2-4 ball pockets in their pants and skirts.  So go buy them and tell your
local tennis shop that &ldquo;I went elsewhere because tennis clothes are &lsquo;obsolete&rsquo;&rdquo;.  That might get the manufacturers attention!</p>

<h3>My Outfit</h3>

<p>I was going to post my outfit today, but I think I will save that for a blog
&ldquo;What does the Fox wear?  The Supersonic Fox wear?&rdquo; ;&ndash;)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dress Your Wall!]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/dress-your-wall/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-25T20:40:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/dress-your-wall</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You may have been playing with your <a href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/first-partner">first partner</a> for quite some time now&hellip; but
have you thought at all about how they feel?  I assume you are playing in some kind of tennisy outfit: shirts and pants, dress,
skirt, maybe sweats, etc.  But all this time your partner has been <em>naked</em> hasn&rsquo;t it?  All this time&hellip;</p>

<p>We need to fix that, for your first partner is not at their best when they are naked.  And for you to get
better, you need all your partners to be at their best.  Even if they are Serena or Federer (which would be awesome!)</p>

<p>Your poor naked wall may look something like this:</p>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/CIMG2509_w1728_q5.jpg"/></p>

<p>That is not nice!  At least make sure it has basic attire:</p>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/CIMG2510_w1622_q5.jpg"/></p>

<p>And if you want to really doll it up, get some tagger to help you do this:</p>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/CIMG2509_w1728_q5_v2.jpg"/></p>

<h2>Targeting</h2>

<p>Just like you had targeting rackets for your serve, you need targets on the court for the rest of your shots.
We will discuss on-court targeting later, but with the wall, you need reference points and goal targets.  The squares
can serve as both.</p>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/CIMG2509_w1728_q5_v3.jpg"/></p>

<p>The standard way is like the simple red square: use a bit of masking/painters tape to make a square.  It can be big (the red square is a bit big)
or even just a &lsquo;visible dot&rsquo;.  You can have concentric squares, circles, triangles, or whatever shape you love the most.  But
don&rsquo;t hit against a bare wall if you can avoid it.  Get some kind of reference point up there and put up some kind of goal/s.</p>

<p>Now get them targets!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
