<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[The SuperSonic (Tennis) Fox]]></title>
  <link href="http://supersonicfox.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://supersonicfox.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-26T17:04:03-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://supersonicfox.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mark Fussell]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Play]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.github.io/blog/play/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-26T18:15:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.github.io/blog/play</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Now that my daughter and I had equipment, we needed just a couple more things.  Courts and Time.</p>

<p>We live within walking distance of Mitchell Park in Palo Alto.  Mitchell has amazing tennis courts!  They clean themselves
every day magically!  They are right next to backboards so people can warm up and then join games!  There are a fair number
of them (seven) and within an easy walk there are six more!  And the tennis players at Mitchell are amongst the friendliest
you will ever encounter.  I am happy to now be counted among this elite community and to be expanding its reach every week.</p>

<p>Yes, I have played on <em>better surfaced</em> courts than Mitchell.  Lots of clays are nicer than Mitchell&rsquo;s surface.
And Wimbledon grass would be nice.  But the self-cleaning and community part is amazing.</p>

<p><img src="../../images/CIMG2413_w864.jpg" width="864" height="1152" /></p>

<p>So shortly after my daughter and I bought equipment at <a href="http://tennistownandcountry.com">http://tennistownandcountry.com</a> , we ventured over to the courts at
Mitchell.  My memory is feeble, so I can&rsquo;t say what time of the day it actually was, but let me guess it was maybe 9AM or 10AM.</p>

<p>With seven courts available, finding court time is not particularly difficult.  So after 30 years of hiatus, I was back on the court.
Teaching my daughter some basics of tennis, and reminding my body of the moves it needed to do.  It was now 48 when last it
really played tennis, it was 18.</p>

<p>This first day I had no actual problems for me and my body, but if you know me from my book
(<a href="http://slumsofpaloalto.com/">http://slumsofpaloalto.com/</a>) this was shortly after my <em>tenth</em> startup.  Startups take 60 to 80 hours a week from you every
weeek.  Or at least that is what they took from me: I was very good, but I had to get a lot done to hope to see any real
payoff.  And with a decade of one-after-the-other startups, I was now fat.  Like 200 pounds kind of fat.  With no significant
amount of muscled to explain that weight.</p>

<p>So although the first day of playing tennis went fine, and my daughter had fun, I was well aware of how fast kids can become
seriously good at something.  And having 30+ pounds of fat was not going to enable me keep up with her.</p>

<p>So a day of play became a start of an incredible journey.  Day by day I simply played, but that play transformed me.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Equipment]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.github.io/blog/equipment/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-14T18:15:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.github.io/blog/equipment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>To play tennis, you  need equipment.  I grew up with tennis in the 1970s and 1980s.  By the time I was &ldquo;serious&rdquo; about tennis,
I played with a Head Professional aluminum racket.  I loved it: indestructible unless you were ridiculously mad at the court.  Until
2013, those were my only kind of racket:  Tiny, stiff, and indestructible.</p>

<p><img src="../../images/CIMG2413_w864.jpg" width="864" height="1152" /></p>

<p>Over the decades of absence, I gave all my tennis equipment away.  So in the summer of 2013, when my daughter Katrina decided she wanted to
play, I had to buy new equipment.  There is only one right place to by tennis equipment.  A tennis shop.  No, don&rsquo;t go online.  No, don&rsquo;t go
to Sports Authority (feel free to go there for other things).  You buy tennis equipment from a &ldquo;Pro&rdquo;: from someone that is at least a 4.x
and who can talk to you about your game.  That is if you want to be good.  If not, just go to a flea market.</p>

<p>My nearest Tennis Shop is Tennis Town and Country <a href="http://tennistownandcountry.com">http://tennistownandcountry.com</a> . Over the year I transformed, I may have spent 100 hours in the shop.
But that first hour with Caden and Todor was critical: What racket should my daughter get?  And what racket should I get?  And finally, what balls should
we play with?</p>

<p>It may not have been critical that we get all this perfect the first time, but a year later I play with exactly the same racket.  Actually <em>five</em> of them.
And after a year of growth physically and in skill, my daughter gave me her racket as a targeting racket<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>.  So as far as I can tell, Todor and Caden
completely nailed it.
My daughter played for a year with a Wilson Roger Federer 24&#8221;, and my racket collection started with a Head Speed MP.  My grip is slightly small for me, but
that is because I put Tourna Grip tape on it, which adds another 1/8th maybe.  I have changed lots of different things about my game, my grip, my strings,
and lots of other equipment.  But through a year of changes, I still play with the Head Speed MP.</p>

<p><img src="../../images/CIMG2414_w864.jpg" width="864" height="1152" /></p>

<p>Why?  Because it is an awesome racket!!!  And it is still better than I am, even as I wander into the 5.x-ish territory.  I did one day play with a Babolet
Pure Strike 18x20.  I admit that is also an awesome racket!!!  Actually it felt like I imagine smoking crack might feel like.  I had such insane amounts of
control that I felt I was fiddling with millimeters.  But I thought the drug too strong and didn&rsquo;t want to swap out my five rackets.  And then Head came out
 with Lynx strings, which was a good fraction of the same drug.</p>

<p>So in one hour we had the two rackets we needed for the courts.  I also bought some Slazenger Wimbledon balls, and although I am <em>capable</em> of playing with
other balls, over the year I would purchase dozens of cans of only this one kind of ball.</p>

<p><img src="../../images/CIMG2415_h864.jpg" width="1152" height="864" /></p>

<p>So we have rackets and balls, what else do we need?</p>

<p>The only right answer is <em>nothing</em>.  <em>Yet</em>  No giant bag for gear you don&rsquo;t have.  No fancy Fila&rsquo;s that feel as light as the air.  No tennis shoes.
You don&rsquo;t need any of that the first day.</p>

<p>But feel free to buy it: it supports the tennis shop and you could definitely have an awesome wardrobe.  Especially try out the biking shirts which will help women
carry tennis balls (at all) and people who need to practice their serve (i.e. everyone) can carry six to ten balls at a time and do away with the
ball hopper.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>A racket you place into the top of the net so you can see where you are serving.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Site Launch!]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.github.io/blog/site-launch/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-07T18:15:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.github.io/blog/site-launch</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have been writing a book <a href="http://slumsofpaloalto.com/">http://slumsofpaloalto.com/</a> and playing a lot of tennis.  The tennis was a major part of
how I transformed in the last year, and may have been a major enabler for writing the book.  Losing 40 pounds of fat, gaining 10+ of muscle,
and having an insanely fun &amp; social activity may have been major catalysts for my transformation.  The book will cover some of what
happened with tennis, but it has a lot of topics in it, and it is mostly about learning &amp; kindness repeatedly being applied after
repeated failures.  This site and blog will focus just on tennis, hoping to help others be better players, and told from
a somewhat elderly, not super-fit (at the start), but definitely committed player.  Not a professional tennis player, but a professional <em>learner</em> who
applied those skills to tennis.</p>

<p>I hope it helps someone else have a little better (or a lot better) of a game, while still having an insanely fun time playing.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
