<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[The SuperSonic (Tennis) Fox]]></title>
  <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-15T11:19:34-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://supersonicfox.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mark Fussell]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pong-Ping]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/pong-ping/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-14T20:40:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/pong-ping</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This site is meant to be primarily about Tennis, and more accidentally about other things.
But today I had a conversation that is more about other things and only somewhat about tennis,
so I guess this post stretches the boundary of this blog a bit.</p>

<h2>Insanity</h2>

<p>Insanity is doing things that you have enough evidence to know <em>will not work</em> but yet you still do them.
That should be the only good definition of the word: you try something, it fails, you try again, it fails, yet
you keep doing exactly the same thing expecting it to succeed.  That is a useful word
and would be helpful to most of the planet if they learned it.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, most people prefer a different definition of insanity, which is basically equivalent to &ldquo;Not like &lsquo;normal&rsquo; people&rdquo;.
This is not a very useful concept because it is pejorative.  &ldquo;Awesome!&rdquo; good word.  &ldquo;Amazing!&rdquo; good word.  &ldquo;Insane!&rdquo; meaning not normal&hellip; useless negative word.
Unless you consider it to be a humbler version of the two definitions preceding it.</p>

<p>So now that I have explained my understanding of the word &ldquo;insane&rdquo;, I will actually accept my last definition and say simply &ldquo;I am insane&rdquo;.
I do things <em>very differently</em> from &lsquo;normal&rsquo; people.  My insanity makes my incredibly productive.  Beyond most
people&rsquo;s conception of &lsquo;productive&rsquo;.</p>

<p>You may or may not want to follow my lead, but I have now committed to explaining it.</p>

<h2>Pong-Ping</h2>

<p>If you have read my book <a href="http://SlumsOfPaloAlto.com/">http://SlumsOfPaloAlto.com/</a>, you know a bit about the sequences of startups I have participated in.  The first four were relatively
soft participations in the management, the fifth was my own (lost a lot of money), and the sixth through tenth were me trying
to focus on executing what I was clearly good at while learning a bit more about the other aspects of the company.</p>

<p>For the first of these five, I joined Jerry Kaplan (<a href="http://www.google.com/?gws_rd=ssl#q=jerry+kaplan">http://www.google.com/?gws_rd=ssl#q=jerry+kaplan</a>) at his startup <a href="http://winster.com">http://winster.com</a>.
There are different kinds of Entrepreneurs, and Jerry would commonly be called an &lsquo;Optimizer&rsquo;.  This is a very useful skill
when things are running very smoothly, so a lot of Jerry&rsquo;s skills would help you have a more optimized life.</p>

<p>One of the critical things Entrepreneurs have to do is <em>raise money</em>.  Potentially lots of money ideally from people you barely know,
so these people need to investigate you quite a bit before deciding to give you money.  And these people are commonly very busy.
Some could take months to get back to you (even when you are Jerry), so you have to be patient.  Also these people do not like
to be &lsquo;pestered&rsquo;, so you don&rsquo;t have to poke them many times.  Poke once and then wait.  Poke many different people to hopefully get
a positive response from someone.</p>

<p>You might consider this to be &lsquo;Ping&rsquo; them and they &lsquo;Pong&rsquo; you back.  So it is a game of Ping-Pong.</p>

<p>But that is not optimal <em>if</em> there are many interactions with these people.  Or it makes the rhythm misleading for the truly optimal
interaction.  Any time you get a &lsquo;Pong&rsquo; you should ASAP &lsquo;Ping&rsquo;.  &lsquo;Pong&rsquo;&ndash;&lsquo;Ping&rsquo;&hellip; pong-ping&hellip;.. pong-ping&hellip;. pong-ping&hellip;</p>

<p>If you rush as soon as you get a Pong, the other person has the ball again and it is up to them to Pong you again.  There is
now <em>nothing</em> you can do&hellip; which is incredibly relieving.</p>

<h2>Pong-Ping <em>everything</em></h2>

<p>I gave the VC cycle as an example, but this actually works for <em>absolutely</em> everything that needs to get done.  Consider
any request from someone this way and you can get it out of your hair (or brain) almost instantly.  I was recently contacted
by McDonalds and responded within five minutes.  It was a completely composed response, which would have been hard for me
to do that quickly a couple decades ago, but the core process was identical:</p>

<ul>
<li> Receive Pong</li>
<li> Read Pong</li>
<li> Decide whether to kill the Pong (trash it)</li>
<li> If going to Ping, do it immediately.  Might take a day or two.  Or you might have to break it into smaller tasks and do one then <em>pong yourself</em></li>
</ul>


<p>And you are done.  It really works for pretty much everything and means you have nothing looming over you undone.  Everything is done, pinged, and you are free to
get new Pongs.  Even from yourself :&ndash;)</p>

<p>The site <a href="http://FixYourMom.com">http://FixYourMom.com</a> went from idea conceived at the lunch table to live in less than four hours based on Pong-Ping!  And during that time I was mostly doing other things!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Unboxed Boxes]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/unboxed-boxes/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-25T20:40:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/unboxed-boxes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I do not want you to be &lsquo;Boxed&rsquo;, to be constrained by artificial constraints or limitations you believe exist but
have never verified or actively chosen.  I hate that kind of boxing and a huge part of SOPA <a href="http://SlumsOfPaloAlto.com/">http://SlumsOfPaloAlto.com/</a>
is getting people to recognize the boxing that occurs and get rid of it in themselves and others.</p>

<p>On the other hand, you must recognize that you are a box&hellip; at least pretty close to a box&hellip; physically.</p>

<h2>Quadrants around Boxes</h2>

<p>Previously I described the quadrants around your body, but in that I treated you as if you were a <em>point</em> in
space.  But looking down at you, your left and right shoulders are clearly visible as different things.  Assuming
you swing your arms vertically in a circle around your shoulders, you form a box: your right swinging arm on the right of you,
and your left swinging on the left of you.</p>

<p>To get to your ultimate game, you have to let the ball (or position yourself to enable the ball to) get to racket-side
of this box.</p>

<h3>Volleys</h3>

<p>For example, a backhand volley is innately <em>easier</em> than a forehand volley because you have both: &ldquo;Get to the ball soon&rdquo;
combined with &ldquo;Hit it on the racket-side of the box&rdquo;.  You rotate your body for a backhand and your racket is automatically
close to the net.  Actually pretty much everything is <em>easier</em> for your backhand, because of this &lsquo;box&rsquo; rotation.  The
only thing that is harder are the strokes that rely on lots of rotation, because you inherently don&rsquo;t need to, so don&rsquo;t
practice, rotational backhands.</p>

<p>People actually comment on my backhand more than almost anything else about my game.  I do like my one-handed-bullet-and-pretty-much-whatever-I-want
backhand, but it isn&rsquo;t my best shot.  It just isn&rsquo;t &ldquo;weak&rdquo;: I hit it as well as a backhand can be hit.  But most people
fear their backhands and so they avoid and don&rsquo;t practice it.  My model is simply &ldquo;Hit my weakest shot&rdquo; and over time
that rotates around and all my shots are &ldquo;my weakest shot&rdquo;&hellip; that makes you <em>very dangerous</em> when your weakest shot
is the shot that everyone complements you on.</p>

<h3>Forehand Slice</h3>

<p>The box is the most frustrating when dealing with forehand slices, including forehand volleys.  You want to hit the ball&hellip; soon&hellip; right now!&hellip;
but no&hellip; you must wait for it to enter your box and almost <em>leave it</em> out the right/rear side of the box.  Slices hit
late can actually be fine with the right grip, but power slices hit early in the box just fly off the court :&ndash;(  Very frustrating
and likely to make you want to hit <em>even earlier</em> which is exactly the wrong reaction.  Be patient!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[El Camino Del Diablo (3)]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/el-camino-del-diablo-3/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-24T20:40:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/el-camino-del-diablo-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Continuing the road to the devil&hellip;</p>

<h2>Serve &rsquo;D&#8217;</h2>

<p>I have no second serves&hellip;. except for one.  It isn&rsquo;t always a second serve, but it&rsquo;s purpose is to relieve me.  Relief
is very useful when you are stressed.  And although I am a pretty laid-back tennis player outwardly, I can get very
annoyed at myself and my inadequacies.</p>

<p>How inadequate?  Well for many <em>months</em> I couldn&rsquo;t manage to toss the ball properly.  Toss&hellip;. toss&hellip; toss&hellip; In club
tennis you can pretty much just keep tossing because people don&rsquo;t play with a time limit.  But eventually I would
just get annoyed and not want to stop play.  So I would hit the one serve I practiced more than any other until
about month-nine.  A drop forehand.  Simply hit.</p>

<h3>A Forehand?</h3>

<p>Yes, a drop forehand is perfectly legal.  It is also very relieving because it is something so practiced that you
just &ldquo;do it&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Actually now I can do some pretty powerful &rsquo;D&#8217; serves, but the goal isn&rsquo;t to win, it is just to get the ball in play.
It does that very nicely.</p>

<p>And some of my partners have even been aced by it!</p>

<h2>Serve &lsquo;E&rsquo;</h2>

<p>Serve &lsquo;E&rsquo; had the most strange development of all my serves, and ultimately it developed all the way to
obsolescence.  I do not use it at all any more&hellip; I don&rsquo;t even practice it any more&hellip; but my <em>entire</em>
touch game is based on understanding this &ldquo;serve&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Serve &lsquo;E&rsquo; is a slice done shoulder-height.  You toss the ball out into quadrant I at approximately 45-degrees and you
slice it.  And by slice, I mean every essence of your mind is thinking and <em>most</em> of your body
is doing &lsquo;slice&rsquo;, &lsquo;perpendicular&rsquo;, &lsquo;rotations&rsquo;, &lsquo;insane&rsquo;, etc.</p>

<h3>Step-1</h3>

<p>Step-1 is just getting the idea that the ball is out in quadrant-1 and you are slicing it.  If you
instinctively get really good at Step-1, the ball barely moves forward.  Ultimately I think I did things
in slightly the wrong order and serve &lsquo;G&rsquo; would have been better to focus on first, but this is a minor
nuance because both serves are really about understanding &lsquo;Step-2&rsquo; so you can go back to &lsquo;Step-1&rsquo; and
get it right.</p>

<h3>Step-2</h3>

<p>The problem with Step-1 is you don&rsquo;t have faith.  If every part of your body is dedicated to slicing, the
ball does not go forward&hellip; at all.  It just spins in place.</p>

<p>So we need the ball to go forward but your arm isn&rsquo;t going to be helping.  But above I didn&rsquo;t say <em>all</em>, I said <em>most</em>.
The part of your body that will make the go forward is the one part that can&rsquo;t help with slice.  Your legs and hips.
These we need to rotate.  Rotate forcefully enough to propel a ball forward over the net.</p>

<p>That isn&rsquo;t actually that hard: attach a racket to your hips and you can serious hit a ball.  But you need to seriously
rotate.</p>

<p>In my case John first made me toss a ball a bit too far away and rotate with my right leg stretched out&hellip; spinning
like a top around the left foot.  This may have helped me start thinking right, but it lasted only a week.  The
next week I was to keep my right foot in and think more like &lsquo;Flying Superman&rsquo; with my bodies and limbs (except the
left leg keeping me in the air)&hellip; but the rotation was still there.</p>

<p>The reasons for the spin are (a) to get contact with the ball that will propel it forward, (b) to make insane slice
easier (effectively the ball is moving toward you by you spinning and that is easier to slice than not-moving), and
&copy; to get your body out of the way of the insane power slicing racket.</p>

<h3>Step-3</h3>

<p>Now combine Step-2 back with Step-1 and make sure to still do Step-2 to get your lower body helping out,
but focus on Step-1 and <em>slice</em> the ball where that is all your slice is about&hellip; slice.  rotations&hellip;
insane rotations&hellip;</p>

<p>The toss is still about 45 degrees into Quadrant-I, but it will be pretty close to your body&hellip;
about a forearms length out.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Quadrants]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/quadrants/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-22T20:40:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/quadrants</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Quadrants</h2>

<p>Serving can be simplified into &lsquo;toss ball&rsquo;, &lsquo;hit ball&rsquo;.  You can have one serve or a dozen, but all of them have this
core rhythm.  If you do have a dozen serves, they do not &ldquo;all work&rdquo; with every kind of toss.  I have an underhand slice
serve that starts with me dropping the ball right in front of me&hellip; very hard to hit top-spin on that one.  I would even
say &lsquo;Inconceivable&rsquo;.</p>

<p>To understand the toss, it can be helpful to think of yourself in the middle of the universe.  Where is your body?
And relative to that body, where is that ball?</p>

<p>Assuming you have only overhead serves, then the ball better be &lsquo;up&rsquo;.  But &ldquo;up where?&rdquo;.</p>

<h3>Four Quadrants</h3>

<p>In plane geometry there are four quadrants going from I (1) to IV (4):
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quadrant_(plane_geometry)">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quadrant_(plane_geometry)</a>.  If you consider your body as the center of the universe,
and you are right-handed, your relative quadrants match the geometry ones exactly.  If you are left-handed, please
flip the even/odd ones.</p>

<p>So there are four quadrants around your body, and the ball is always in one of them (or on a line, but let&rsquo;s not be
picky about that).  So where is it?  And where should it be?  The obvious answer is &ldquo;It depends&rdquo;.</p>

<h3>Different serves, different quadrants</h3>

<p>For my butterfly, flat, &lsquo;A&rsquo; serve, I contact in &lsquo;I&rsquo;.  My body rotates so my right shoulder is forward (parallel to the baseline plus or minus)
before contact, which basically guarantees I have to hit in &lsquo;I&rsquo;.  The ballistic serve &lsquo;B&rsquo; is behind me, so in either &lsquo;IV&rsquo; or maybe
&lsquo;III&rsquo;.  And &lsquo;C&rsquo; is a top-spin serve, so you want to be mostly going &lsquo;up&rsquo; and that means the ball is in &lsquo;III&rsquo;.</p>

<p>Note that the quadrants exist <em>all the time</em> and if your body is moving, the quadrants are changing because of your
movement.  Later I will explain my &lsquo;hell&rsquo; serve, which is basically a serve that you toss deep into &lsquo;I&rsquo; and then get your
body in the right spot to hit top spin on it: i.e. &lsquo;III&rsquo;.</p>

<h3>Proper ball position</h3>

<p>The quadrants are a great way to start being aware of &lsquo;proper ball position&rsquo;.  There are others too, but
lets stop with this for the moment.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[El Camino Del Diablo (2)]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/el-camino-del-diablo-2/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-11T20:40:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/el-camino-del-diablo-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Continuing the road to the devil&hellip;</p>

<h2>Serve &lsquo;C&rsquo;</h2>

<p>Again, the serves are alphabetical on the time that John or I came up with them.  After understanding the ballistic serve &lsquo;B&rsquo;,
we returned to a more normal top-spin serve &lsquo;C&rsquo;.  This turns out to be both one of the most useful serves if you want to &lsquo;win&rsquo;
or just &lsquo;have fun&rsquo; (without blowing people&rsquo;s minds like &lsquo;B&rsquo; does).</p>

<p>Serve &lsquo;C&rsquo; is also amongst the most complex of the serves until we get into the hell range.</p>

<p>To serve an &lsquo;A&rsquo;, your racket comes
up from behind, hits the ball in front of you (quadrant &lsquo;I&rsquo; if you look down on your body <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quadrant_(plane_geometry)">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quadrant_(plane_geometry)</a>)
and then finishes into quadrant &lsquo;III&rsquo;.  So for a right-handed person the racket ends to the left of your left leg.  At
least to me, this all seems very natural and I can do a butterfly movement all day long where the racket starts in &lsquo;I&rsquo;,
goes down and back into &lsquo;IV&rsquo;, then goes up and back into &lsquo;III&rsquo;, over the top
to hit the ball in &lsquo;I&rsquo;, and then back down briefly through &lsquo;II&rsquo; into &lsquo;III&rsquo;
and then comes back up to the start in &lsquo;I&rsquo; to do it all again.  Part of my warm-up is swinging those butterflies.</p>

<p>If you move the ball more to the left and on top of you, and swing an &lsquo;A&rsquo; you might think you get a &lsquo;C&rsquo;, but that is not a &lsquo;C&rsquo;,
it is just a kind of weird &lsquo;A&rsquo;.  &lsquo;C&rsquo; is really about understanding your rotator cuff <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rotator_cuff">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rotator_cuff</a>, which is an impressive and potentially fragile
set of muscles that connect your arm to your body.  If you google &lsquo;rotator cuff&rsquo;, the first entries are about injuries!  So
please talk with a coach before <em>trying</em> anything I am describing.  I am not a doctor!  Don&rsquo;t <em>trust me with your body</em></p>

<p>So how is &lsquo;C&rsquo; related to the rotator cuff?  I will show you!</p>

<p>With a racket in hand, stick whichever arm you serve with straight out from your body.  Like the lower arms of this: <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leonardo_da_Vinci#mediaviewer/File:Da_Vinci_Vitruve_Luc_Viatour.jpg">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leonardo_da_Vinci#mediaviewer/File:Da_Vinci_Vitruve_Luc_Viatour.jpg</a>.
Now have the racket face upward (your palm forward depending on grip).  The face of the racket should be forward, toward the net.
Now rotate just your shoulder so the racket is downward and the face of the racket is now to facing the fence.  About 180 degrees of rotation.
Do that a few times to get the feel of it.  You can enlarge it a bit to get more than 180 degrees too, but that core 180 degrees
is the core of how &lsquo;C&rsquo; is very different from &lsquo;A&rsquo;.</p>

<p>After practicing sideways, practice the same move with your arm vertical.  The racket starts facing the net over your head, and ends facing the fence and away
from your body.  John calls this a &lsquo;helicopter&rsquo;.  Some other people call it &lsquo;whipping a wet diaper&rsquo;.  This helicopter move
imparts a lot of racket velocity: I can actually serve quite nicely using it alone (back to being &lsquo;to the side&rsquo;).  And
that extra velocity is very effective for producing spin.  Eventually tennis becomes all-about-the-spin: velocities are
so high that <em>going faster</em> will simply <em>go outer</em>.  But <em>spinning faster</em> will stay in and drive people crazy.</p>

<h3>Wrong-side</h3>

<p>OK, so you take an &lsquo;A&rsquo;, add the helicopter, and toss the ball slightly more left and on top of you, and you get a &lsquo;C&rsquo;.  That is
most of the basics of a &lsquo;C&rsquo; except for one major issue&hellip; where does the racket <em>go</em> after you hit that ball?  With an &lsquo;A&rsquo; the racket
went forward and veering to the &lsquo;III&rsquo; quadrant (left of left-leg for a right hander) is natural.  With a &lsquo;C&rsquo; you just flipped
your racket way to the right and quadrant &lsquo;III&rsquo; is no where close.</p>

<p>Well, if &lsquo;III&rsquo; is gone, the only thing left is &lsquo;IV&rsquo;, so that is where you have to finish.  Except &lsquo;IV&rsquo; is where your other leg is!
Don&rsquo;t wack it!  It isn&rsquo;t pleasant!</p>

<p>You need to get that leg out of the way to do a real &lsquo;C&rsquo;, and because of rotational aspects and other dynamics, the best place to put
it is further away (up) in &lsquo;IV&rsquo;.  So the racket goes below your outstretched leg, which gives it enough time to slow down.</p>

<h3>What?</h3>

<p>So &lsquo;C&rsquo; is really quite complex and I probably can&rsquo;t explain it well without photos (maybe later), but I wanted to get
something down on paper to start with.  If you practice the helicopter to your side and above, you will begin to
understand the &lsquo;C&rsquo;.  That is a good start.  Just keep your shoulder attached while you do it :&ndash;)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[El Camino Del Diablo]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/el-camino-del-diablo/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-19T20:40:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/el-camino-del-diablo</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As I have mentioned before, I <em>do not</em> have a second serve.  For nine or more months I worked on a single
serve that was meant to be as close as possible to Federer&rsquo;s flat-ish serve.  That was my model.  I served
it twice.  No second serve, just a first serve served twice.  I failed a lot.  And over time I became pretty
insanely great with that model.  At least insanely great for a 50-year old geezer :&ndash;)</p>

<p>After I managed to have a reasonable serve, which I simply named &lsquo;A&rsquo;, I was willing to consider other serves.
To really get a strong beach-hold on &lsquo;A&rsquo; I ultimately needed a coach (John) and John was very generous with
offering me &ldquo;Other Serves&rdquo;.  Again, none of these are a second serve, they are just &ldquo;different serves&rdquo;.  John
is very scientific and intelligent and pretty much insanely great at teaching people about tennis.  If they
want to listen.  To his insanity.  Which it isn&rsquo;t.</p>

<h2>Serve &lsquo;A&rsquo;</h2>

<p>So as of about March, 2014, I had one serve:</p>

<ul>
<li> A: Full Power Serve.  Hit relatively flatly, arm finishes to my left, and I am right handed.</li>
</ul>


<p>Serve &lsquo;A&rsquo; seems straightforward, and it is.  But serving is anything but straightforward.  Learning to springboard, learning
to handle any kind of toss, and even learning to toss a fuzzy yellow ball&hellip; all of these things seem simple but they aren&rsquo;t.
So &lsquo;A&rsquo; lets you worry about things other than &ldquo;How do I hit thee?  Let me count the ways!&rdquo;.</p>

<p>For quite a while, I refused to learn a different serve because I didn&rsquo;t really get &lsquo;A&rsquo;, so didn&rsquo;t want to be distracted by
something different.</p>

<p>But one fine Friday, I said the fateful words, &ldquo;John, I am ready to learn another serve&rdquo;.  That was the birth of &lsquo;B&rsquo;&hellip;</p>

<h2>Serve &lsquo;B&rsquo;</h2>

<p>My serves are simply &lsquo;in-order&rsquo; alphabetically, but sometimes coincidences occur.  Serve &lsquo;B&rsquo; is also my &lsquo;Ballistic&rsquo; serve.
It is an insane serve from John, and witnessed by me when I said &ldquo;I am ready&rdquo;.  To serve &lsquo;B&rsquo; you have to let the fuzzy
yellow ball fall <em>behind</em> you.  And by behind you, I mean <em>way behind you</em>.  You are still headed forward but that ball is going
backward.</p>

<p>And you are patient right?  You must be patient!  For eventually that ball will be behind you enough to hit &lsquo;B&rsquo;.  &lsquo;B&rsquo; is hit up
into the air and it lands in the service box (if you are so lucky) and bounces&hellip;. and is never to be seen again.  At its best
&lsquo;B&rsquo; leaves the court after that bounce.  One bounce&hellip; one kill.</p>

<p>The crazy thing about great shots is they commonly don&rsquo;t work how you think they do.  To hit a &lsquo;B&rsquo; you don&rsquo;t hit &ldquo;up&rdquo; at all.  &lsquo;B&rsquo;
is among the crazy slice family.  You put incredibly amount of spin on a ball, and because of its position, that spin does
incredibly things to a ball.  As I mentioned, <em>you</em> are going forward.  Ignoring the movement of your racket, as long
as you are going forward, you will impart forward kinetic energy to the ball.  Effectively <em>your body language</em> hit the
ball into the service box.  Now your racket is free!</p>

<p>A freed racket is a marvelous thing, and &lsquo;B&rsquo; takes that freedom to solely produce &lsquo;kick&rsquo;.  The ball lands&hellip; it &lsquo;kicks&rsquo;&hellip;
it is gone!</p>

<p>Returning a &lsquo;B&rsquo; is a different topic, but understanding a &lsquo;B&rsquo; is a gateway to understanding the insanity of &lsquo;slice&rsquo;.  Which
is incredibly awesome!!!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[La Ti Da!]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/la-ti-da/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-12T20:40:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/la-ti-da</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A simple organization around doing any physical activity is:</p>

<ul>
<li>Form: The maneuvers of your body, muscles, joints, etc. that you use to cary out the activity</li>
<li>Fitness: How strong and fit you are at doing the above form</li>
<li>Timing: How you do things at the right time to be successful (or better) at the activity</li>
<li>Mentality: What you think when doing the activity (beyond Form and Timing)</li>
</ul>


<p>This post is specifically on the third of the above: &lsquo;Timing&rsquo;.  How do you get the right timing for the various
strokes and activities you have in tennis?</p>

<p>In music, being aware of timing is basically innate to both you and the activity.
You can use a metronome to produce a consistent &lsquo;beat&rsquo;, and you can easily
hear the different speeds.  Percussion instruments (which include the Piano), are
the most obvious of all the musical instruments.  And this obviousness almost
certainly makes timing easier (on the one hand) and more awesome (consider a drumline or a great pianist)
on the other hand.  Tennis players do not have the awesome timing of a great drummer.
Or do they?  And if they do, how did they get it?</p>

<h2>Grunt! or Ha!</h2>

<p>The answer to awesome depends on what you think of service returns and rapid volleying.  I will
tend to stay with service returns as I consider them to be the most visibly awesome aspect in
tennis, and I believe I can produce visuals to help describe &lsquo;what is going on&rsquo;.</p>

<p>To start at the beginning, I will start with the simplest of timing.  When do you hit the ball?  How do you know?
There are two good answers:</p>

<ul>
<li> I know because I just saw me hit the ball – I was watching it</li>
<li> I know because I heard the ball hit the racket – I was listening to it</li>
</ul>


<p>Of these, the first is a little more reliable: light travels faster, and background noise does not impede it.  Strangely though,
the route to great timing is more likely based on the latter: our brains are very sound-timing oriented compared to
our vision.  If sound entered your ear/s only 30 times per second, you would be <em>very disturbed</em>.
Your brain doesn&rsquo;t like that.  Your brain works with sound <em>much faster</em> than 30 times per second, and it is
very good at telling the distance between those sounds (that distance-between-sound is basically the definition of &lsquo;pitch&rsquo;).</p>

<p>So although it is import to watch the ball, and your brain does work with the information, ideally you would always
have both &lsquo;I can see it&rsquo; and &lsquo;I can hear it&rsquo;.  If the ball made no sound when it hits your racket, simply make the
 sound for it.  In my case I &lsquo;grunt&rsquo; when I hit a ball at my fullest.  But when I am playing softer, I say/think something
 like &lsquo;Ha!&rsquo;.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t actually think &lsquo;Ha!&rsquo; because I have a different word, but John recommends &lsquo;Ha!&rsquo; and so I do too.  John is a better
coach than me :&ndash;)</p>

<h2>A! Ah!</h2>

<p>OK, so you watch the ball as you hit it with your racket, and you made a &lsquo;Ha!&rsquo; at the moment of contact.  That is kind of the
start to awesome timing, but not really.  There is no &lsquo;time&rsquo; involved, just a moment-in-time.  We need &lsquo;time&rsquo; to get &lsquo;timing&rsquo;.</p>

<p>To get the most basic form of time, you need two moments.  The &lsquo;Ha!&rsquo; is the second moment: you hit the ball.  Not much more to do than
that on that current ball (although maybe&hellip;)  So you need the first moment&hellip; the &lsquo;A&rsquo; moment. But let us call it the &lsquo;Ah!&rsquo; moment.</p>

<p>So now we have a nice timing pair:</p>

<ul>
<li> Ah!  – ?</li>
<li> Hah! – Contact</li>
</ul>


<p>If the Hah! is Contact, what should the Ah! be? Turns out there are lots of choices&hellip;</p>

<h3>Ah! the bounce</h3>

<p>You can &lsquo;Ah! the bounce&rsquo; before contact.  This is among the most basic (and also the most powerful) &ldquo;Ah! Hah!&rdquo; pairs.
The bounce is basically the last easily determined moment in time before contact.  By getting the feel of the following variations,
you open yourself up to both some interestingly powerful shots (e.g. on the rise off the bounce) and also start
yourself down the path of insane reaction times where the &lsquo;dot&rsquo;s below are ticks at 30 ticks per second or even 120 ticks per second!</p>

<ul>
<li> &ldquo;Ah! &hellip;&hellip;&hellip;&hellip;. Hah!&rdquo;</li>
<li> &ldquo;Ah! &hellip;&hellip; Hah!&rdquo;</li>
<li> &ldquo;Ah! &hellip; Hah!&rdquo;</li>
<li> &ldquo;Ah! . Hah!&rdquo;</li>
</ul>


<p>If you can get your brain and body to do these variations with a dot representing 1/120th of a second, you can likely return
any professional&rsquo;s serve.</p>

<h3>Ah! the hit</h3>

<p>You can also choose to &ldquo;Ah!&rdquo; the contact (the &lsquo;hit&rsquo;) of the &ldquo;opponent&rdquo;.  This is way earlier than the bounce, but the big
advantage is that you are now <em>clearly tracking that ball</em>.  You have made sure your brain and eyes are paying attention
and can start moving your body where it needs to move (both feet and hands).</p>

<p>Now let&rsquo;s take this up a level!</p>

<h2>La Ti Da!</h2>

<p>Simply combine the two above with a simple rename</p>

<ul>
<li> La – The Hit</li>
<li> Ti – The Bounce</li>
<li> Da – Contact</li>
</ul>


<p>If you have seen me return serve at my best a few months ago (April 2014), that is what I was doing.  And I could <em>totally crush</em>
many serves that seemed to others to be almost un-returnable.  But bit by bit my &lsquo;ticks&rsquo; became faster and faster and by &lsquo;Ti&rsquo;
I was in position and the &lsquo;Da&rsquo; was sending a decent serve back at the net man (or the space in the center) at a nice 100+ MPH
pace.</p>

<p>Get your &ldquo;Ah! Hah!&#8221;s and your &#8220;La Ti Da!&#8221;s into your head and your game&hellip; and you will become much better very quickly.</p>

<h2>Don&rsquo;t take my word on it.</h2>

<p>Some captures from high-speed video to show the idea.</p>

<h3>Ah! Bounce, Hah! Contact</h3>

<h4>Ah! Bounce</h4>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/LaTiDa_20140912a_f3_w779.png"/></p>

<h4>Hah! Contact</h4>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/LaTiDa_20140912a_f4_w779.png"/></p>

<h3>Ah! Hit, Hah! Contact</h3>

<h4>Ah! Hit</h4>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/LaTiDa_20140912a_f2_w779.png"/></p>

<h4>Hah! Contact</h4>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/LaTiDa_20140912a_f4_w779.png"/></p>

<h3>La! Hit, Ti! Bounce, Da! Contact</h3>

<p>Switching to &ldquo;La Ti Da!&rdquo;</p>

<h4>La! Hit</h4>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/LaTiDa_20140912a_f2_w779.png"/></p>

<h4>Ti! Bounce</h4>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/LaTiDa_20140912a_f3_w779.png"/></p>

<h4>Da! Contact</h4>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/LaTiDa_20140912a_f4_w779.png"/></p>

<h3>Fa! Toss, La! Hit, Ti! Bounce, Da! Contact</h3>

<p>And to help you beat me <em>now</em>, I use something closer to this as my model.</p>

<h4>Fa! Toss</h4>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/LaTiDa_20140912a_f1_w779.png"/></p>

<h4>La! Hit</h4>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/LaTiDa_20140912a_f2_w779.png"/></p>

<h4>Ti! Bounce</h4>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/LaTiDa_20140912a_f3_w779.png"/></p>

<h4>Da! Contact</h4>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/LaTiDa_20140912a_f4_w779.png"/></p>

<h4>And the result :&ndash;)</h4>

<p>By the &lsquo;ticks&rsquo; (30 feet in about &frac14;th of a second), this ball is traveling at about 80 MPH to the net,
so above 90 MPH off the racket against a relatively slow serve.  To confirm the fraction of the second,
if you look at the &ldquo;net man&rdquo; (his name is Tuan&hellip; he is <em>very</em> fast), he has barely moved by the time the ball passes the net.
The server has not moved at all between the two frames.</p>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/LaTiDa_20140912a_f5_w779.png"/></p>

<h2>Summary</h2>

<p>The core of the idea is &ldquo;Ah! Hah!&rdquo;.  This enables you to leverage your natural auditory and mental timing capabilities to get
your physical timing right.  Right can be &ldquo;warmed up&rdquo;, &ldquo;match ready&rdquo;, or &ldquo;on a new level&rdquo;.  Try it.  It&rsquo;s insanely great :&ndash;)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What does the fox wear?]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/what-does-the-fox-wear/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-04T20:40:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/what-does-the-fox-wear</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As part of doing <a href="http://insanelyGreatTennis.com/">Insanely Great Tennis</a> for the local pros of Palo Alto,
I came up with the idea of pitching a franchise to <a href="http://google.com/search?q=SharkTank">Shark Tank</a>.  To
pitch a television show, you need a picture of yourself.  I had my standard Linked-In profile, but that isn&rsquo;t really
very compelling.  So I augmented my pitch with my tennis outfits, so it is a good time to blog about them :&ndash;)</p>

<p>My outfits came out of two issues:</p>

<ul>
<li> I frequently played tennis after biking (I biked with my kids to school, and then biked some more after).</li>
<li> To play tennis, you need <a href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/lots-of-fuzzy-balls">Lots of fuzzy balls</a></li>
</ul>


<p>Through daily dealing with these two issues came my <em>amazing epiphany</em>: you should play tennis in biking shirts!  And by <em>you</em>, I really mean
<em>you</em>&hellip; as in everyone&hellip;. if you are reading this&hellip; go change your shirt&hellip; and go play some tennis :&ndash;)</p>

<p>Another constraint on my tennis outfits and clothing in general is that I do not want to think about clothing very much.  So
I have suits.  My primary suits involve a red shirt and black pants.  Sometimes I swap in a black shirt.  That is it.
Two choices.  Mostly affected by the contents of the hamper.</p>

<p>Below you will see four outfits, which were initially just one, but broadened somewhat when the second and especially the
third came along.</p>

<h2>The Red Fox</h2>

<p>This is the original.  Worn with either a red (&ldquo;Fear the Tree&rdquo;) or black cap.</p>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/IGT_Foxes3_mlf1a2_w720_redFox.png"/></p>

<h2>The Frisco Fox</h2>

<p>This is a fun augmentation to the Red Fox.  There is a picture of the Golden Gate bridge on the shirt, and it promotes
a good local bike shop.  No one (sane) in or near San Francisco actually calls the city Frisco, but my slightly insane
daughter likes to call it that, so this outfit&rsquo;s name is for her.  The hat is an alien-hat which seems to match the
charm of the city too!</p>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/IGT_Foxes3_mlf1a2_w720_friscoFox.png"/></p>

<h2>The Zebra Fox</h2>

<p>The above shirts were the top of the heap until this one came along.  Having a shirt named after you is too awesome to
not wear it.  I need to get this in red though.</p>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/IGT_Foxes3_mlf1a2_w720_zebraFox.png"/></p>

<h2>The Yoga Fox</h2>

<p>This is a fun shirt, but  has just one large pocket in the back, so isn&rsquo;t as good as the ones above for tennis (or for biking either).
This was actually the original &ldquo;biking/tennis shirt&rdquo;, but it has only one rear pocket, so I now
store it as a dry spare in my bag.  For this outfit, I reveal my (lack of) hair.</p>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/IGT_Foxes3_mlf1a2_w720_yogaFox.png"/></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lots of fuzzy balls!]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/lots-of-fuzzy-balls/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-28T20:40:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/lots-of-fuzzy-balls</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I am going to reveal my most incredibly genius complete transformation of the planes of reality&hellip; just for
you!</p>

<p>First some context.  In tennis, you need to hit fuzzy tennis balls.  Sometimes you hit the ball where you want it to go,
and the other person hits it back to you.  That is called a rally.  If all you ever do in your tennis life is &lsquo;rally&rsquo;,
my incredible genius is not meant for you.</p>

<p>But in certain circumstances in tennis, you either (a) don&rsquo;t hit the ball where your partner is, or (b) you or your
partner don&rsquo;t really hit the ball well at all.  So if either of these happen to you, you need to either go chasing after
that wayward ball, or have a brother/sister-ball easily available.</p>

<p>I value my and your time very highly, so I don&rsquo;t like chasing wayward fuzzy balls.  Instead I carry sibling balls with
me to stand in their elders&#8217; place: primus, secondus, &hellip; septimus, and onward.  Wait did I just say &lsquo;septimus&rsquo;?  That is
seven right?  Nobody carries seven balls!  Well, except me.  And as of today, I will teach you to as well.</p>

<p>The tennis industry is a bit backward.  Men are allowed to maybe carry four balls, plus one in their hand if they have a
single handed backhand (Hah!).  Women are apparently still meant to torture themselves with various bizarre &ldquo;stashes&rdquo; or
equipment just to carry one ball out-of-hand.  The tennis fashion industry is clearly seriously demented.</p>

<p>So look elsewhere for salvation.  Where?  Biking!  Yoga!  Walking!  All these other industries can make tennis more fun and
functional for you.</p>

<p>If you are a &lsquo;guy&rsquo; (or &lsquo;dude&rsquo; or &lsquo;mensch&rsquo; or an awesome woman who is also flexible with her clothing), you can actually acquire
some Fila or similar
tennis pants.  Later I will let you know what should be under those pants (and no, it isn&rsquo;t &lsquo;underwear&rsquo;&hellip; and no, it isn&rsquo;t
&lsquo;commando&rsquo; either&hellip; but that is a different topic for a differnt day).  OK, so you have pants that can now carry four balls.
Huzzah!</p>

<p>Now for the seven.  Well, actually, the dozen!  Instead of buying a silly tennis shirt, go buy a 3-pocket biking shirt.
These shirts are both totally suitable for tennis, and by having <em>three</em> pockets, they can carry <em>six</em> balls.  Four in the
pants, six in the shirt, and two in your left hand.  With one in play, you have a baker&rsquo;s dozen.
Burdened with a two-handed backhand?  Terrible penalty!  You are down to <em>ten</em> balls plus
the one in play.  A &ldquo;two-handed dozen&rdquo;?</p>

<p>Playing with ten to a baker&rsquo;s dozen balls is a very different experience.  Much more time hitting with your partners.
Much more productive and less chase-y.  And totally
suitable for <em>serving</em> without having the overhead of a ball-hopper.</p>

<p>You are the ball hopper!</p>

<h3>Women</h3>

<p>If you are a woman and don&rsquo;t want to buy men&rsquo;s clothes to get pockets (Tennis industry dementia), apparently LuluLemon and likely
similar clothing lines are happy to provide 2-4 ball pockets in their pants and skirts.  So go buy them and tell your
local tennis shop that &ldquo;I went elsewhere because tennis clothes are &lsquo;obsolete&rsquo;&rdquo;.  That might get the manufacturers attention!</p>

<h3>My Outfit</h3>

<p>I was going to post my outfit today, but I think I will save that for a blog
&ldquo;What does the Fox wear?  The Supersonic Fox wear?&rdquo; ;&ndash;)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dress Your Wall!]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/dress-your-wall/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-25T20:40:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/dress-your-wall</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You may have been playing with your <a href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/first-partner">first partner</a> for quite some time now&hellip; but
have you thought at all about how they feel?  I assume you are playing in some kind of tennisy outfit: shirts and pants, dress,
skirt, maybe sweats, etc.  But all this time your partner has been <em>naked</em> hasn&rsquo;t it?  All this time&hellip;</p>

<p>We need to fix that, for your first partner is not at their best when they are naked.  And for you to get
better, you need all your partners to be at their best.  Even if they are Serena or Federer (which would be awesome!)</p>

<p>Your poor naked wall may look something like this:</p>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/CIMG2509_w1728_q5.jpg"/></p>

<p>That is not nice!  At least make sure it has basic attire:</p>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/CIMG2510_w1622_q5.jpg"/></p>

<p>And if you want to really doll it up, get some tagger to help you do this:</p>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/CIMG2509_w1728_q5_v2.jpg"/></p>

<h2>Targeting</h2>

<p>Just like you had targeting rackets for your serve, you need targets on the court for the rest of your shots.
We will discuss on-court targeting later, but with the wall, you need reference points and goal targets.  The squares
can serve as both.</p>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/CIMG2509_w1728_q5_v3.jpg"/></p>

<p>The standard way is like the simple red square: use a bit of masking/painters tape to make a square.  It can be big (the red square is a bit big)
or even just a &lsquo;visible dot&rsquo;.  You can have concentric squares, circles, triangles, or whatever shape you love the most.  But
don&rsquo;t hit against a bare wall if you can avoid it.  Get some kind of reference point up there and put up some kind of goal/s.</p>

<p>Now get them targets!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[That was good!  Now try this!]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/that-was-good-now-try-this/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-24T20:40:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/that-was-good-now-try-this</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My coach John is <em>amazing</em>! If I had my current mentality plus John when I was 18, Federer and McEnroy would both be scared of me.</p>

<p>John is an insanely positive kind of coach&hellip; you can do good, but you can&rsquo;t do wrong by him.  You can just
learn new things that will make you better.  John and I seem to be connected at a level that is a bit unusual, but
his positiveness is not a critical aspect of our connection.  But it may be critically important to you!</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>One of the critical things to John (IMHO) is that &ldquo;no shot is wrong, it is <em>at worse</em> the wrong shot at this particular point!&rdquo;.
An example of this idea, is that hitting shots into the double&rsquo;s alley is only &ldquo;wrong&rdquo; if you are not playing doubles.  So don&rsquo;t
convince your body that the amazing shot you just hit is wrong <em>universally</em>, just remind your body and your mind that you need to
only hit that particular shot in &ldquo;Doubles!&rdquo;.  Just call &ldquo;Doubles!&rdquo; and a &ldquo;bad shot&rdquo; has become a great shot!  No, it doesn&rsquo;t
change you single&rsquo;s score, but your body and your mind now know that &ldquo;That was a wonderful shot!  For Doubles!&rdquo;</p>

<h2>Into the net</h2>

<p>The main area where I and John diverge are &ldquo;into the net&rdquo; shots.  Yes, it is <em>possible</em> that in a particular <em>position</em> that
my <em>into the net</em> shot might actually clear the net and do something useful.  Yes, all that is possible.  But I choose to
simply say &ldquo;No!&rdquo; when my shots go into the net.  Go long!  That is fine.  I can either be further back or swap in a higher-control
racket.  But I say &ldquo;No!&rdquo; when my shots go into the net.</p>

<p>John would likely say &ldquo;That was good!  Now try this!&rdquo;  And that is why John is an amazingly better coach than me.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Crush or eat the Donut!]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/crush-the-donut/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-20T19:40:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/crush-the-donut</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A donut is when you have won no games.  You have a zero vs. the opponent&rsquo;s who-knows-what.  In normal set play,
your zero is going against their goal of winning six games.  Being 0-5 on your serve is not a lot of fun,
unless you think it is!  And then the only right attitude is: crush or eat that donut!</p>

<p>Today I was playing with a good player, and after a good first set, given work-timing constraints,
we decide to play a &lsquo;bonus&rsquo; four games.
Two for his serves, two for mine.</p>

<p>He went first and I was fiddling/practicing my serve and failed to fiddle well enough the first pass through.
So as of my last service, it was 0 serving 3.  Giant DONUT!  I don&rsquo;t like having donuts, but I don&rsquo;t care about
them today against my able opponent.  I care about them at Wimbledon &ldquo;tomorrow&rdquo; when they will be against Federer or Nadal.
Seriously!</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>So I have this big, giant, gargantuous, donut facing me!  And what do I do?  I serve the biggest, giantous, gargantuous-ness
serves I could possibly do.  My first &ldquo;second-serve&rdquo; is an ace!  And through and through, the vorpal racket went snicker-snack.
That game it was on.  No donut for me.</p>

<p>By being prepared to lose, I was similarly prepared to be something better.  Progress through failure.</p>

<p>I could have easily won <em>any</em> of my serves today by holding back, to leverage my particular skills.
But to beat Federer, I have to <em>progress</em>.  And today, I did that vs. a donut.  And tomorrow, so should you.</p>

<h2>USTA is a bit clueless</h2>

<p>On the same day as the above, I received amongst the silliest emails I have received in my life.</p>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/USTA_image.png"/></p>

<p>If winning vs. being awesome isn&rsquo;t important to you, just play against a bunch of gophers.  Bill Murray will enjoy the company.  You might
win, but those gophers are quite wiley!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fourth Partner]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/fourth-partner/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-19T19:40:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/fourth-partner</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>During the late summer and fall of my transformation, I encountered a couple problems.</p>

<ol>
<li> I couldn&rsquo;t really practice &ldquo;real volleys&rdquo;</li>
<li> I couldn&rsquo;t regularly practice &ldquo;real groundstrokes&rdquo;</li>
</ol>


<h2>Real Volleys</h2>

<p>The problem with &lsquo;Real Volleys&rsquo; is that good volleys are meant to end a point.  Being at net puts you in great control and
great peril at the same time.  If you have control, you must use it.  To win!  Practicing with a friendly human partner,
it is somewhat &lsquo;not nice&rsquo; to end the point every time they hit a ball to you.  It makes you feel guilty, and until you
can hold almost a dozen balls (more about that soon), it makes practice sessions very much about picking up balls.  If you
are playing with a human partner, I recommend you &lsquo;win&rsquo; on the third ball.  Two back to them, and after that you do whatever
it takes to win.  And they do the same.</p>

<p>Trying to do &lsquo;Real Volleys&rsquo; against a wall is not realistic either.  Too predictable.  Hard to tell what shot you actually made.</p>

<p>The ideal partner for &lsquo;Real Volleys&rsquo; is a Lobster!  Or a similar high-end, random-capable, ball machine.  Don&rsquo;t buy a ball machine
if you are 4.x+ that isn&rsquo;t random-capable.  You will outgrow it almost instantly.  Good for kids and beginners, but not for you.
If you outgrow your first partner (the wall), you need a partner with some modest level of braininess.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The ball machine I bought is a <a href="http://www.lobstersports.com/products/Ball_Machines/Battery_Machines_Model_Comparison/el04.htm">Lobster IV or V</a>,
and the random capability of the machine enabled me to get my volleys into shape, and crush me at the base line (back then, not now).
Very cool.  The ball machine sometimes has issues and certain limitations (can&rsquo;t serve to me), but if you can afford it or borrow
it from me, it will make you a better player.</p>

<h2>Real GroundStrokes</h2>

<p>The problem with playing against a wall with real groundstrokes is that eventually the equation is not solvable.  Or at least
not &lsquo;normal&rsquo;.  You hit a ball at the wall, and you have to immediately return it!  Like you were teleported to the opposite side
of the net to receive your own ball.  Up to a point, this isn&rsquo;t so bad, but when my backhand &lsquo;blossomed&rsquo;, it was <em>impossible</em>
for me to return my own shot with that little time.</p>

<p>Again, a ball machine helps with this.  The Lobster can feed a ball every other second, which is quite fast, but isn&rsquo;t the
insanity of returning your own shot.  And you can adjust timing to be whatever rhythm your play level is at.</p>

<h2>Fiscal Reality</h2>

<p>I realize that you may not be able to afford a ball machine.  Don&rsquo;t sweat it if you can&rsquo;t!  Eventually your &lsquo;second partner&rsquo; (people)
will be all you need.  I don&rsquo;t use my ball machine <em>at all</em> anymore, because my partner-friends are much better than it.  And
they are quite a bit more fun to play with.  So a ball machine might help for a time, but it is not critical and your three other
partners (who I believe are all &lsquo;free&rsquo;) will be all you need.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Targeting Rackets]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/targeting-rackets/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-16T19:40:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/targeting-rackets</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Continuing with the targeting rackets, we had this:</p>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/IMG_9222_h1224.jpg"/></p>

<p>Which is meant to make you look at the court a bit differently.  More like this:</p>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/IMG_9222_h1224_mlf1a1.png"/></p>

<p>Whether you are very consciously aware of it or not, if you repeatedly focus on that racket (the square) and serve,
eventually your mind and body will understand all three green lines <em>and</em> the height of the net.
You will know the shape of the target, how to reach it.  Nice little diddies of &lsquo;Over the net and into the corner&rsquo;
will play deep inside your head.</p>

<p>If you don&rsquo;t use this technique, you will likely have &lsquo;randomness&rsquo; issues.  Not random as in ball-tosses being a bit
unpredictable.  But randomness as in you being unable to land things reliably inside that box.  No amazing curves over
the net, or straight down the middle.  You won&rsquo;t know where you are and where your target is.</p>

<h3>The racket is a lie</h3>

<p>If you study the picture a bit more closely, you will realize the racket is irrelevant.  The actual target for me
is that pole <em>behind</em> the racket.  Between baseboard and windscreen.  The racket wasn&rsquo;t there when I served the
other day, I put it there to explain the idea.  The racket is a very temporary crutch.  Use it until you don&rsquo;t
need it, because you have a pole (very convenient) or some less convenient way to target the same location.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Another way the racket is a lie, is that I don&rsquo;t even faintly target the racket (or the pole).  They are a reference.
You target them to say &ldquo;I acknowledge you are a reference&rdquo; but with an actual toss in an actual game, they are not
usually a very good target.</p>

<h3>Onto Doubles</h3>

<p>You serve doubles in a different location from singles.  For me, doubles is all about &lsquo;feeding&rsquo; my net partner.  I serve,
you return, into my partner, and she crushes you.  Very simple and sweet :&ndash;)</p>

<p>But besides the rhythm being quite pleasant, the serve location start and target is different.</p>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/IMG_9223_h1224_mlf1a1.png"/></p>

<p>We have moved out wider on the baseline, basically to the singles sideline.  And to compensate, we are now targeting
the next pole over through our (totally awesome 1980x Head Professional) targeting racket.  Note that we are still basically
targeting the same &lsquo;vector&rsquo; end.  The corner of the service box.  That may just be my peculiarity, or maybe John wanted
it that way, but it isn&rsquo;t very conscious, it just showed up in the pictures that way.</p>

<h3>Shades of Gray</h3>

<p>If you move wider, move the target to the left.  If you are somewhere between center and the singles&#8217; sideline, find somewhere in between
the &lsquo;known&rsquo; targets that seems a reasonable trade-off (ratio).</p>

<h3>The other side</h3>

<p>Yes, the other side (the advantage court) works exactly the same way.  Have fun!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Third Partner]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/third-partner/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-14T05:40:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/third-partner</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Now that you have <em>many</em> <a href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/second-partner">second partners</a>, it is time to introduce
your third partner.  Unfortunately your third partner is as socially inept as your first, but
it is much better at one thing: giving you feedback on your serve.</p>

<p>Some people do serve to their <a href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/first-partner">first partner</a>, but the information you get
back is not very useful.  And the wall is missing a number of critical things that I and John (my coach)
think you should be learning.  The only advantage that the wall provides vs. your third partner is
balls come back to you, so you don&rsquo;t need very many balls at all.  Later I will solve
that problem for you and enable you to carry almost a dozen balls!</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Your third partner is the tennis court itself without anyone on the other side.  Serving is a very solitary thing.
You don&rsquo;t need a partner, an opponent, or any spectators.  You just need you vs. the court.  Serving is all
under <em>your</em> control, so blot out all the rest.  Improve your serve week after week and you will someday be a terror
to many of your opponents.  Acing people tends to deflate their egos!</p>

<p>OK, so to serve you stand on the baseline and hit the ball over the net right?  NO!  Go back a couple blogs and find <a href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/model">your model</a>,
and then watch how they serve.  You can change models for your serve vs. other strokes.  Heck you can have a different model for each
stroke.  But you <em>must</em> have a model.  Try to copy the model, and as you do, your individuality will emerge.  And emerge with
an <em>awesome</em> serve vs. a &lsquo;that is what everyone does&rsquo; serve.</p>

<h2>I am not a coach</h2>

<p>OK, so you are watching your model, imagining you serve like that, and maybe you have a coach/instructor that can give you feedback.
You are on your way, and can merrily skip to the next blog entry if you are content.</p>

<p>If not content, read on, but remember, I am <em>not a coach</em>.  At this point, I will be relaying
things that work for me, or were told to me by John.  But what John tells me is different from what John tells other students,
so I have no idea if what I am going to relay to you will be useful to you.  But it will at least show the thought and later the
originality that goes into having an awesome serve!</p>

<p>My model for serving is Federer.  Or at least it was when I started and before John started tweaking me.  Federer has an
amazing serve when he is <em>on</em>.  Very fast.  Very controlled.  He has a flat and a topspin.  Tends to use the topspin for his
second serve.  And there is tons of video on him serving.</p>

<p>I wanted Federer&rsquo;s serve.  Or the closest I could get to it.  And that <em>is all</em> I wanted.  Month-after-month I would practice this serve.
On my own, I got better and better.  Finally with John, I started to clinch it: I had an amazingly fast (for a club player) flat serve.
Today I clocked it at 85MPH to the net.  That means it likely left my racket (40 feet earlier) at over 100MPH.  Crazy!</p>

<p>You can&rsquo;t learn to serve like that in one blog entry, so this entry will be about &ldquo;The Court&rdquo; and your relationship to it.  This
is from John, so it is fairly &lsquo;recent&rsquo; to me but it was months ago.  Nicely it involves pictures :&ndash;)</p>

<h2>Targeting Rackets</h2>

<p>If you look at a court from the baseline it looks something like this:</p>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/IMG_9219_h1224.jpg"/></p>

<p>That is actually incredibly <em>un-useful</em>.  Don&rsquo;t look at the court like that ever again after today.</p>

<p>With one image, I will send you on your way.  Here we go:</p>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/IMG_9222_h1224.jpg"/></p>

<p>What!  There are rackets in the net!  Who left those things there?  Well, John and I put those things there, and next to
the racket in your hands, those are the most <em>awesome</em> rackets on the planet!  At least to you.</p>

<p>As you can see, there are two rackets.  Why two?  Because one is for singles (the left) and one is for doubles (the right).
If you consider the picture, we are clearly standing near the center of the court, and so are likely playing singles.
For singles, you position the &ldquo;target racket&rdquo; approximately 3.5 racket lengths from center.</p>

<p>So do something like that on your third-partner and now try to hit that racket!  Look at it before you start your service motion.
Stare.  Then start.  Then hit or don&rsquo;t hit that racket.  That part isn&rsquo;t actually very important.  That racket
is your <em>bearings</em>.  It reminds you &ldquo;I am in a singles position&rdquo;, &ldquo;I am serving in the deuce court&rdquo;, and &ldquo;That court has a
particular shape relative to that target racket&rdquo;.  That is all.  But for the fun of it, keep trying to hit it.</p>

<p>If you do, you will find it very unrewarding :&ndash;(  Because the ball comes back to you :&ndash;/</p>

<p>(To be continued)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Second Partner]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/second-partner/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-14T05:40:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/second-partner</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Again, what I mean by &lsquo;Partner&rsquo; is someone who plays tennis with other people.  Your <a href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/first-partner">first partner</a> is very reliable but
not very communicative or varied.  Given a particular shot from you, they always do the same thing.
So we should augment your first partner so you have a bit more diversity and a bit more social interaction.  But you also want
reliability.  So who should your second partner be?</p>

<p>Ideally, you are in a nice tennis community.  Very social.  Very inclusive.  Not terribly serious.  Lots of tennis being played everyday.  If you
are, your second partner will be a bit better than if you are in a less active or less inclusive community.  If you are in the Palo Alto area, simply go to <a href="http://tennispaloalto.com/">http://tennispaloalto.com/</a> to see what social and inclusive meetups are
occurring near you.  If you are somewhere else, try to find out that information from your local tennis shop, library, etc.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>But onward to the &lsquo;second partner&rsquo;.  Who should your second partner be?  It should be <em>anyone playing</em> at the same time as you
who could possibly hit with you.  I am a 5.0, and if you see me serving at Mitchell (I wear red on top, black on the bottom),
please come by and ask to hit with me.  Whether you are a 1.0 or a 6.0, I will hit with you and I will do my best to make
it fun for you and for me.  Similarly if you are a 6.0 or something less, you should be happy to hit with a 1.0 through 6.0 (or Federer
or Serena if either of them stops by).</p>

<p>Hitting precise shots is not easy!  Hitting at 30MPH within the hit range of a 1.0 is not easy.  Pushing the 1.0 to move a little more,
to handle a bit of speed, to handle a bit of spin, and so on, all without making them frustrated, this is true tennis control.</p>

<p>Surviving 90+ MPH ground-strokes is also not easy.  But any <em>real player</em> who claims to be 4.0+ can hit you 30,40,50,60,70,80,90 MPH
on each and every shot.  Or if they can&rsquo;t, they should be <em>striving</em> to do so.  And making the rally fun for both of you.</p>

<p>So whether it is a person serving who could have a real partner (empty courts aren&rsquo;t very communicative either), someone with their
first partner (a wall), someone who&rsquo;s partner recently wandered away and may have some more energy, or a three-some needing a fourth, &hellip; just go ask &ldquo;would you
like to hit?&rdquo;  At worse they will say no, and you can either ask someone else or go to your first partner who will never say &lsquo;no&rsquo;.</p>

<p>Some people are jerks.  They will say no when they should say yes.  Some people have different goals.  Every couple weeks I ask
&lsquo;David&rsquo; to hit and he always says no.  He apparently uses his first partner to meditate.  It makes me a little sad, but I
understand.  The jerks I don&rsquo;t, but I just let them go.</p>

<p>To be great at tennis you have to be open to improving (even fanatical about it), understanding, and willing to let things go.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Trust or Replace]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/trust-or-replace/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-10T05:40:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/trust-or-replace</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have two trainers now.  One is my &ldquo;Tennis Coach&rdquo; (John), and one is my &ldquo;Physical Trainer&rdquo; (Steve).  They
are both awesome and focus on different things for me.  John is getting me to play better by mostly focusing on technique,
and Steve is helping me play better and not injure myself by mostly focusing on my muscles and conditioning.  Steve is
relatively new to me, but we have had one evaluation session, and one real session.  So by this point, I can guess where
things are going :&ndash;)</p>

<p>An important thing about trainers, coaches, and mentors, is you have to <em>trust them</em> and <em>do exactly as they say</em>.  You need
to leave your ego at the door.  You are not the coach.  You are not the trainer.  You do not know what to do, or if you are
so sure of yourself, just walk back out of that door.  And stop wasting your money.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>So John tells me to do something, and as long as I <em>can understand</em> what he is telling me: I do it.  There are times I think
John is completely nuts.  But I do his nutty thing.  And 2-3 days later, I realize he is not nuts.  I was the one with a
blocked Chakra, a box, or some other limiting concept in my head (see <a href="http://slumsofpaloalto.com/">http://slumsofpaloalto.com/</a> for background).</p>

<p>After about four months of this, I no longer think John is nuts.  And I do the same actions I did before, with a slightly
less nutty flavor to them.  You can think your coach is nuts, but don&rsquo;t replace them until you think they are <em>not helpful</em>.
John is insanely helpful to me.  He will not soon be replaced.</p>

<p>Steve is different in one regard.  Steve doesn&rsquo;t seem to be nuts at all.  He seems completely driven and skilled at making
me into the best muscular and coordination machine I could be.  What Steve tells me to do may seem nuts to other people
(&ldquo;throw this medicine ball through that wall&rdquo;), but our insanities align and I <em>want</em> to do exactly what he tells me to do.
It seems totally sane to me, so I do it.  He says JUMP, and I say HOW HIGH while I jump as high as I can imagine me capable
of jumping.  And then he shows me how to use a few additional muscles or a better technique and I jump higher.  I will not
be replacing Steve any time soon either (thanks Melinda! and Ashley!).</p>

<p>Again, listen, do, think nuts or not, do more, and repeat.  Or replace.  Very black and white.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Progress through failing]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/progress-through-failing/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-08T05:40:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/progress-through-failing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After I wrote the first version of <a href="http://slumsofpaloalto.com/">http://slumsofpaloalto.com/</a> (the MVB), my aunt sent me a very interesting article.
It was about &lsquo;Focus&rsquo; and two mildly successful people: Bill Gates and Warren Buffet.  You can read it <a href="http://qz.com/231907/why-bill-gates-and-warren-buffett-are-so-successful-in-one-word/">Here</a>.</p>

<p>Accidentally, this posting will do the same thing with the word &lsquo;Progress&rsquo;.  &lsquo;Progress&rsquo; is both <a href="http://www.google.com/search?q=Progress+definition">a verb and a noun</a>.
And for you to succeed with the noun &ldquo;Make progress&rdquo;, you must succeed with the verb &ldquo;Progress&rdquo;.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>And what are you going to progress through?
Failing of course (see <a href="http://slumsofpaloalto.com/">my book</a> for lots more info about success through failing)!
You don&rsquo;t want to avoid failing, you want to fail a lot.  And then progress through it so you can start failing
at something else.  Day after day, fail after fail, onward to Wimbledon.  Seriously.</p>

<p>And you can leverage your incredible advantage over Federer and Nadal: I doubt you make any money from tennis, so winning
shouldn&rsquo;t really be at all important to your livelihood.  And more radically: it shouldn&rsquo;t be at all important to you, PERIOD!</p>

<p>If you want to be great, you will happily lose pretty much <em>all the time</em>.  You won&rsquo;t be throwing the match.  That is silly.
You will constantly <em>play your best</em>.</p>

<p>So why are you losing?  Or to change pronoun.  Why am I always losing?  For more than a year, I have played tennis and almost
always lost my serve.  I consider it almost bizarre to win my serve.  I do commonly win matches now because certain parts of
my game are so good that they really don&rsquo;t fail.  If I am not serving every other game (i.e. playing Doubles), I actually do win a
fair amount now.  But it is effectively <em>in spite</em> of me failing so much.</p>

<p>Finally, the punch-line.  I fail so much because I am always practicing <em>my best game</em> and this is also commonly <em>totally new and
difficult</em>.  For nine months I tried to serve like Federer.  Failed a lot.  By month nine, I had a decent 90 MPH serve.  Not
totally reliable, but definitely decent.  So I had progressed from being a 3-ish kind of player to being a 4-ish kind of player.
Definitely &lsquo;made progress&rsquo;.  Awesome right?!</p>

<p>A week later, my serve was notably &ldquo;less winning&rdquo; (you might call it &lsquo;worse&rsquo; but that would be incorrect).
I could barely keep it in the court.  I could barely land my feet properly.  And this was all John&rsquo;s fault&hellip; and all my
fault.  Lots of fault to blame the faults on ;&ndash;)</p>

<p>What happened?  I was going for a 100MPH serve.  I had a 90, wanted 100.  That required a couple tweaks to my service motion
and it took me a week of practice to get those pieces in play.  When I headed for 120 MPH, my motion was so big that it
took me almost a month of daily practice to get it.  I have it now (the motion if not the 120), and lo and behold today
is my day with John.  And he tweaked me again.</p>

<p>So I am constantly failing and losing because I am <em>constantly practicing</em> the strokes I need <em>for Wimbledon</em>.  I may never
go.  I may never make it.  But when I play a game with you, I am treating you like Federer, and playing a game that could
potentially beat Federer.  Or at least the best game I possibly can.  The best game I could ever have given where I am today.</p>

<p>So that is why I fail a lot but have also progressed a lot.  Failing to beat Federer is not a particularly bad thing.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Need to be slow to be fast]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/need-to-be-slow-to-be-fast/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-04T05:40:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/need-to-be-slow-to-be-fast</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>About nine or ten months into my transformation, I was hitting serves and ground-strokes at about 90 MPH.  &ldquo;What!&rdquo;
Yes, really.  You can ask my partners, but more objectively you can ask my Go Pro Hero.  The Go Pro is a
wide angle, 120 FPS, video camera.  It has other abilities too, but for tennis, this particular mode will
be the most important for you.  If you don&rsquo;t have a Go Pro Hero, try to borrow one from someone, or stop
by my courts and I will tape you.</p>

<p>Again, about ten months in, I had video confirming the 90 MPH speeds.  Of course, if I am serving at 90 MPH the
obvious question is &ldquo;How do I serve at 120 MPH?&rdquo;  At least, that is the obvious question to me :&ndash;)</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>So I asked my coach John, how do I serve at 120 MPH and he told me to do four new things.  One involved holding
my racket looser, which I actually applied to every stroke.  My racket is floppy in my hands now, significantly
aided by a tacky Tourna-Grip wrap.  But the other three things involved my coiling my body in a way that even
this morning caused me to pant.  Just practicing it involves so many muscles in my body that I feel completely
spent every time I do it.  I now serve beyond 100 MPH, and maybe I reach 120 on a good serve.</p>

<p>But this post isn&rsquo;t about that, it is about the other side of a 100 MPH serve.  It is about being incredibly <em>slow</em>
to be that incredibly <em>fast</em>.</p>

<p>In previous posts, I mentioned that you are trying to convince your body that tennis is a critical part of
its survival.  That is definitely true, but at the same time, you are not trying to actually <em>harm</em> your body.
It is on your side.  You need to take care of it.  Very good care.</p>

<p>So wear sunscreen :&ndash;)</p>

<p>But also recognize that your body is probably not innately comfortable traveling at 100 MPH.  To produce a 100 MPH
serve or ground-stroke, your racket has to be traveling at 100 MPH.  Yes, the racket head is a bit further out than
your palm, but not by that much.  So your palm is traveling at basically 100 MPH (say you now hit 120 with your serve)
and your elbow a bit slower, and you shoulder a bit slower, etc.  But to be simple, lets just assume <em>everything</em>
is traveling at about 100 MPH.  That is a lot of speed.  And more importantly, that is <em>a lot of energy</em>.</p>

<p>For me, I feel it mostly in the shoulder.  The rotater cuff is a crazy complicated and impressive set of muscles.
Pitching softball a few years ago, I mangled it a bit, but have apparently recovered since then.  But now in
tennis, I am in constant communication with this set of muscles.  I serve at 100 MPH+ and I am asking these muscles
very politely to <em>keep my arm attached</em>.  I would like the ball to go to the other side of the court and my arm
to stay on this side.  And I recognize this is no small request on my rotater: that arm is traveling nearly 100 MPH
and those shoulder muscles are keep that arm attached.</p>

<p>The next section may seem &ldquo;extreme&rdquo;, and if you are under 25, feel free to do whatever you want with your body.
But remember I warned you :&ndash;)</p>

<p>So back to our bodies.  You need your body to travel at 100 MPH without tearing itself apart right?  You can do this,
but just do it very slowly.  Using serving as an example, my preparation for serving has been getting slower and slower
as my serving has been getting faster and faster.  I can take me 15 to 30 minutes to be ready to serve now, where before
I would just walk up to the line and wail on that ball.</p>

<p>During these 15 to 30 minutes, I:</p>

<ul>
<li> Toss the ball many times, to different &lsquo;quadrants&rsquo; surrounding my body.  If you looked down from about, quadrant &lsquo;1&rsquo; is your front right, &lsquo;2&rsquo; is your front left, and so on.</li>
<li> Do a tai-chi like swinging of my racket as a continuous motion around my body.  If you hit 100 MPH, you need to make sure you don&rsquo;t need to <em>stop</em> the 100 MPH energy.  The flow of your racket should be able to slowly dissipate the 100 MPH.</li>
<li> Alternate tossing the ball and seeing its blur, with swinging the racket and seeing its blur.</li>
<li> Do very lazy serves of just one part of the service motion (say a top-spin &lsquo;helicopter&rsquo;) but by this point my racket is contacting the ball, so my wrist is feeling it.</li>
<li> Practice the three-plus dimensional coil, using the fence to provide resistance and feedback</li>
<li> Start a fuller service motion, but don&rsquo;t take it very seriously</li>
<li> Take it a bit more seriously</li>
<li> Practice hitting balls over the far fence with my &lsquo;A&rsquo; (pure power, most natural flow) serve</li>
<li> Then start working through the actual serves</li>
</ul>


<p>As you can see, the above is not a small list.  By the time I am hitting balls over the far fence, my body is ready for the 100 MPH, but
there are at least six bullets before that.  Those bullets didn&rsquo;t seem very important to me for nine months, but now they are
critical.  I rarely skip any of them, and when I skip some I am trusting that my routine the day before made that skipping
&lsquo;safe&rsquo;.</p>

<p>You don&rsquo;t have to have exactly the same bullets as I do, but I definitely recommend you figure out what yours are.  My arm
is still attached to me, and I would like yours to be too.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Model]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/model/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-28T05:40:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/model</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Previously I said I could provide nothing to help you determine &ldquo;What should I actually be practicing?&rdquo;  That
was a lie, but it was important to get out of the way: <em>you</em> are responsible for what you should be practicing.
Coaches, friends, random strangers, and so on can suggest things you should be practicing.  They may be right
or wrong (I have had a lot of unsolicited suggestions in the last year, some of which were actually useful),
but you must practice, so it is up to you to decide &lsquo;what&rsquo;.</p>

<p>I still don&rsquo;t have a lot of insight into &lsquo;what&rsquo; you should be practicing, but based on the last year, I do
have one piece of advice: Pick a Model.</p>

<p>Pick some pro in the top 500 of men or women who you want to be like.  Then imagine you play like them.  Start
studying their playing style, look at slow motion of their strokes, imagine that your muscles worked like theirs.
And practice <em>that</em>.  Twelve hours a week (or more&hellip; or less).</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>My Model</h3>

<p>I picked Federer.  It was kind of a no-brainer (given his rank), but I picked Federer when he was &lsquo;down&rsquo; and no
longer #1.  The reason I picked Roger Federer is that he played how I wanted to be able to play.  It was as simple
as that.  The second reason I picked Roger is that there was <em>a lot</em> of
high speed film of him.  So there was a lot of information about <em>how</em> he hit the ball from baseline through
serve.  Actually, I couldn&rsquo;t care less how Federer volleys: I have a touch game where my volley is basically innate.
I earned my volley through 18 years of work in my youth, so I don&rsquo;t actually watch or think about it at all (except <em>to think</em>
about it: they hit, I hit, watch ball, hit ball, see it hit your racket, don&rsquo;t look where it is going).</p>

<p>So Roger had the game I wanted, and had the videos of the game I wanted, but the last thing Federer had was something
he <em>didn&rsquo;t have</em>.  Federer has no talent.  That might sound like a slam against him, but it is actually the opposite.
Federer has a game <em>he completely deserves</em>.  He built himself into being able to play that game.  It isn&rsquo;t his
naturally gifted game: I hear he had that too, but that isn&rsquo;t what he plays with.  He has a game that he wanted, created,
and then executed on.  It is a &ldquo;Game Plan&rdquo;, and as long as his &ldquo;no talent&rdquo; isn&rsquo;t totally alien to &ldquo;my body&rdquo;, I can
copy him.</p>

<p>When I left tennis John McEnroe was the icon of tennis.  But McEnroe is the opposite of Federer: he is insanely, innately,
talented.  Or if not, he has created a tennis game that is simply <em>not copyable</em>.  I have seen youth try and fail.
I have seen them try and injure themselves.  Try, try, try, and fail, fail, fail.  Failing is not bad unless
success is impossible.  In my opinion, copying McEnroe is impossible.</p>

<p>But copying Federer is not.  At least one person did it (Federer himself), and the rest of us can do it too&hellip; if you
want.</p>

<h3>Your Model</h3>

<p>You need to pick your model.  Feel free to pick Federer, but feel free to instead pick Serena, Rafeal, or anyone else in the top 500 who
makes you feel awesome.  &ldquo;If I could play like that, I would feel awesome!&rdquo;</p>

<p>And then start watching them, and start thinking &ldquo;How could I play like that?&rdquo;  &ldquo;What would my strokes look like?&rdquo;</p>

<p>Now you have the &lsquo;what&rsquo;.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
