<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[The SuperSonic (Tennis) Fox]]></title>
  <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-04-06T18:00:10-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://supersonicfox.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mark Fussell]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[GMS Tennis: April 8th]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/gms-tennis-20150408/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-06T20:40:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/gms-tennis-20150408</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Blog entries with the title &ldquo;GMS Tennis&rdquo; are specifically for the tennis team at Girls Middle School.  Others
might find the materials interesting too, but this is a different flow from the main blog.</p>

<h2>What To Bring</h2>

<p>For the first meeting, everyone should try to acquire a racket that they like reasonably.  If you don&rsquo;t have a racket,
GMS has some you can try.  I also have a couple spares that might have the right size grip.</p>

<h2>What We Will Cover</h2>

<p>The first meeting will start off with meeting each other, finding the courts, and some quick Tennis-related
introductions.</p>

<h3>Timing</h3>

<p>After that, we will start working through &lsquo;Timing&rsquo;.  Learning timing is a major part of getting good at any sport and
is especially true for Tennis.  Besides some specific timing things to work on, we will more generally focus on
timing tools which you can use to learn and improve many different tennis strokes.  If you want a quick overview
there is one at (see <a href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/la-ti-da/">http://supersonicfox.com/blog/la-ti-da/</a>)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lore and Lies and Limits]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/lore-and-lies-and-limits/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-07T20:40:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/lore-and-lies-and-limits</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Tennis has much lore that is simply incorrect.  It may have applied when players in the royal court played in England,
but it has nothing to do with modern tennis.  Unfortunately it is still taught and some tennis players will spend
their lives playing &lsquo;not tennis&rsquo;.</p>

<p>Tennis also <em>needs</em> lots of lies.  They aren&rsquo;t really sincere lies, they are short-term &lsquo;fibs&rsquo;.  They make you think about
tennis the right way, but eventually the lie has to be revealed because you can&rsquo;t get better by believing the lie anymore.
When I played in Indian Wells, I encountered one of the lies head-on, and needed to let it go or I couldn&rsquo;t get any better.</p>

<p>The particular lie was that tennis serves are hit &lsquo;up&rsquo;.  You are short.  The net is tall.  You must hit up to get the
ball over the net.  This lie is very much true for a long time in tennis.  At 60MPH it is true.  Without a jump serve
that gets the racket three meters off the ground, it is true.  But as your serve speed and height increases, it is a
lie.  If you could shoot bullets off your racket, you clearly can not aim &lsquo;up&rsquo; or the bullet would never land in the
vicinity.  No, if you are shooting bullets, you must aim &lsquo;down&rsquo;.  Your service motion is &lsquo;up&rsquo; but the angle of your body
and your racket compared to the court must be downward.  Or that ball is never coming down in time to get into that service box.</p>

<p>What angle downward?  Well, right above the net kind of downward.  And the actual ratio is seven-to-one (one meter fall/rise for
every seven meters forward), and the angle is a bit downward at 82 degrees.  So basically your body needs to angle inward a few degrees,
and then you hit &lsquo;up&rsquo; at the ball, but it comes off your racket neither up or even flat, but downward.  If the ball bounces
off the racket differently from 90 degrees, you may have to compensate even more.</p>

<p>The angles are not important, what is important is you can control the range.  You <em>must</em> be able to hit the tape with
your serve and your racket.  Even a few inches below the tape.  Putting all the energy you have into the serve: you are
not de-powering to land this serve.  You can&rsquo;t win Indian Wells by de-powering to fix a problem, you must control your power.  Then depowering
is a timing tool, not a crutch.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Losing at Indian Wells (2015)]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/losing-iw-2015/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-02T20:40:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/losing-iw-2015</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I landed in Indian Wells after a ten hour commute on Friday, February 27th.  I was expecting to spend the weekend
getting used to the courts and finding people to play with.  Unfortunately, the weekend didn&rsquo;t work out that way,
and this helped contribute to a very rapid demise on my part on Monday.  To continue to perfect my &lsquo;draw&rsquo;, I believe
Chase (the #1 seed, 150-ish in the world) asked to have two matches on the same day&hellip; or maybe someone else in our
subtree did.  Either way, instead of two days to go long (beat #150) or go home, this was all set up for Monday morning
and afternoon.</p>

<p>Arriving on Friday (night) helped me get very comfortable in Indian Wells by the end of the weekend.  I met the people running the tournament on
Saturday, tested out the courts twice (morning and afternoon), found a good local tennis shop, and found food and coffee
to nourish me.  There were two problems though:</p>

<ul>
<li> No other challenger showed up on Saturday to the courts, so I had &lsquo;no one&rsquo; to play with.  I offered to play with a club player, but he apparently got scared of &ldquo;my level&rdquo;</li>
<li> It started raining on Sunday.  I sacrificed some of my Wimbledon balls to the rain on other courts (IW is very protective of their courts), so I got two workouts on Sunday.  <em>But</em> I could not use the ATP balls I bought on Saturday.</li>
</ul>


<p>So when the courts dried just-in-time for my 9AM match on Monday</p>

<ul>
<li> I had never played with the ATP balls</li>
<li> On the IW courts</li>
<li> With a serious player</li>
</ul>


<p>Chase was annoyed by this as well, as he apparently also thought it was a good idea to &lsquo;warm up&rsquo; for a couple hours and
acclimate to the courts you were about to play matches on.  I wasn&rsquo;t annoyed but next time I would be much more concerned.</p>

<h2>ATP Men&rsquo;s Tennis Balls</h2>

<p>As soon as I started warming up with my partner (opponent), I was shocked.  My strokes were missing the court.
I don&rsquo;t mean missing the line&hellip; the ball was coming off my racket with so much energy, I was hitting the fence!
Apparently ATP Men&rsquo;s Balls (women play with more normal balls) are significantly more bouncy/efficient than any
tennis ball I had ever seen before.  So if I was trying for sixty feet, the ball was going seventy.  That is a lot of change.
My opponent was a local (lived there and had warmed up others in the Paribas challenge the year before) and this was &lsquo;normal&rsquo; for him.  He
wasn&rsquo;t particularly amazing (really just one serve&hellip; not super fast or nasty&hellip; decent ground strokes&hellip; no real net
game) but he was definitely comfortable.  I was incredibly uncomfortable.  Not unhappy or angry or anything, but very
surprised.  And unable to adapt.</p>

<p>My normal approach to adapting to a too-hot game are pretty simple:</p>

<ul>
<li> Swap in slower and spinnier equipment</li>
<li> Try to &ldquo;Go Rafa&rdquo; and spin the ball more, reducing the pace a little</li>
</ul>


<p>The first just couldn&rsquo;t do the trick at all.  It is meant to deal with a couple-feet-long issue, not ten foot long.
And it turns out the first and the second combined approach &ldquo;produce more spin&rdquo; actually doesn&rsquo;t work either with these ATP
balls.  I will describe the issue in another article in depth, but the quick summary is that given the ball efficiency,
more spin was causing more speed at the same time.  Yes, if I hit a lot slower I could do it.  But that is simply death
at this level of play.  I needed to hit at different angles (especially for my serve), and I do not normally adjust
that.  And so I never thought to adjust it at IW.  Must have faulted 75% of the time, where I rarely fault more than
20% of the time normally.</p>

<p>I controlled almost every ball in the match.  And managed to make unforced errors on pretty much all of them.  Well,
actually, I was getting better in the second set, but I was simply &ldquo;too stupid&rdquo; and &ldquo;too slow&rdquo; to adjust in time.</p>

<h2>Preparing for IW 2016 and other tournaments</h2>

<p>So IW was an incredibly efficient learning environment.  I did watch Chase play next to me, so I have some feel for a &lsquo;150&rsquo; player,
and I learned about things that could vary (balls) more than I ever expected, and I learned I need more control points
to adjust within my game.</p>

<p>I brought back the ATP balls I bought on Saturday and have been on the court three times in the last 36 hours with them, and
now I adjust my service angle (how far forward the toss), target the service line on ground strokes more, and am
working on a dozen
other things that may help me with IW 2016 and other professional matches.</p>

<p>Oh, And I plan to study the weather more carefully before I head to a venue :&ndash;)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Draw for PNB Paribas Indian Wells Challenge]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/the-draw/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-25T20:40:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/the-draw</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I received the ladder for the Paribas challenge yesterday.  It is basically &ldquo;perfect&rdquo; for me,
so unless I get injured or sick, I have little to complain about.  First, I hit the #1 seed (ranked 151 in the world)
on the second day.  So basically go long or go home.  If I lose, I come back and try to make some money the good old
fashioned way.  If I win, I will have confirmation that I should keep going and the monetary loss/risk is at least
&lsquo;sane&rsquo;.</p>

<p>Second, there is only one match a day.  And for me (at the top of the ladder), those are always in the morning.  So
I can work the rest of the day with a possible practice in the afternoon to keep sharp.  But I don&rsquo;t have to deal
with nasty sun beating down on me.</p>

<p>Finally, there are enough NorCal locals that I can try to get a group of us set up even if I completely blow the
tournament.  I have given myself &lsquo;two seasons&rsquo; to make something happen or to ramp back down.  If I blow Indian Wells
this year, I get one more try.  The ultimate failer sport :&ndash;)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tennis: The ultimate delusional sport]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/ultimate-delusional-sport/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-14T20:40:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/ultimate-delusional-sport</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Continuing the &lsquo;competency thread&rsquo; (see <a href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/being-competent/">http://supersonicfox.com/blog/being-competent/</a>), this issue has come much
more to the foreground lately.  Apparently rumors and spectators have taken notice of my insanity and I get people
that visit and watch, or visit and play for ten to twenty minutes, or even those that play with me regularly, who
then chime in about &ldquo;Your just a 4.x&rdquo; or &ldquo;I played with him and I can beat him&rdquo;.  Now until I get my ATP or USTA
official rank, I can&rsquo;t deny these to be possibly true.  But I am pretty sure they are not.  Later I will explain
why it is hard for lower level players to have any ability to recognize a higher level player unless they are <em>very
 open-minded and very perceptive</em>.</p>

<h2>The ultimate delusional sport</h2>

<p>The problem with tennis is that it is basically a &lsquo;small tank&rsquo; sport.  There are lots of little groups of tennis
players who rarely play outside their group.  Do they go to Stockton for that tournament?  No.  Play any of the
opens?  No.  They play in their town or nearby, and they play at the <em>lowest</em> level they can possibly play.  USTA
will kick you up, but not too far.  And worse, they won&rsquo;t kick you down.  So you played 4.0 one year and are a 3.5
now, but still playing in the 4.0 league.  So it is no longer a 4.0 league just from that problem.</p>

<p>Plus, you don&rsquo;t get compared to other 4.0s in the nation.  There is no &ldquo;4.0&rdquo; rank.  It is a level, and it is specific
to your community.</p>

<p>So a lot of 4.0s are not, a lot of people who played in college think they are much better than they are
(thousands of people played in college).
And people who play matches daily think that the time invested makes them amazing.</p>

<p>So lots of people think they are big fish, but they are in a tiny tank, and they are minnows in the real tanks.</p>

<p>This &lsquo;small tank&rsquo; problem affected me when I was young: I played at school and in clubs, and I was &lsquo;good&rsquo; and striving to be #1 on my school&rsquo;s team.
But then two delusion-fixers came through my life: first was a tennis camp from Florida.  Yes, a <em>Real</em> tennis camp for would-be professionals.
Within the first day it was clear that I was not good.  And I worked on trying to catch up to them&hellip;. worked really hard&hellip; and got closer at least.
The second was Patrick who played the 16-under and 18-under tours, and when he joined my high school, the chance of being #1 was
forever stripped from me because he was on a completely different plateau.</p>

<h2>How not to spot a 5+ player</h2>

<p>If you are a 4.x player, you may think you can spot a 5+ player easily.  But there are issues.  For one, a 5+ player
who is playing with you is playing at least one if not two levels beneath them.  This is not challenging.  At least
not if you play it without constraints.  Even with constraints it is still a social activity.  Imagine you were playing
with a 2.x.  What would you do differently?  Would it be obvious to the 2.x who is playing with you that you are a 4.x?
And by playing with a 2.x, I mean <em>all the time</em>.  There are no 4.x to play with.  For this to be fun, you have to
put on various constraints most of the time.</p>

<p>A list of constraints I have placed on myself include:</p>

<ul>
<li> Must play in singles even when in doubles</li>
<li> Must serve my nastiest serve even when it isn&rsquo;t landing properly</li>
<li> Must not kill the net player or anyone who is at net</li>
<li> Must not take advantage of players being out of shape, having no backhand, no ability to return lobs, etc.</li>
<li> Must hit it <em>to</em> the other player vs. away from them</li>
<li> Must not serve the serves that wins against you after I have determined what they are</li>
<li> Must work on all my shots even when most are thoroughly un-needed against you.</li>
<li> Must work on open stance backhands, left handed forehands, incredibly hard shots that can &lsquo;win&rsquo;, etc.</li>
</ul>


<p>Up until yesterday, pretty much all of these were in force, and with them in force, I am probably a 4-ish kind of
player (will &lsquo;tie&rsquo; a 4-ish player in one set, likely win in three, and definitely win in five because I am in better shape
and all the above constraints become irrelevant as my game becomes &lsquo;hot&rsquo;).  My game would look &lsquo;weird&rsquo;, but the
score would not.</p>

<p>The next way not to identify a 5+ player is by whether they trounce you.  Sure, they could.  It is kind of fun.
But it turns out it is bad practice.  To beat a 4.0 you need to play at a 4.2.  Against a 4.5, you should be a 4.8.
Voila &mdash; you win two sets straight or at least the tail two sets.  This is the way to consistent winning: run faster
than the other player, not the theoretical Tiger (or in tennis, Roger-Rafa pair) who is chasing you.</p>

<p>Why the tail?  Again, a 5+ player doesn&rsquo;t want
to play against a 4.x except for social fun.  And if you are putting in 30 hours a week, you try to minimize the
4.x time because it is sucking up real practice time.  So it is likely that the 5+ player is not used to playing
against certain shots that 5+ players don&rsquo;t have.  Flat serve.  Not likely.  Slow serve.  Not likely.  Mediocre
topspin.  Not likely.  Floaters&hellip; etc.  Recalibrating takes time.  Ideally four games or less, but that can put you at a
handicap in the first set.</p>

<h2>How <em>to</em> spot a 5+ player</h2>

<p>Now for how to spot.  This is more theoretical (I haven&rsquo;t done &ldquo;blind&rdquo; testing with it), but these are suggestions
if you care.</p>

<p>   1 Are they actually ranked&hellip; (duh)
   2 Are some of their shots quite extreme?  Way more power than seems necessary?
   3 Do they have a lot of different serves?  Or did you see one once that was &ldquo;crazy good&rdquo;?
   4 Do they <em>not</em> have any weak strokes?
   5 Are they sweating?  Or maybe not at all?
   6 Do they spend more time practicing than playing matches?  Have you ever asked?
   7 Are they going to tournaments more than sixty miles away?  With cash rewards?
   8 Do they have coaches and trainers?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Winning Indian Wells (2)]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/winning-indian-wells-2/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-01T20:40:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/winning-indian-wells-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the biggest issues I have with winning Indian Wells is that I will be playing against people that
are significantly better than people I play against now.  Tennis, like almost all sports, does not involve your
conscious brain during play.  Or very little of it.  Tennis play is dominated by sub-second reactions.  With
balls traveling at 120 MPH, they are traveling at 2 MPM or 10000 FPM, and finally about 160 FPS.  Although
not this regular, you can think of a tennis court as being divided into four 20-foot sections from end to end.
So baseline to baseline is a half a second.  Net to baseline is a quarter of a second.  Baseline to service is
three eights of a second.  Yes, the times are a little longer as speeds go down, but no matter what you
are sub-second at the professional levels except for defensive lobs.</p>

<p>A half a second is not a useful amount of time to think about something.  You must be leveraging your reactions to something similar
that you have seen before and let your body take over.</p>

<p>When I did a tournament at Stockton, I encountered something I hadn&rsquo;t seen for more than thirty years.  A good
left-handed player.  His shots weren&rsquo;t faster than anything I had seen before.  His serve wasn&rsquo;t stronger.  But
everything was &ldquo;off&rdquo; and I couldn&rsquo;t get my game together against him.  There are a number of causes for this, but
certainly one was that his spins were just &lsquo;different&rsquo; and I was not subconsciously used to them.</p>

<p>So to get ready for Indian Wells, John was nice enough to serve left-handed to me.  And I have an insanely great
ball machine that can serve left handed too.  With exactly four weeks to go, we will see if I can level up
by day-1.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Serving Stage Two]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/serving-stage-two/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-30T20:40:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/serving-stage-two</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I finished discussing the way of the devil with the hell (H) serve.  There are actually a number of serves after the hell serve,
but instead of boring you with lots of serve motion variations, I will bore you with lots of ball positions.  As
I get ready for Indian Wells, I am losing serves.  Most professional tennis players have incredibly dangerous forehands.
You should not hit to them.  Nasty Slice Serve?  Yes, that sets up for a perfect death stroke to your left or right as the right-hander&rsquo;s
forehand picks and chooses.  What rattles a 4.0 and below does not rattle a 6.0 and above.  They will be there and
if they are there with a clean forehand, you have just lost the point.</p>

<p>So, some of my serves like &lsquo;E&rsquo; are gone.  And doing an &lsquo;H&rsquo; on the ad-side is gone.  And my &lsquo;A&rsquo; was always a practice serve.
And a wide &lsquo;C&rsquo; serve on the deuce side is gone.  Overall, I lost about four out of eight primary serves.  If the
opponent is a lefty, I switch some of the losses and end up back at four.  Four serves isn&rsquo;t a lot of serves.
Even if my hell serve, my wide &lsquo;C&rsquo; on ad, and my J1 serve are on the mark every time, my opponent would just get
used to them.  This is not a good thing.</p>

<p>But then John steps in and levels me up.  Serves have a motion, and that motion is usually most easily understood
when you toss the ball in a particular place.  The hell serve is in front and directly above my head.  Slice is way
to the right.  Loopy topspin falls behind me.  But learning a serve motion and using a serve motion are not the same
things.  As soon as you have learned the serve motion, you can use it in many different ball toss situations.  John (and
now I) divide the world into 5+ locations.  Three is above your head.  Two is headed toward your serving arm.  And one
is almost parallel to your head and wider than your shoulder on your serving arm&rsquo;s side. Four and five are basically the
same going away from your serving arm.  And six pushes that even further.</p>

<p>So if I just fell to four good service motions, I now have 3 or 4 ball tosses I can use with each.  And each produces a different
behaved ball.  3H vs. 2H vs. 4H are all different.  2J1, 3J1, 3J2, and 4J2 are all different.  And now that I have
enough variations, I can even keep you honest and throw in a forehand attack.  It might be rare, but you slide or
expect too much, and a 4H or 3E to your forehand will do something very interesting.</p>

<p>I still don&rsquo;t normally use a change-up: where I put different amounts of energy into the serve for timing confusion.
But with sixteen serves, they naturally change up on their own.  And I can always work on that next.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First Partner (2)]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/first-parter-2/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-11T20:40:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/first-parter-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>About a year and a half ago I stopped using my first partner (see <a href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/first-partner">http://supersonicfox.com/blog/first-partner</a>).
Based on a progression of getting more and more powerful strokes, having a decent ball machine, and having good
people to play with, the wall became obsolete.  I was to never need it again.  Or so I thought.</p>

<p>As of last Friday, I now go to the tennis courts twice a day.  I need to get used to Palm Springs weather, I need
to get used to playing twice a day, and I need to practice more just generally.  This is now approaching forty hours
a week, but that is just like any other profession.  It is just strange that you practice a lot (without any monetary
gain) and then compete a little with potentially huge monetary gains.  It makes sense: it is a show.  Just not
like any job I was previously familiar with.</p>

<p>Well, the problem with going to the courts in the middle of the day is that lots of people are on the courts.  So
getting court time is difficult, at least on the weekend.  I visited the courts three days, and on no day did a
court open up.  But luckily the wall was still there.  And it didn&rsquo;t seem mad I had ignored it for more than a year.
I had to have time to myself to get back into the relationship.</p>

<h2>The insanity of a wall</h2>

<p>Hitting against a wall at slower speeds and spins works fine.  At higher speeds, topspin flies upward and underspin
shoots downward.  That would be OK and realistic if it was from the bounce on the ground, but it is actually happening
on the bounce on the wall.  Enough topspin and your ball can hit high on the fence behind you where on court it would
curve inside the baseline.  There is basically nothing you can do about this with a normal wall or likely any other
bouncy surface: having an object in the way is not realistic.  Unless you imagine it is a volley.  Now that makes
sense: volley back from drive.</p>

<p>The second insanity is that the ball comes back way too early and likely too fast.  But again, imagine volley and
the world makes more sense.</p>

<h2>Learning through insanity</h2>

<p>So if the wall is a bit insane, does that make it useless?  No.  But as your racket speeds up, you need to
realize what shots you can really play.  For a couple weeks of returning to the wall, I would do &ldquo;Offense-Defense&rdquo;
hitting.  One shot was a drive, and the next shot was a &lsquo;flick&rsquo; to keep the ball in play.  As I learned to have
more and more compact (but heavy) shots, I could even do &ldquo;Drive-Drive&rdquo; combos.  But that took dozens of hours to
get to the point.</p>

<p>In any case, if you can set up the two ball sequences you have a highly effective and productive environment
to learn within.  No chasing after wayward balls, and no being nice to your partners.  Walls aren&rsquo;t very demanding.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Winning Indian Wells]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/winning-indian-wells/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-10T20:40:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/winning-indian-wells</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I registered for Indian Wells ATP challenger tournament.  If I make it through the challenger, I go through a
qualifier tournament.  If I make it through the qualifier, I get into the main tournament, where Roger and Rafa
will be &ldquo;waiting&rdquo;.  If I beat all of my side of the ladder, I will have either beaten  Roger and Rafa, or will have
beaten the people that beat these Tennis giants.  I will also make quite a bit of money and likely make a bit of news.</p>

<p>I expect to win it all, so this year may be a pretty notable year in my life.</p>

<p>If you have read my writings here and there, you may realize I am not a normal person.  My expectations are lofty,
my abilities bizarre, and my life either a dreamy heaven or a living hell depending on how you look at it.  A lot
of me is not transferable.  You can&rsquo;t just be me.  But this one aspect of me, you can take to yourself like the
transfer of the Olympic flame.  You should expect great things.  From yourself.  And then do your best to make
those great things happen.</p>

<p>I am not sure how those words ring on your ears: &ldquo;You should expect great things.  From yourself.
And then do your best to make those great things happen.&rdquo;  My guess is that you just kept reading along.  But
I didn&rsquo;t write those three sentences for you to read them and move along.  They are a torch.  They are fire.
You should read and repeat them.  Aloud.  Like a Koan.  I will even change the pronoun and structure to make that easier: &ldquo;I
expect {something great} from myself.  And I am now doing {all the things that requires} to make that happen&rdquo;.</p>

<p>This phrase is far more powerful than a New Years resolution.  Because although it could be lofty in its expectation,
it is grounded in its action.  &ldquo;I expect to win Indian Wells, and beat Roger and Rafa.  So I am now playing tennis
forty hours a week in weather similar to Indian Wells&rdquo;.  I am prepared to not win Indian Wells, but I expect to win or
why am I going down there?  I am going to do everything <em>now</em> that I could possibly do to prepare <em>now</em> to win <em>now</em>, or
again, why am I going down there?  If I am under-prepared&hellip; then I need to get prepared&hellip; or i shouldn&rsquo;t go into the
jungle.</p>

<p>This one thought is the difference between professionals and the rest: a true professional expects to <em>win now</em>,
to <em>do now</em>, and is <em>preparing now</em> for what their profession requires.  A professional is a soldier.  Without the
downside.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[One grip to rule them all (2)]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/one-grip-to-rule-2/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-31T20:40:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/one-grip-to-rule-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I mentioned previously (<a href="http://SupersonicFox.com/blog/one-grip-to-rule/">http://SupersonicFox.com/blog/one-grip-to-rule/</a>) that there are basically two grips that
can &lsquo;rule&rsquo; your grips:</p>

<ul>
<li> Continental – Conservative grip that works both forehand and backhand</li>
<li> Western – Aggressive grip that works both forehand and backhand</li>
</ul>


<p>The advantage of the above is not needing to change grips per side.  I believed these were the only &lsquo;true grips&rsquo;
until I spent several days with a two-handed backhand.  And then I realized tennis had gotten everything wrong
about one-handed backhands&hellip; since&hellip; whenever people stopped hitting with a Continental.</p>

<h2>The grips</h2>

<p>If you go to any standard grip reference like <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grip_(tennis)">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grip_(tennis)</a>, you will read about
bevels and what the grips are named.  If you start with a Continental, it is on Bevel #2, and the racket is
perpendicular to the ground if you hold your wrist &lsquo;properly&rsquo;.  The description of the forehands are all correct,
but it leaves off the &lsquo;side-effects&rsquo; of shifting grips:</p>

<ul>
<li> As you move to an eastern and then western forehand, the ideal contact point moves toward the net.

<ul>
<li>If you went the other way (Eastern backhand / bevel 1), the contact point would move backward.  This is not a normal shot, but is good in certain stretch pinches.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li> As you move &lsquo;western&rsquo; the racket is able to whip more and more effectively</li>
</ul>


<p>If you consider these side-effects, you will actually see the insanity that occurred on the backhand and why
one-handed backhands are &ldquo;grip-inferior&rdquo; even when they are &ldquo;flow-superior&rdquo;.  That is why they died.  And by
thinking through the two-handed backhand, I just resurrected them.</p>

<p>Start again with the Continental for the backhand.  This is natural and you hit it from the &lsquo;Front of the Box&rsquo;.  Great
for volleys, and actually fine for top-spin although weaker than some other options.  But for whatever reason
humanity went insane when it decided what to do with a backhand to make it better than the continental (note that a two
handed backhand holds a Continental by default for the &lsquo;forehand-hand&rsquo;).</p>

<p>What humanity did is turn the bevel to #1.  Now consider the side effects mentioned above:</p>

<ul>
<li> As you move to an eastern and then western forehand, the ideal contact point moves toward the net.

<ul>
<li>Our body is turned around, but we are also turning the grip the opposite direction</li>
<li>And I think this should obviously be viewed as insane because it is <em>the wrong direction</em> for spin.  You can&rsquo;t hit spin easily outside the box.  Inside yes, outside, no.  Power yes, Spin no.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li> As you move &lsquo;western&rsquo; the racket is <em>less able</em> to whip</li>
</ul>


<p>An eastern backhand is &ldquo;fine&rdquo; and even scary because you go for a bit more power than a continental has.  For all but the top 20 people in the world, it may not matter.
There are lots of other issues people have, so a bad backhand may not be a problem.  And most people now opt-out and pick a two-handed anyway.</p>

<h2>The right backhand grip</h2>

<p>I have both a one-handed and a two-handed backhand.  Recently I spent several days (so about 15 hours) playing with primarily a two-handed backhand.  The goal was to
get more spin on service returns, which I now can drive but not top-spin (flick).</p>

<p>I have the alternative two-handed backhand grip: I combine two eastern forehands vs switching to a continental with my right hand.  The two-handed was better
than my one-handed at spinny shots.  I studied the motion to get it as &lsquo;epic&rsquo; as possibly and it definitely was crazy what I could do with the ball.
But I hate how &lsquo;tight&rsquo; a two-handed backhand feels, and when I switched back and forth I sometimes got the contact point wrong (one handed is net-side of the front
of the box, two-handed is from the back of the box) so that was frustrating.</p>

<p>Finally, one day (yesterday), it dawns on me that I am hitting my backhand with a different right-hand grip.  That in changing to a two-handed, I changed <em>two things</em> (a) my right-hand grip, and (b) having my left hand participate too.</p>

<p>You should never change two things at once: you don&rsquo;t know whether they both matter, they might cancel each other, etc.</p>

<p>And with this revelation, I found the one true backhand we should have been using since the continental.  It is still an &lsquo;Eastern&rsquo;, but it is an &lsquo;Eastern Forehand&rsquo;.</p>

<p> ## Eastern Forehand on the Backhand</p>

<p> I have not found anyone who officially plays with this (before me), but if you run the analysis you can see it is the right thing to do.  First, just
 the macro statement:</p>

<pre><code>* We turned around (left side for a righty)
* We are hitting on the opposite side of the racket
</code></pre>

<p>The two things <em>cancel</em> each other.  The grips should go in the same rotational direction because of this.</p>

<p>Now consider the side effects:</p>

<ul>
<li> Going toward a western forehand (for your backhand) moves the contact point away from the net

<ul>
<li>And into the middle of the box&hellip;</li>
<li>This is perfect for spin!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li> As you move &lsquo;western&rsquo; (again forehand for the backhand) you are more able to whip</li>
</ul>


<p>You can actually see the craziness of the original grips when you see a western backhand.  The racket is so out of position, it is basically a weird slice: the wrist goes away from the shoulder (slice) vs. the thumb heading toward the shoulder (top-spin).</p>

<p>No, this is not an easy grip to play with.  An Eastern Backhand is easier.  A Continental is easier.  But the Eastern Forehand is the optimal grip for a crazy spin backhand.</p>

<p>So if you want the spin of a two-hander, first try to progress your one-handed grip clockwise.  If that is too hard for you, then do the two-handed thing.  But maybe revisit the one-handed
later in life.  It might surprise you :&ndash;)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What does the fox wear? (2)]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/what-does-the-fox-wear-2/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-27T20:40:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/what-does-the-fox-wear-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Tennis is a major part of my life, but it can not interfere with the &ldquo;normal&rdquo; part of my life:</p>

<ul>
<li> I must make money</li>
<li> I must spend time with my family</li>
<li> I must sleep</li>
<li> I must do a bunch of other crazy things, like write books, teach kids, etc.</li>
</ul>


<p>How I manage this is that tennis normally ends by about 8AM, or sometimes 9:30AM on Saturdays.  But
I have to put in about 20-30 hours a week to keep my game at the level it is.  That is at least three hours
a day, so I have to start about 5AM every day.</p>

<p>There are some flaws with starting at 5AM.  First, it is quite dark.  The sun is rising at almost 7AM now, so
that is two hours of no sun.  At 6AM I can turn on the lights, so I work out for about an hour without much light.
A street lamp lights part of the court, and your eyes adjust to the dark.</p>

<p>The second flaw is that although I can turn on lights, I can not turn on the heat lamps.  Because there aren&rsquo;t any
heat lamps to turn on.  California is pretty temperate by the coast line, so this isn&rsquo;t a big deal most of the year,
but today was &lsquo;notable&rsquo;:</p>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/clothes_20141227.jpg"/></p>

<h3>There is no bad weather</h3>

<p>I believe in the maxim &ldquo;There is no bad weather, just bad clothing&rdquo;, so when I see those numbers on my dashboard I
do the obvious thing: &ldquo;Winter Up!&rdquo;.  Seeing freezing temperatures when thinking &lsquo;Tennis&rsquo; does not elicit particularly
useful images.  But thinking &lsquo;Winter Sport&rsquo; conjures images of downhill and cross-country skiers, Iditarod sled-teams, and
outdoor speed skaters.  These people can handle the weather, so why can&rsquo;t I?</p>

<p>Due to my ZAST training, handling these temperatures for tennis only required a single piece of equipment.  I already
had Patagonia skiing outer shells, which are fine at about freezing.  A bit colder and I will need a few more heating layers under it.  I have
two-layer gloves/mittens, which can keep my left hand warm-ish.  The only problem was the racket-holding right-hand.</p>

<p>Fortunately, while I was in the local tennis shop (<a href="http://TennisTownAndCountry.com/">http://TennisTownAndCountry.com/</a>),
I asked about gloves, but was redirected to consider a warm &lsquo;tube&rsquo;.  Your
hand goes in one end, and the racket another.  You meet in the secretive and warmer tube-world.</p>

<p>Yes, shifting grips is a bit difficult.  Especially if you play with the super-tacky grip I play with.  But warming
up I don&rsquo;t shift grips that much anyway, so this aligns pretty well: any given morning I am full of hope that I can
take the tube thing off before I have to switch grips on the fly!</p>

<p>:&ndash;)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Targeting (2)]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/targeting-2/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-25T20:40:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/targeting-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Previously I discussed targeting rackets as part of serving (<a href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/targeting-rackets/">http://supersonicfox.com/blog/targeting-rackets/</a>).
The critical part of targeting rackets is to realize you are targeting <em>above</em> the net, not the court itself.  And
it also makes sure you always have a good, repeatable, frame of reference.</p>

<p>The other day it dawned on me that I use this for all shots, and that other people may not.  I don&rsquo;t hit into the net
very much.  I hit the top of the net, and I hit long, but into the actual net?  Not likely after I have warmed up.
How can that be?  Why do I rarely hit into the net, where others do quite often?  Well, I believe it turns out that
it is related to targeting again.  If you look at the following picture:</p>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/targeting_20141225_p1_w1366.png"/></p>

<p>You will see four &ldquo;Court Targets&rdquo; identified.  I am standing in the center of the court on the baseline, and say I
drop a ball to my right-hand forehand or left-hand backhand.  Where am I to target (mentally) to hit &lsquo;CT1&rsquo;?  What
path should the ball take?</p>

<p>Unfortunately, I think a lot of people think this is right:</p>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/targeting_20141225_p2_w1366.png"/></p>

<p>That is unfortunately hopelessly wrong.  Even if the ball shot out of my eye, it is still below the top of the net.
And the ball isn&rsquo;t going to shoot out of my eye.  A normal drop and the ball is about waist high, and about two feet
to my right.</p>

<p>The right picture is this:</p>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/targeting_20141225_p3_w1366.png"/></p>

<p>By targeting the &lsquo;yellow&rsquo; I have now gotten the ball over the net, and by &lsquo;considering&rsquo; the green, I have now dealt
with the parallax issue between my eye and the rightness of the ball compared to my eye.  My eye targets yellow,
but my hit stroke targets green.  And the green line should be the trajectory of the ball.  Makes sense?  If so,
you may now be able to shoot a bow better too :&ndash;)</p>

<p>But wait!  Why the bottom of the windscreen?  That is <em>so high</em>, and the ball will be way over the net.  Well, if
you ever played with me, you will notice my balls are barely over the net.  Like millimeters.  And that is basically
because targeting the bottom of the windscreen is targeting directly over the net.  The second parallax effect is
the difference between your eye and the ball vertically.  A picture from ball height should make that second
perspective crystal clear :&ndash;)</p>

<p><img src="http://supersonicfox.com/images/targeting_20141225_p4_w1366.png"/></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[One grip to rule them all]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/one-grip-to-rule/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-14T20:40:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/one-grip-to-rule</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I hear a lot of &lsquo;chatter&rsquo; about grips when on the court.  People switching between a and b, c and d, forehand and
 backhand.  Never for any particularly logical reason, but just switching all the same.</p>

<p>I play with a classic (1980s) set of grips: Eastern forehand, Eastern backhand, Continental volley, Less-than-Eastern-Backhand
Forehand slice / serve, and finally Eastern-Forehand backhand slice.  Of these, only the last would be a little
unusual / extreme.  I started with a Continental, but my 4500 RPM backhand is partially possible because I am a bit
more extreme than a Continental.  All of these I may slightly tweak to suit my strokes or the specifics of a particular shot.
But they are clearly my core.  I can also do both right and left-handed two-handed backhands, but that is a different story.</p>

<p>A couple days ago I was working on an aggressive topspin lob on my one-handed backhand.  This is among the hardest strokes
 in the game to me.  I can &lsquo;bullet&rsquo; my backhand trivially.  And can topspin the bullet quite easily too.  But getting a
 ball high up in the air with a lot of spin&hellip; that was not happening for me.</p>

<p>At first I cheated and switched to a two-handed backhand.  Actually, ultimately, this cheat may simply be my solution,
but after cheating a bit, I wanted to figure out what was failing with my one handed backhand.</p>

<h2>Forehand topspin</h2>

<p>My forehand was fine, so I switched back to it and thought about what I was doing.  To control any shot, you must be able
to apply full power and go <em>short</em> and <em>long</em>.  Then all you do is dial in the middle.  On my forehand, I couldn&rsquo;t go
really short, but I could lob and hit the service line, which is about as short as you ever want to go with a real shot.
And I could lob into the other court, which is normally a bit longer than you ever want to go.</p>

<p>OK, so this was better than my backhand.  But wasn&rsquo;t as controlled as I wanted.  Why couldn&rsquo;t I go shorter?  Say lob
and have it land <em>on</em> the net.  I pondered and decided it must be the grip.  So I shifted to a western-ish grip.  And
hit some balls.  Really short.  Like straight at my service line.</p>

<p>I pondered Rafa who has the most extreme topspin I am aware of, and I tried to &ldquo;channel him&rdquo; along with &ldquo;his grip&rdquo;.
Now I had something.  Lots of spin.  Not much power, but definitely a lot of spin.</p>

<p>So what was the advantage compared to the backhand?  The grip?  Actually, no.  The eastern backhand is <em>as extreme</em>
as the western forehand for generating topspin.  I will get to that in a moment.</p>

<p>Basically the advantage came down to the <em>stance</em> and <em>ball contact</em> point.  For my normal, driven, forehand, I hit the ball
and my racket goes forward and up, eventually with my thumb passing over my left ear.  For my &lsquo;Rafa&rsquo; forehand, I hit
the ball and my racket goes almost straight up, with my thumb never even passing my <em>right</em> ear.  For both of these, I
use an open stance.  The first doesn&rsquo;t require it, but the second totally does (or so I believe).</p>

<p>My flaw with my backhand is I was trying to do an upward drive with a closed stance.  And basically up isn&rsquo;t really possible
because your should is already in front based on the stance vs. on the side.</p>

<p>So my ultimate fix to my backhand lob was to open my stance.  Or to two-hand it.  The later still is better to date.</p>

<h2>One grip, Two grip</h2>

<p>A tennis racket grip is an octagon (usually), so grips are primarily based on hand anatomy compared to that octagon.
But one grip is easy to describe in more normal vernacular: the continental.  The continental is also called the &lsquo;shake hand&rsquo;, or
&lsquo;hatchet&rsquo; grip.  If you place your tennis racket on a table so it is &lsquo;slicing&rsquo; the table, the continental is simply shaking
hands with the grip.  Your &lsquo;v&rsquo; will be on top, your fore-finger hand-joint will be to the side, and your thumb and finger tips
will touch-ish on the other side.</p>

<p>If you had to pick <em>one grip</em> to use throughout an entire game, this seems like the obvious one to choose.  Everything
is symmetric, so both forehand and backhand can be hit.  Flat is easy.  Slice is easy.  Topspin is a little hard, but
is possible.</p>

<p>One grip&hellip; to rule them all.</p>

<p>Except it isn&rsquo;t the <em>right grip</em> to rule anyone nowadays.  Probably wasn&rsquo;t even right back in the sixties.  But lets not
dwell.</p>

<h3>The true one grip</h3>

<p>I mentioned my grips above, but swapping in Rafa for some of mine, we get:</p>

<ul>
<li> Western-ish forehand, topspin</li>
<li> Eastern backhand, topspin</li>
<li> Eastern-ish backhand, forehand slice</li>
<li> Western-ish backhand, backhand slice</li>
<li> Eastern-ish backhand, serve</li>
</ul>


<p>Isn&rsquo;t the symmetry above a little suspicious?  Now consider that a Western Forehand and an Eastern Backhand <em>are identical</em> grips (just flipped in motion direction)
and we now have:</p>

<ul>
<li> EB-ish forehand, topspin</li>
<li> EB backhand, topspin</li>
<li> EB-ish forehand, slice</li>
<li> EB-ish backhand, slice</li>
<li> EB-ish backhand, serve</li>
</ul>


<p>So the true one grip is the EB/WF grip.  It is the most extreme spin grip.  It is just kind of hard to &lsquo;wield&rsquo; so people
tend to approach it vs. use it.</p>

<p>And why it is both aweful and awesome is simple to see when you describe how to grip it in normal vernacular.</p>

<p>Put your racket <em>flat</em> on a table.  Now shake hands with it.  Now you have a flyswatter vs. a hatchet.  Awesome!</p>

<p>This hold makes it so your default capability with any ball coming toward you (or simply dropped in the air) is to <em>slice it</em>.
On either side of your body (forehand, backhand).  In either direction (forward, backward).  And even on either side of the racket (bottom strings, top strings).</p>

<p>Slice it eight ways baby :&ndash;)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Time dilation]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/time-dilation/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-11T20:40:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/time-dilation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I stand near the service line (halfway) when I return serve.  People find this unimaginable, even inconceivable.
The ball is coming at 120 MPH and you are standing there?!?!</p>

<p>The answer to how I can stand there has two parts, but the first is basically &lsquo;Time Dilation&rsquo;.  Just like computers
do a lot of things in a short amount of time, you too can do a lot of things in a short amount of time.  You just don&rsquo;t
realize it.  You are operating on &lsquo;slow&rsquo;.</p>

<p>The difference between &lsquo;slow&rsquo; and &lsquo;fast&rsquo; is not the effort, energy, or
speed aspects of what a person does.  It is changing the <em>unit of time</em> at which the person does exactly the same
things you are doing on &lsquo;slow&rsquo;.  So the simplest way to think about this is to adjust time to be in equivalent &lsquo;slow&rsquo; units
vs. thinking the person is doing more in a unit of time.  This is exactly how 120 FPS becomes 30 FPS.</p>

<p>For most people, thinking in &lsquo;tens&rsquo; is the easiest.  So imagine I (or maybe Roger) is operating at 10x the speed of you
on the tennis court.  Where <em>one second</em> passes for you, <em>ten seconds</em> passed for Roger.  Where three tenths of a second
passed for you, three seconds passed for Roger.  You can get a lot done in three seconds!  And have a sip of coffee to
boot.</p>

<p>If you want to see the time dilation in action, just slow down the video of Roger to going at 1/10th its normal speed.
I believe you will see <em>continuous motion</em> at that speed.  Or something really close to it.  Now do the same of some
video of your club matches.  And everyone will look &lsquo;frozen&rsquo;.  That is time dilation.  Mages are in continuous motion at
about 10x the speed of muggles.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[In the rain]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/in-the-rain/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-30T20:40:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/in-the-rain</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It is raining in California.  This is a good thing, because we need a lot of water and we don&rsquo;t have it.  The rain causes my internet to go out (another story),
which is actually enjoyable because the internet is a dangerous drug.  Cold turkey the drug!</p>

<p>It doesn&rsquo;t rain very much in California any more: climate change has caused our weather to be &lsquo;nicer and nicer&rsquo;.  Tennis is played outside, so
tennis benefits from this niceness.  It is hard to not be able to play tennis in California (or at least the Bay Area).</p>

<p>You can certainly play tennis in the rain.  Don&rsquo;t play if you start sliding around, but other than that, there is absolutely nothing preventing playing in the rain. Yes,
the balls will get wet and be no longer Wimbledon quality.  Yes, the racket will get wet and you may have to replace the grip or even the strings.  So what?</p>

<p>Well, for most people, even a drizzle makes them go somewhere else.
On my courts, when I manage to get two-three hours in a day (in the rain or between spells), almost no one else shows up at all.</p>

<h2>Better courts after a rain</h2>

<p>If it has recently rained but is no longer raining, you can get your courts (hard courts) in better shape by leveraging the power of the sun.  The sun is <em>really good</em>
at drying things, but it needs &lsquo;to see&rsquo; the water.  Puddles are not good (can see the top but not below), so you should squeegee puddles and spread them around.  You
can also blow things around with an electric blower, mop with a blanket, push with a broom, etc.</p>

<p>If you get the water spread out, it takes about 15-30 minutes for a wet court to be quite playable.  So you can choose your ball-wetness to wait time.</p>

<p>I rarely wait for much of anything nowadays :&ndash;)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Being a Mage]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/being-a-mage/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-24T20:40:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/being-a-mage</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday I documented what an objective camera showed: I have crazy, top-40 professional, levels of spin and speed in my game.  I might be able to make it all the way to the US Open in New York.
I am 48.  I have only played for eighteen months since taking a thirty year hiatus.  I have a full-ish time job doing something quite sedentary (read software).  This is all quite bizarre.</p>

<p>Well, it is different from &lsquo;normal&rsquo;.  I am a tennis mage.  I learned from John, who is also a tennis mage.  John started at 14 when he earned a racket.  Then he VHS taped all the
great tennis that was out there (McEnroe, Borg, Lendl, Everett, Navratalova, etc.), he went to the court and tried it out, and year-after-year he self-taught himself the actual
magic that is required to do crazy things to a fuzzy yellow ball.  He is a self-taught mage.</p>

<p>Eighteen months ago I decided to start playing tennis with my daughter.  For about nine months, I did something similar to John but only watched one pro: Federer.  I would watch
slow-motion captures of his strokes and read/listen-to analysis of what he did so well.  At the end of nine months, I was not a mage but maybe a 4.x player.</p>

<p>But then I met John, and his wisdom combined with my effort and focus enabled me to become a mage too.  Yesterday I both measured my magic and revealed who I was.  And I did it in my &lsquo;Fox&rsquo; shirt :&ndash;)</p>

<p>Yesterday was a ton of fun, but today I was on the court yet again for about two hours starting at 5:30AM.  Why?  Because I love the magic, and need to practice it
and look for new spells everyday.  Today I worked on &lsquo;checked&rsquo; backhands and forehands.  The &lsquo;checked&rsquo; backhand is critical to returning serves targeting your left leg.
John showed me it the other day, and yesterday a 110 MPH serve targeted my left leg and I hit it.  The leg that is&hellip; so I would like to not do that again.  The &lsquo;checked&rsquo;
forehand is just because it is symmetric.  John didn&rsquo;t mention it, but it is natural.  So are &lsquo;checked&rsquo; slices.  The trajectory of the ball comes off the racket differently,
and that may have been helpful against this crazy kid who had wicked topspin.</p>

<p>So being a mage is not an award&hellip; an honor&hellip; it is a state along a journey.  I know magic and I want to know more.  When there is no more, I may be a bit more bored with tennis.  But maybe not :&ndash;)</p>

<p>Being a mage also tends to make you want to pass it on, so I taught a tiny two year old girl &lsquo;La Ti Da&rsquo; to help her catch a tossed tennis ball :&ndash;)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Wilson Spin Clinic]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/wilson-spin-clinic/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-23T20:40:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/wilson-spin-clinic</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I had an awesome time with adults and kids at a &lsquo;spin clinic&rsquo; hosted by Wilson.  Basically they want to show how swapping in one of their newer rackets makes your shots better.
It was interesting to see other people do it (I was helping retrieve balls, so was effectively &lsquo;receiving&rsquo; and watching pretty closely).  The right way to do this is you hit
your kind of normal 70% game speed balls, swap in a new racket, and compare.  I am not normal, but I did try the &lsquo;normal way&rsquo; and swapped in a wilson racket for my best
HeadMP+Strings+57.  Unfortunately for Wilson, their racket was not better.</p>

<p>But again, I was invited to this by Timi and was there to <em>have fun</em> and <em>be helpful</em>.  For the <em>helpful</em>, I provided  music, fresh orange juice, champagne, and a good ball retriever.
For the <em>fun</em>, I did what any mage would do with a machine like that watching them.  I hit my <em>wickedest</em> shots possible off every ball that was hit my way :&ndash;)  And then
wanted to see my stats.</p>

<p>The numbers:</p>

<ul>
<li> Forehand-Topspin: 2500 RPM</li>
<li> Forehand-Slice:  4500 RPM ! :&ndash;)</li>
<li> Backhand-Topspin: 1500 RPM</li>
<li> Backhand-Slice: 3000 RPM</li>
</ul>


<p>And my favorite number:</p>

<ul>
<li> Furthest travel: 140 feet :&ndash;))</li>
</ul>


<p>I also served, but they were packing up and I didn&rsquo;t really get any numbers for it (too many kinds of serves and only five serves as my quota).</p>

<p>Great day.  And I am headed to Carmel for the Prequalifier for the New Haven Qualifier for the New York Open.  :&ndash;)</p>

<p>Thanks to John for the game and to Steve for keeping my shoulder on.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[El Camino Del Diablo (5)]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/el-camino-del-diablo-5/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-22T20:40:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/el-camino-del-diablo-5</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Continuing the road to the devil&hellip;</p>

<h2>Serve &lsquo;H&rsquo;</h2>

<p>Serve &lsquo;H&rsquo; is the serve this series is actually named after.  It is the &lsquo;Hell&rsquo; serve.  It is my first &ldquo;this is only a jump serve&rdquo;,
but to understand that you need to watch &lsquo;Roger Rabbit&rsquo;.  So go watch that&hellip; I will wait&hellip;</p>

<h3>Flow</h3>

<p>The key to all tennis and martial arts motions is &lsquo;flow&rsquo;.  You flow your body through the motions that you want your body
to do.  But it isn&rsquo;t just any-old-flow.  It is a &ldquo;get real fast&rdquo; and &ldquo;woah horses&rdquo; pair.  It turns out that the &ldquo;woah horses&rdquo;
part is the harder part.  Because you don&rsquo;t really want to halt your horses, you want them to just relax.  To slow down on their
own.  Stop being &lsquo;fast&rsquo; and somehow you will get back to some reasonable velocity.  And by horses&hellip; I really mean &lsquo;Joints and Muscles&rsquo;
because I am pretty sure you don&rsquo;t have horses inside your body.  Even if you are a Unicorn yourself.</p>

<p>I can&rsquo;t teach you here how to become slow.  And slow down.  Please seek John and Steve and my other mages if you want to learn that.
But be aware that slowing down is critical to the road.  If you can slow down, basically without brakes, then you are ready to speed up.
Don&rsquo;t continue until then.</p>

<h3>Coil, Spring</h3>

<p>All real tennis serves are jump serves.  You might not see it visibly, but a jump serve is simply a &ldquo;Coil, Spring&rdquo; serve, which
is the ultimate version of &ldquo;flow&rdquo; ignoring the slow down part I addressed above.</p>

<p>To serve a real serve, you toss the ball, and then <em>immediately</em> go get it.  Coil, Toss, Spring.  I tend to say the &ldquo;Coil&rdquo; to myself in a nice low voice.
Not sure what actor I am channeling for the Coil.  But for the &lsquo;Spring&rsquo; I channel Roger Rabbit (you did see the movie right?  If not, please go back to paragraph-1).</p>

<p>So &ldquo;Cooooiiiiilllll&rdquo; , &ldquo;SPRING!&rdquo;.  &ldquo;Cooooiiiillll&rdquo;, &ldquo;SPRING!&rdquo;.</p>

<p>I actually hit some spectacularly bad serves when I start off, because I am not really ready to &ldquo;SPRING!&rdquo;.  But <em>all</em> my serves have this rhythm.  I jump-serve <em>all</em>
my serves.  The only thing that varies is where the ball is.</p>

<h2>Serve &lsquo;A&rsquo; prime</h2>

<p>The value of Serve &lsquo;A&rsquo; (my flat butterfly serve) is that it is simple.  It has a nice continuous flow, so slowing down is not a problem.  That makes it great
for testing new things out.  A-prime is a test of &ldquo;Toss that ball somewhere crazy&rdquo; and &ldquo;Go get it&rdquo;.</p>

<p>If you have a jump serve, the coil puts your body into a jump-capable position.  So, if you toss the ball somewhere &lsquo;stupid&rsquo; you should be able to jump after
it.  And get to it.  If you can get all this timing right.</p>

<p>Again, I can&rsquo;t help you with all the timing, physical fitness, etc.  Blogs and books aren&rsquo;t a good medium, and I haven&rsquo;t taken
enough time to process all my videos.</p>

<p>But the basic concept is: &ldquo;Toss the ball <em>forward</em> about one foot, and then do &lsquo;Serve A&rsquo; given the ball is there&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Doing this with your &lsquo;A&rsquo; serve likely produces a little more speed on the ball and reduces the amount of time people
have to react to the ball.  You are closer to them.  You hit it faster.  Very obnoxious.</p>

<p>But this is basically the <em>same serve</em> as an &lsquo;A&rsquo;, so I don&rsquo;t label it differently.  It is just a more serious &lsquo;A&rsquo;</p>

<h2>Serve &lsquo;H&rsquo;</h2>

<p>The Hell serve is a different serve from all that preceeded it.  It is actually a jumped &lsquo;C&rsquo; (topspin) serve, but unlike a jumped &lsquo;A&rsquo;
this produces something radically different.  Because you tossed the ball so &lsquo;wrong&rsquo; for a &lsquo;C&rsquo;, when you actually hit the ball,
it similarly comes out &lsquo;wrong&rsquo; and is ridiculously flat.  A proper &lsquo;C&rsquo; is a nice loopy serve.  A proper &lsquo;H&rsquo; is flat.</p>

<p>Until it hits the ground.  When all hell breaks loose.  A proper &lsquo;H&rsquo; has all the top-spin of a &lsquo;C&rsquo; but that is concealed in an &lsquo;A&rsquo; like
trajectory.  When an &lsquo;H&rsquo; hits ground, it transforms into a &lsquo;C&rsquo; and worse, and that ball kicks all over the place.</p>

<p>When I learned &lsquo;H&rsquo; I thought I had been given a gift of the nastiest serve on the planet.</p>

<p>But the letters continue&hellip;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Being Competent]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/being-competent/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-21T20:40:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/being-competent</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Continuing my &lsquo;insanity&rsquo; subtopic, or slightly related to it, I am now going to properly define &lsquo;competent&rsquo;, and explain
how you become competent at something, and how long this takes.  The answer may surprise you because it makes complete
sense, but is not how people commonly (incorrectly) define the term.</p>

<p>An important realization is that &lsquo;Competent&rsquo; is <em>completely orthogonal to</em> &lsquo;Skill&rsquo; (independent of, think North-South vs. East-West).
I am a skilled and competent
tennis player.  I may be a 5.5.  Not totally sure.  Will figure that out at the next tournament.  With professional competitive sports
it is very hard to become <em>incompetent</em>.  If you beat Roger, you are #1.  If you lose to him, you probably are not.  If you
can&rsquo;t even <em>see</em> his serve, you are likely a lot less skilled than Roger.  Almost all sports have this wonderful characteristic:
on game day every one is competent&hellip; or simply in denial.  No incompetency at all.</p>

<p>I am also a highly unskilled and competent brain surgeon.  I will not operate on your brain.  Period.  Just not going to happen.
If we are trapped in the woods and I have to chop off you leg to get you out of a bear trap&hellip; I will first warn you that
I am similarly unskilled as a leg-chopper-offer.  I am competent at it, but you are likely to die if you ask me to do it.</p>

<p>With the second example, you can see that being competent takes <em>absolutely no time</em>!  At all.  None.  Phew!  Thought it
was hard.</p>

<p>Ah&hellip;. but it can be hard.  It gets hard to become competent when you are trapped in being incompetent.  To be incompetent probably takes some amount of time&hellip;
you invested a year or two in improving your tennis game&hellip; and during that time you thought your were getting better and better&hellip; you were sure it was the
case.  An hour here and there&hellip; adds up to 100 hours&hellip; over five years, maybe 500 hours&hellip; You put in all time, so you must be &lsquo;Good&rsquo;.</p>

<p>But that is delusional.  You aren&rsquo;t good because your put in time.  One becomes good by progressing through failure.  Over&hellip; and over&hellip; and over&hellip;
Playing 500 hours of club tennis makes you as skilled in tennis as&hellip; have no idea.  But <em>you can</em> figure it out.  Find a 4.0 and play them.
Oh&hellip; they might be incompetent too and are really a 3.0?  Yes.  That is the sad part.  If you get enough incompetent people together,
you have no clue.</p>

<p>That is why I am going to a spin-clinic tomorrow, why I have nine go-pros, and why I am going to a true &ldquo;Kill each other&rdquo; kind of Open in the spring.
Because I know I am not incompetent&hellip; but I have no idea what my skill level <em>really is</em>.  I don&rsquo;t care very much, but I am curious.</p>

<p>Never going to be even a moderately skilled brain surgeon.  Never is enough for that one.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[El Camino Del Diablo (4)]]></title>
    <link href="http://supersonicfox.com/blog/el-camino-del-diablo-4/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-19T20:40:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://supersonicfox.com/blog/el-camino-del-diablo-4</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Continuing the road to the devil&hellip;</p>

<h2>Serve &lsquo;F&rsquo;</h2>

<p>Serve &lsquo;E&rsquo; does not make a lot of sense as an actual serve, but it is highly useful in a game.  If you hit a ball
to me at about should height, you will get a snap serve back.  Basically serve &lsquo;E&rsquo; but with a snap (to be explained later).
Actually, at this point, if you hit a ball to me above my waist-line you may get a snap serve back.  You probably will
not like that&hellip; but I digress.</p>

<p>Serve &lsquo;F&rsquo; is a pure slice.  Again, you must leverage the fact that you are a box and make sure the ball is in the <em>back</em>
of the box and generally a bit higher than your head.  Then you slice it just like you did with &lsquo;E&rsquo;.  Very nice slice.
You must put everything you can into slicing that ball to really see how wonderful a serve this is.  And after you
have done all of that, I will show you more.</p>

<h2>Serve &lsquo;G&rsquo;</h2>

<p>Serve &lsquo;G&rsquo; is among the most fun serves to do as well as the most useless in an actual game.  To do a &lsquo;G&rsquo; serve, your
racket is parallel to the ground.  Yes, facing down.  If you get better it is facing down and <em>backward</em>.</p>

<p>The goal of the &lsquo;G&rsquo; serve is to produce <em>maximum spin</em> with <em>minimal ball travel</em>.  A perfect &lsquo;G&rsquo; does not travel forward
at all.  The ball simply rises up in the air, hits the ground, and goes backward from where you are standing.  You are
slicing the air with your racket, and the ball just happens to be there to feel the slice.  If another person was there&hellip;
well&hellip; they wouldn&rsquo;t be very happy.</p>

<p>As with all serves, you should be able to put everything you have into this serve.  Yesterday I was measured to produce about 800 watts per arm,
and I put 800 watts into Serve &lsquo;G&rsquo;.  &lsquo;G&rsquo; is awesome.  And useless.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
