<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[The Slums of Palo Alto]]></title>
  <link href="http://slumsofpaloalto.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://slumsofpaloalto.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-07T18:22:25-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://slumsofpaloalto.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mark Fussell]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[More 3]]></title>
    <link href="http://slumsofpaloalto.github.io/blog/more3/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-01T16:42:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://slumsofpaloalto.github.io/blog/more3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With a new month, now we start filling in the software-techy aspects of the book.  This isn&rsquo;t meant to be a major thread since I think other threads are more valuable
to more people, but if you are interested in the software / programming parts, these will be woven in as well.</p>

<p>Passed 30K words.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[More 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://slumsofpaloalto.github.io/blog/more2/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-30T07:36:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://slumsofpaloalto.github.io/blog/more2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The raw content of the book surpassed 25,000 words in the last day.  So I added a second &lsquo;<a href="http://slumsofpaloalto.github.io/more2">More 2</a>&rsquo; section to keep
things in manageable size.  A pass at organizing the content has been done as well, so whether the book ends at 50,000 or more
words, it basically has a first full pass at structure and flow.</p>

<p>No agents yet.  I investigated self publishing during the last week, and it certainly seems manageable.  I just rather have someone skilled do what they are skilled at :&ndash;)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[More Samples]]></title>
    <link href="http://slumsofpaloalto.github.io/blog/more-samples/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-24T11:06:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://slumsofpaloalto.github.io/blog/more-samples</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I added a significantly larger set of samples into the &lsquo;<a href="http://slumsofpaloalto.github.io/more">More</a>&rsquo; section.  I did not want to change the samples section itself because
that is meant to be concise.  I may be missing one or two that should be in there (maybe &lsquo;Dissent&rsquo;) to have more diversity, but
it shouldn&rsquo;t just grow as more chapters seem to be &lsquo;possibly interesting&rsquo;.  The &lsquo;more&rsquo; section may grow over time as basically a
sampling of the entire book.  Enjoy!  And thanks for all the encouragement.  Even some of my agent rejections seemed really encouraging.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Site Launch!]]></title>
    <link href="http://slumsofpaloalto.github.io/blog/site-launch/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-21T15:17:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://slumsofpaloalto.github.io/blog/site-launch</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Earlier today I decided that I should have a site for the book.  After doing so many startups, and with some great services out there,
launching the IT (or Infrastructure) of a new company is incredibly easy.  A web site is among the easiest of the infrastructure to
set up.  I purchased the domain name, pointed it at github.io, cloned and customized Octopress, and after a few &lsquo;rake generate; rake deploy&rsquo;
edit cycles, the book proposal and this blog posting were up and alive.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
